<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A treatise of schisme Shewing, that al Catholikes ought in any wise to abstaine altogether from heretical conuenticles, to witt, their prayers, sermons. &amp;c, deuided into foure chapters, whereof 1. Conteineth sundry reasons to that purpose, grounded for the most part vppon scriptures and fathers. 2.Examples out of holy scriptures. 3. Examples out of ecclesiastical histories. 4. Answeres to the chiefe obiections. By Gregorie Martin Licentiate in Diuinitie.</title>
            <author>Martin, Gregory, d. 1582.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1578</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 207 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 94 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A07105</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 17508</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S107013</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99842718</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99842718</idno>
            <idno type="VID">7400</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A07105)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 7400)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 479:03)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A treatise of schisme Shewing, that al Catholikes ought in any wise to abstaine altogether from heretical conuenticles, to witt, their prayers, sermons. &amp;c, deuided into foure chapters, whereof 1. Conteineth sundry reasons to that purpose, grounded for the most part vppon scriptures and fathers. 2.Examples out of holy scriptures. 3. Examples out of ecclesiastical histories. 4. Answeres to the chiefe obiections. By Gregorie Martin Licentiate in Diuinitie.</title>
                  <author>Martin, Gregory, d. 1582.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[180] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Apud Iohannem Foulerum [i.e. W. Carter],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Duaci [i.e. London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1578.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imprint false; actual place of publication and printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: 2* A-K L² .</note>
                  <note>Slight print show-through.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Catholic Church --  Doctrines --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:7400:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:7400:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>A TREATISE OF SCHISME.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Shewing, that al Catholikes ought in any wiſe to abſtaine altogether from heretical Conuenticles, to witt, their prayers, ſermons. &amp;c. deuided into foure Chapters, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of
<list>
                  <item>1. Conteineth ſundry reaſons to that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, grounded for the moſt part vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon Scriptures and Fathers.</item>
                  <item>2. Examples out of holy Scripture.</item>
                  <item>3. Examples out of eccleſiaſtical hiſtories.</item>
                  <item>4. Anſweres to the chiefe obiections.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> Gregorie Martin <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centiate in Diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>DVACI. Apud Iohannem Foulcrum. 1578.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <pb facs="tcp:7400:2"/>
            <p>HIc Tractatus eſt planè Catholi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus, &amp; noſtris imprimis homini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus hoc ſchiſmatis tempore perneceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarius.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Ita teſtor Gulielmus Alanus S. Theologiae Doctor &amp; Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſor.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:7400:2"/>
            <head>¶ THE PREFACE to the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Onſtantius Emperor,</hi> father vnto Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine the great,
<note place="margin">Euſ. de vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta Conſt. lib. 1. ca. 11.</note> offered vnto his nobilitie this Condition, That as many as would offer Sacrifice vnto the Idols, ſhoulde haue both acceſſe vnto his royal perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, dwel in his Court, and haue offices &amp; great honour in the common wealth. They that would not thus doo, ſhoulde haue no acceſſe vnto his perſon, no familia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie with him, ſhould beare no office in the common wealth, but ſhould be ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed the Court, and alſo be depriued of ſuch offices and honours, as preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye they did enioy. Forthwith y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whole Court is deuided in two partes, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the Emperour eaſily might perceue eche mans mind, faith, truth, &amp; religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: for the true Chriſtians were by and by readie humbly to depart, rather the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by tarying to violate their faith for world lye honor. Then Conſtantius opening his ſecrete purpoſe, blameth the diſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling ſort, calleth them daſtardes,
<pb facs="tcp:7400:3"/>faint harted Cowardes, traitors vnto their God, and his truth, and flatterers vnto their Emperour, men vnwoorthy to liue in his ſeruice. For howe wil ye kéepe faith vnto me your maſter (ſaith he) that haue violated your faith vnto the eternal God? ye are co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uicted of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iurie vnto God, howe can yée be true vnto man? The others he commended highly for their co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtancie, pietie, &amp; true faith, he iudgeth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> woorthy to haue rule &amp; charge of earthly thinges, that had ſhewed the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues faithful to God. They are (ſaith he) like to be true vnto their Emperor, that haue ſhewed them ſelues true and faithful to God, he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitteth the cuſtodie of his owne per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to them, the charge &amp; gouernment of the Empire he layeth in their han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, the reſt he did vtterlye baniſhe as pernitious flatterers, turne-coates, and hipocrites. Verily, the fact was heroical, &amp; woorthie the father of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantine, it was the very way to trye true men from flatterers, faithful ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaunts from falſe deceauers. For he that wil not ſticke to violate his faith,
<pb facs="tcp:7400:3"/>his religion, &amp; his conſcience towardes God, for lukers ſake, who can thinke that ſuch wilbe faithful and truſty vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to man? Great therfore is the ouerſight of our dayes, wherein he that can beſt diſſemble, he that can violate his faith vnto God and his Churche, for world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye preferment, is taken for moſt truſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and faithful: he that wil come to the Church, although it be neuer ſo muche againſt his conſcience, he that wil re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue their what ſhal I cal it, although he wiſheth it in his belye that deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth it, is thought to be beſt to be truſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with the greateſt affaires &amp; weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tieſt buſines about the prince. But this good Emperour iudged them vnwoor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie to haue charge about men, that made no conſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce to violate their faith vnto God. But one wil ſay,
<note place="margin">4. Reg. 5. Obiectio.</note> Naaman the Aſſirian was permitted by Elize<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us the Prophet, to goe with the king into the temple where Idolatrie was, and yet neuer impaire his conſcience: euen ſo may we go to the Churche for obedience ſake without hurting our conſcience, or violating our fayth to
<pb facs="tcp:7400:4"/>God.
<note place="margin">Reſp.</note> If Elizeus gaue him leaue (as you geſſe, which yet the text proueth not) to goe to doo his maſter temporal ſeruice, not in reſpect of religion, but according to his office, it was, (as you confeſſe) but by leaue of the prophete, whom God did wil then to be obeyed: but he that is Elizeus nowe, doth geue you no ſuch leaue, but doth commaund the contrarye, whoſe voyce you are bounde to obeye, els this example of Naaman wil condemne you. For if he durſt not doo ſo much, as his temporal office vnto his maſter in the temple without the prophetes leaue, how dare you doo an acte of religion, to further hereſie againſt the expreſſe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of him,
<note place="margin">Deut. 24. Math. 19. Marc. 10. Heb. 7. Galat. 3.</note> who is greater in office then Elizeus? Moyſes gaue the Iewes <hi>libellu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> repud<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> a letter of diuorce, not that it was ſo fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the beginning, but <hi>propter duritia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>;</hi> becauſe of the hardnes of their heartes, becauſe of the imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of the Iewes, for the olde lawe brought nothing to perfection, gaue no grace, but was a time of infancie: but now infancie is paſſed into mans age,
<pb facs="tcp:7400:4"/>and grace is geuen more aboundantly to men. The time a time of perfection that wil admit no ſuch diuorce, no ſuch licence (as you ſéeme to ſay) Naaman thaſſirian had, who was but a Proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lite or a Catechumene.
<note place="margin">1. Cor. 10.</note> Alſo there were no ſuch weaklinges to take ſcandale at his preſence in the Temple of Rem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, as are here in the Sinagoge of heretikes. You may not therfore draw this example of Naaman to coulour your offence, no more then may theſe that now doo put away their old wiues and take new, vſe this example of the old law to cloake their aduoutry.
<note place="margin">Math. 5.</note> For vnleſſe your righteouſnes doo excéede y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> righteouſnes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Scribes &amp; Phariſes, ye can not enter into the kingdome of heauen. Alſo hereſie &amp; ſchiſme are two moſt gréeuous ſinnes, yet diſtinct accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to that whereto they are directlye oppoſite of them ſelues:
<note place="margin">S. Tho. 2.2</note> as hereſie of it ſelf is repugnant vnto faith, Schiſme oppoſite vnto the vnitie of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal charitie. And therfore, like as fayth and charitie are two diuers vertues, (although whoſoeuer lacketh faith, is alſo voide of charitie) So Schiſme and
<pb facs="tcp:7400:5"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:7400:5"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:7400:6"/>and hereſie are two diuers vices, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though who that is an heretike, is alſo a ſchiſmatike,
<note place="margin">Hier. ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per epiſt. ad Galat.</note> yet not euery Schiſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tike is an heretike: as teacheth S. Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rome. <hi>Inter ſchiſma &amp; haereſim hoc in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt, quòd haereſis peruerſum dogma habet, Schiſma ab eccleſia ſeperat. &amp;c.</hi> Betwéene Schiſme and hereſie theſe are the oddes, That hereſie hath al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes a peruerſe opinion againſt an article of fayth, Schiſme ſeperateth from the Churche: yet like as the lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of charitie is the very high waye towardes the loſing of a mans faith, according to that of S. Paule, <hi>A qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus quidam aberrantes, conuerſi ſunt in vaniloquium.</hi> From which ſome wandring (charitie and ſuch like) are reſolued into brablinges. So is Schiſme the high way into hereſie, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though at firſt Shiſme may be vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoode ſomewhat diuers from hereſie it ſelfe, yet in thende there is no Schiſme that doth not coyne forth-with ſome hereſie to haue a colour to reuolt from the Church. And therefore commonlye the ſinne of Schiſme hath bene more
<pb facs="tcp:7400:6"/>gréeuouſly puniſhed in the Scriptures then infidelitie or Idolatrie.
<note place="margin">Exod. 32.</note> For we reade, that the ſinne of Idolatrie was puniſhed by the ſword, by mans execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<note place="margin">Num. 16.</note> But of the ſinne of Schiſme we reade, <hi>Si nouam rem fecerit Dominus, vt aperiens terra os ſuum deglutiat eos, et omnia quae ad illos pertinent. etc.</hi> If our Lorde ſhould doo a newe thing, that the earth opening her mouth doo ſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe them, and al thinges that doo ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertaine vnto them, and liuing, they ſhal deſcende to hel, by this you ſhal knowe that they haue blaſphemed our Lorde God. Alſo the tenn tribes, which through Schiſme reuolted from the kingdome of Dauid, were moſt grée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uouſly puniſhed,
<note place="margin">3. Reg. 12.</note> and in fine fel from Schiſme to Idolatrye. Moreouer, as longe as Abraham abode amonge the Chaldeis, who were Idolatrers,
<note place="margin">Gen. 13.15-17.</note> it is not found that our Lord appered much vnto him, althogh, as it may be thoght, he was a good man: but when he depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from thence, we reade, that often God appered vnto him, and as of a be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefite moſt ſinguler, doth put him in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance
<pb facs="tcp:7400:7"/>of his deliuerie.
<note place="margin">Gen. 33.</note> 
               <hi>Ego do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minꝰ qui eduxi vos de terra Hurr Chal deorum.</hi> Iacob the beloued did refuſe to goe into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> company of reprobate Eſau, although by giftes he had pacified him, neither woulde ſuffer anye of his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uantes to be among his herdmen.
<note place="margin">Gen. 21.</note> Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maels playe with Iſacke did ſo offende Sara, that it is called in Scripture per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſecutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Hard it was, (although Abraha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> proſtrate beſought it) to ſaue Lot from the wrath of God in Sodoma: yea, his wife for looking once backe towardes y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> place where the wicked were,
<note place="margin">Gen. 19.</note> is eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally puniſhed:
<note place="margin">Math. 26. Luk. 22.</note> and Peter the prince of thapoſtles by entring into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> palace of the high Superintendent, &amp; warming him ſelf at their fire, is driuen to deny his faith: Iohn the beloued could not eſcape their hands, but by leauing his gaberdine behind, glad to eſcape ſtarke naked. Theſe are written for our in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions,
<note place="margin">2 Tim. 2.</note> that we ſhoulde beware of falſe heretikes and Schiſmatikes, whoſe ſpéech créepeth as doth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> diſeaſe of a cancar,
<note place="margin">Ca. Apoſt. 63.</note> &amp; infecteth thoſe that it tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth. The Church therfore, as a care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful mother, hath by Canons of antiqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie
<pb facs="tcp:7400:7"/>vtterlye forbidden her children to come nere the forſaken company,
<note place="margin">Con. La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>od. can. 9.3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.33.</note> as by the cotations in the margent may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pere. <hi>Bruno</hi> a learned writer ſaith, that ech prouiſo wherby hereſies &amp; ſchiſmes are to be auoyded, doo conſiſt in theſe:
<note place="margin">Bruno.</note> 
               <hi>Haereticorum communione, collegiis, conuenticulis, Scholis, praedicationibꝰ, &amp; doctrinis, libris falſis, ab haereticis, vel compoſitis, vel deprauatis</hi> By com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municating with heretikes in their colleges, conuenticles, or prophecying, prechings, ſchooles, or in bookes, either by them fally made, or by their notes corrupted: for as by theſe things being ſuffred, hereſies &amp; Schiſmes doo grow, encreaſe, take rooting, and infect: So theſe occaſions being prohibited &amp; cutt off, they are either ſuppreſſed or vtterly extinguiſhed. To communicate with heretikes in theſe thinges, is for thrée cauſes forbidden by the Churche, and that vppon paine of the cenſures therof. The firſt, becauſe heretikes are cutt from the Churche, with whom neyther the Churche, nor they of the Churche ought to haue eyther felow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipp
<pb facs="tcp:7400:8"/>or communion. Secondly, becauſe Catholikes communicating in any of the premiſſes with heretikes, <hi>corum ſe peccatis inuoluant,</hi> doo wrapp them ſelues (to be giltie) in their ſinns, as it is written, Depart from the ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacles of theſe wicked men (Schiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matikes) touche nothing that apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyneth vnto them,
<note place="margin">Rom. 12.</note> leaſt in their ſinnes you wrapp your ſelues. Thirdly, leaſt in vſing their ſocietie, you be made one of them.
<note place="margin">2. Tim. 2. 1. Cor. 10.</note> 
               <hi>Qui ſtat videat nè cadat.</hi> For their ſpéeche and company doth infect. <hi>An emulamur dominum?</hi> Shal we pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoke or trye whether God dare puniſh vs? Are we ſtronger then he, that we can abide his diſpleaſure? We doo eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry day prouoke him to anger, when we come to the conuenticles of his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies. It is not good to ſuſtaine his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure. And therfore is it forbidden by the Conſtitutions of the Apoſtles.
<note place="margin">Conſt. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſt. lib. 5. ca. 4. Et i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis in lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis. Vide F. Turria.</note> 
               <hi>Impios haereticos qui impoenitentes fuerint. &amp;c.</hi> The wicked heretikes that haue ſeperated them ſelues from the faithful Catholikes, caſt off, for they are impenitent, and charge the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likes
<pb facs="tcp:7400:8"/>to abſtaine from their felowſhipp by al meanes, neither let them haue anye communication with them in ſpéeche or prayers, for they are aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries and thieues to the Churche, they begile the flock, defile the heritage. We warne you therefore, that ye auoyde them, leaſt they intangle your ſoules in their ſnares, for it is not lawful to runne with théeues. No man can ſerue two maſters at once. Thus farre the Apoſtles. We ſée what charge they gaue to the children of the houſholde: For like as the life of the body procée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth from the quickening ſpirite (for vntil the breath of life was into the noſethrils of man breathed,
<note place="margin">Aug. Ser. 186. &amp; in Ioan.</note> the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy was ſenſeleſſe, without life,
<note place="margin">A fitt ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militude.</note> for the life of the body is the ſoule, made after the Image of God: al the members as long as they remaine in the body, haue life and ſtrength effectual to their ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed operation procéeding from the ſoule, in the ſame body for that purpoſe abiding. But if either legge, arme, eare, or noſe be cut off from the body, the life of the ſoule foloweth it not, it is deade,
<pb facs="tcp:7400:9"/>vnprofitable, wretched, and miſerable: the life of the ſoule foloweth not a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided member: Euen ſo, looke what the ſoule of man doth in the natural bodye of man, the ſame doth the holy Ghoſte in the miſtical bodye of Chriſte. By Baptiſme we haue put on Chriſte.
<note place="margin">Gal. 3. Rom. 6.</note> 
               <hi>Quotquot in Chriſto baptizati eſtis, Chriſtum induiſtis.</hi> We are incorpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate into his body, as truly, as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> leggs, armes, and head, are by ſinewes orga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nically ioyned to the life of thy ſoule. So truely are they that haue putt on Chriſte in Baptiſme, vnited vnto the miſtical body of Chriſte, which is the Catholike Churche: The ſoule or life of which body is the holy Ghoſt,
<note place="margin">Ioh. 15.</note> like as the life of man is his ſoule. As long as we remaine in this bodye miſtical, in this vine, as true members, as true branches, ſo long haue we life, grace, &amp; giftes proportionable vnto the part, that we occupie in the miſtical body. If we cutt off our ſelues by hereſie, by ſchiſme, by going into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Church, where it is, or where any part of the ſchiſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical ſeruice therof is ſaid or preached, we haue no more the life, graces, and
<pb facs="tcp:7400:9"/>giftes of the holy Ghoſt, to merite life euerlaſting, then hath the leg or arme, cut off from the body, the life of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſoul, which onely remaineth in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> body. The graces of the holy Ghoſt doo not folowe a deuided me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber, what good works ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer he doo, they helpe nothing to merite life, but he is a dead me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber withered to be caſt into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> euerlaſting fire of helliſh paine and woful miſerie. <hi>Vbi eccleſia,
<note place="margin">Iren. li. 3. cap. 40.</note> ibi &amp; ſpiritus, &amp; vbi ſpiritus dei, illic eccleſia &amp; omnis gratia, ſpiritus autem veritas.</hi> Wher y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Church is, there is the ſpirit, &amp; where y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſpirite of God is, there is the Church &amp; al grace, &amp; the ſpirit is truth. And S. Auguſtine ſaith: <hi>Qui ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> relinquit,
<note place="margin">Aug. tract. 1. in 1, Ep. Ioh.</note> quomodò eſt in Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſto?</hi> How is he in Chriſt, that forſaketh y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> church of Chriſt? how is he in Chriſt, that is not in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> body of Chriſt, which is his Catholike Churche? To trye whether thou be a member of this Church (good reader) peruſe this booke for thy ſaluation prepared not by one man, but by the whole Church, whoſe voyce thou art bounde to obeye: and if thou findeſt thy ſelfe to lacke, vſe the remedie therein preſcribed to ſaue thy
<pb facs="tcp:7400:10"/>ſaue thy ſoule, and praye for them that for thy behoofe haue ſet it foorth. From Remes within the Octaues of Al Saintes. 1578.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>By your countriman G. M.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="chapter">
            <pb facs="tcp:7400:10"/>
            <head>¶ REASONS THAT CATHOLIKES ought in any wiſe to abſteine from heretical Conuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles.</head>
            <head type="sub">CAP. I.</head>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Heir verye perſons ought to be auoyded:
<note place="margin">Tit. 3.</note> 
               <hi>Haereticum hominem poſt vnam &amp; alteram admonitione<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> deuita.</hi> A man that is an he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retike auoide after he is once or twiſe admoniſhed. And, <hi>Nec Aue ei dixeritis:
<note place="margin">Ioh. 2.</note> qui nam<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> dicit illi, Aue, communicat operibus eius malignis.</hi> Saye not ſo much to him as, God ſaue you, for he that ſaith ſo to him, doth communicate with his wicked workes.
<note place="margin">Euſeb. li. 3. cap. 22.</note> As S. Iohn did teach other, ſo him ſelfe gaue exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple: <hi>Fugiamus hinc, nè balneum cadat ſuper nos, in quo eſt Cerinthus verita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis hoſtis.</hi> Let vs flée from hence, leaſt the bathe fal vpon vs, in the which <hi>Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinthus</hi> is, the enemie of truth. It is a famous hiſtorie: S. Iohn the Apoſtle
<pb facs="tcp:7400:11"/>and Euangeliſt would not tary in the place,
<note place="margin">2. Tim. 4.</note> when he hearde Cerinthus the heretike was there. <hi>Alexander aerari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us reſtitit verbis noſtris, quem &amp; tu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>deuita.</hi> Alexander the Copper-ſmith withſtoode our wordes, whom I wil that thou alſo doo auoide or ſhunne.</p>
            <p>It is daungerous.
<note place="margin">Rom. 16.</note> 
               <hi>Per dulces ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mones &amp; benedictiones ſeducunt cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da innocentium.</hi> By ſwéete wordes and gaye bleſſinges they ſeduce the heartes of the ſimple or good meaning perſons. And therefore, <hi>Rogo vos fratres vt obſeruetis eos, &amp; declinate ab<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>illis.</hi> I beſéeche you brethren take good héede of them, and turne aſide from them.
<note place="margin">2. Tim. 2.</note> And, <hi>Sermo eorum vt cancer ſerpit, &amp; ſubuerterunt quorundam fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem, multùm enim proficiunt ad im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pietatem. Sed firmum fundamentum Dei ſtat, habens ſignaculum hoc, cog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouit Dominus qui ſunt eius.</hi> Their talke créepeth like a canker, and they haue ſubuerted the faith of certaine, for they preuaile much in vngodlines. But the foundation of God ſtandeth
<pb facs="tcp:7400:11"/>ſure, our Lorde knoweth who are his. Onely they that flée from ſuche: and therefore it foloweth: <hi>Diſcedat abini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitate omnis qui nominat nomen Domini.</hi> Let him depart from wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, euery one that nameth the name of our Lorde: euery good Catholike. Againe,
<note place="margin">2. Pet. 2.</note> 
               <hi>Pellicientes animas inſtabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les, eos qui paululum effugiunt.</hi> Allu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring vnconſtant ſoules, ſuche as ſcape them but a very litle. Who are they <hi>qui paululum effugiunt,</hi> but ſuch as boldlye communicate with them, and therefore are in daunger to become theirs altogether? <hi>Effugiunt,</hi> they ſcape them, becauſe in heart they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent not: but <hi>paululum,</hi> very litle, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe in fact they are like to them. If they preſume vpon their conſtancie or knowledge, that there can enſue no daunger, <hi>Qui ſtat, videat ne cadat.</hi> He that ſtandeth, let him beware he fal not. And, <hi>Qui tangit picem,
<note place="margin">Eccleſi. 13.</note> inquina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitur ab ea.</hi> He that toucheth pitche, ſhalbe defiled with it.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:7400:12"/>
            <p>And,
<note place="margin">Eccleſi. 3.</note> 
               <hi>Qui dormit iuxtà ſepern, morde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit eum coluber.</hi> He that ſléepeth néere the hedge, a ſerpent wil ſting him. And, <hi>Qui amat periculum peribit in illo.</hi> He that loueth or ſéeketh daunger ſhal periſh in it.</p>
            <p>For the ſelfe-ſame cauſe it is not lawful,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> to reade heretical bookes, and is it lawful to heare their ſermons and praiers?
<note place="margin">Sozom. li. 1. ca. 20. &amp; li. 2. c. 31. de libris Mar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>celli haere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tici.</note> Conſtantine the great made it death to him that did not burne the bookes of Arrius. Martian alſo and Iuſtinian made careful decrées to this purpoſe. This place is verye large. Gregorie the great (Biſhop of Rome) did not abſolue one Anaſtaſius a prieſt from ſuſpitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of hereſie,
<note place="margin">Li. 5 ep. 64</note> til he had pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed, that he would neuer reade that heretical hooke againe, for the which he was ſuſpected. <hi>Anaſtaſium pręsbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terum promittentem, quòd codicem quendam haereticum nunquàm denuò lecturus eſſet, ita demùm abſoluit ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectum haereſeos.</hi> Sée Heſſels that fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Doctor of Louaine <hi>in 1. Tim. 6. ad illud in graeco, <hi>aphistaso apo ton tointon.</hi>
               </hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:7400:12"/>Dioniſius Alexandrinus a moſte aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient, learned,
<note place="margin">Euſeb. ec. li. 7. ca. 6</note> and vertuous Biſhopp confeſſeth to a frend of his who war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned him of heretical bookes, that he felt him-ſelfe the woorſe for them, and had abſtained, but that a heauenly viſion gaue him, as it were, a priuiledge, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding this cauſe: <hi>Nam ſatis habes viri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um &amp; firmitatis ad quae<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan>, tùm con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uincenda, tùm exploranda.</hi> For thou art ſtronge &amp; ſure enough, both to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founde al that is in them, and to exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine them. He that hath not this war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantize from Chriſt, or from his vicar, may not preſume. It is noted in cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine learned Catholikes of our time, that by reading ſuch bookes they ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what yéelded to error, Albertus Pig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hius and Alphonſus: Maye ignorant men be bolder then theſe?</p>
            <p>It doth argue conſent,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> and that by preſence you allow their doinges, and therfore, <hi>in foro eccleſiae,</hi> you are taken for ſuch, although you be not ſuch,
<note place="margin">Apoc. 18.</note> and you ſhalbe puniſhed with them. <hi>Exite de illa (Babilone, haereſi) populus me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us,
<pb facs="tcp:7400:13"/>vt nè participes ſitis delictorum e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ius, de plagis eius non accipiatis.</hi> Goe out from her (meaning Babilon, which ſignifieth hereſie) my people, that you be not partaker of her ſinnes, and that you receaue not of her plages. Marke: <hi>Populus meus,</hi> My people, becauſe they were in heart his,
<note place="margin">Rom. 1.</note> but in conuerſation ioyned with his enemye. <hi>Digni ſunt morte non ſolùm qui ea faciunt, ſed etiam qui cònſentiunt illa facientibus.</hi> They are woorthy of death, not onely the doers, but they that conſent.</p>
            <p>It doth diſhonour God,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> and honour his aduerſarye: a diſgrace to the Churche, a ioye and comfort to hereſie. The Churche is a Citie vpon an hil, that maye onely appere and be ſéene: the more it appereth and is vniuerſal, the more it is for the honour of Chriſt.
<note place="margin">Prouer. 14</note> 
               <hi>Honor Regis multitudo populi; pau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citas plebis ignominia Principis.</hi> It is the Kinges honour to haue a multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of people, to haue fewe is diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour to the Prince. The aduerſarys
<pb facs="tcp:7400:13"/>knowing this, deſireth onely to make vp a number, and is careleſſe what they thinke in conſcience, ſo they make a ſhewe to be his by any means.
<note place="margin">Pſalm. 16.</note> 
               <hi>De abſconditis tuis adimpletus eſt venter eorum.</hi> Of ſuch as are ſecrete Catholikes, they fil vp their hereti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Sinagoge: Lutherans, Caluiniſts, Puritanes, Anabaptiſtes, al are the aduerſaryes by profeſſion. If he maye get alſo of them that would other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe be compted Catholikes, to ioyne openly with them, is it not his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour? He that in ſecret ſootheth his prince, and openlye taketh part with his enemve, in heart is his, in fact the others: his in peace, and the others in time of daunger, whether of the two doth he moſt honoure?
<note place="margin">1. Reg. 2.</note> But God ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth: <hi>Honorem meum alteri non dabo.</hi> I wil not geue mine honour to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. And, <hi>Qui me glorificauerit, glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rificabo eum: qui autem contemnunt me, erunt ignobiles.</hi> He that ſhal glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifie me, him wil I glorifie: but
<pb facs="tcp:7400:14"/>wil I glorifie: but they that ſet litle by me, ſhalbe of no reputation. And that voyce of our Sauiour to the Iewes what true Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> may abide, when it is woorthely ſaide to him-ſelfe alſo.
<note place="margin">Ioh. 8.</note> 
               <hi>Vos autem inhonoraſtis me,</hi> But you haue diſhonored me. And, <hi>Sic luce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at lux veſtra coram hominibus, vt vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deant &amp; glorificent Patrem veſtru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> qui in coelis eſt.</hi> Let your light ſo ſhine be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore men, that they may ſée it and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifie your Father that is in heauen. <hi>Nemo accendit lucernam &amp; ponit eam ſub modio, ſed ſuper candelabrum.</hi> No man is by Gods grace lightned with Catholike faith and vnderſtanding, to hide it in his boſome. O it is a glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous thing, not onely in minde, but bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dely to ioyne with our Lorde. A nota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble example in the Leuites,
<note place="margin">Exod. 32.</note> when Moi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes ſaide: <hi>Si quis eſt Domini, iungatur mihi.</hi> If any man be of our Lordes ſide, let him ioyne with me. They ran fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Schiſmatical Idolatours, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſting that they were on their Lordes ſide, and therefore they were <hi>Pars &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:7400:14"/>haereditas Domini,</hi> The prieſtly tribe, and afterwards accompted al one with Iuda, vnder the ſpecial protection of Almightie God. <hi>Ambroſ. li. 2. off. cap. 24. Licet tibi ſilere in negotio pecuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ario. &amp;c. In cauſa autem Dei, vbi com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munionis periculum eſt, etiam diſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulare peccatum eſt non leue.</hi> Thou maieſt holde thy peace ſometime in a mony matter, but in Gods cauſe, wher there is daunger of communicating with his enemies, to diſſemble onely, is no ſmal ſinne.</p>
            <p>It is not onely glorious,
<note place="margin">6. Luc. 12.</note> but neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye, to confeſſe our faith openly. <hi>Qui negat me coram hominibus, negabo &amp; ego cum coram Patre meo &amp; Ange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis eius.</hi> He that denieth me before me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, I wil alſo denye him before my Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and his Angels. And,
<note place="margin">Rom. 10.</note> 
               <hi>Corde cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditur ad iuſtitiam,</hi> To be iuſtified we muſt beléeue in the heart in catholike quietnes. <hi>Ore confeſsio fit ad ſalutem.</hi> To be ſaued we muſt confeſſe with our mouth in time of hereſie. And,
<note place="margin">Hebr. 10.</note> 
               <hi>Iuſtus meus ex fide viuit. Quod ſi ſubtraxe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit
<pb facs="tcp:7400:15"/>ſe,
<note place="margin">Subtracti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>o ſeu prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaricatio.</note> non placebit animae meae. Nos autem non ſumus ſubtractionis filii in, perditionem, ſed fidei in acquiſitione<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> animae.</hi> My iuſt one liueth by faith. But if he ſecretly reuolte, he ſhal not pleaſe my ſoule. We are not reuolting children to perdition, but the children of faithfulnes to ſaue our ſoule. <hi>Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trahere ſe,</hi> is to ſhrinke from proteſting his faith: <hi>
                  <hi>huposteilasthai</hi> praeuaricari. D. Amb. ep. 3. Ipſis Gentilibus diſplicere conſueuit praeuaricantis affectus, liberè nam<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> debet defendere vnuſquiſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dele mentis ſuae &amp; ſeruare propoſitu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> The Panims them ſelues were wont to miſlike his behauiour that betray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth his owne cauſe: for euerye man ought fréely to mainteyne and to kéepe the faithful purpoſe of his owne mind and conſcience.</p>
            <p>It argueth a neuter,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> that is, ſuche a one as is not affected to eyther religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and conſequently of no religion: <hi>
                  <hi>atheon,</hi> ſine deo in hoc mundo:</hi> an A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theiſte,
<pb facs="tcp:7400:15"/>one that acknowledgeth no God in this worlde. <hi>Apoc. 3. Vti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam frigidus eſſes aut calidus, ſed quia tepidus es, &amp; nec frigidus nec ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lidus, incipiam te euomere ex ore meo.</hi> I would thou were colde or hott, that is, no diſſembler, but a plaine dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler one way or the other. But becauſe thou art luke warme, and neither cold nor hott, a neuter, earneſt in neyther,
<note place="margin">Mat. 11.</note> I wil beginne to ſpewe thée out of my mouth. <hi>Qui non eſt mecum, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra me eſt, &amp; qui mecum non colli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>git, ſpargit.</hi> He that is not with me is againſt me, and he that gathereth not with me, ſcattereth.</p>
            <p>Or if thou haue a conſcience to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde the Catholike Religion,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/> and doeſt cleane contrarye,
<note place="margin">Rom. 14.</note> that is dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable. <hi>Beatus qui ſe non iudicat in eo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>quod probat.</hi> Bleſſed is he that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demneth not himſelfe in doing con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarye to that he beſt alloweth. <hi>Quod enim ex fide non eſt, peccatum eſt.</hi> that is, according to his conſcience:
<pb facs="tcp:7400:16"/>
               <hi>hoc eſt ſecundùm conſcientiam,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1.2, q 19.</note> as S. Thomas expoundeth it: who maketh this concluſion ſo certain and vnfalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, that if a man in conſcience ſhoulde erre, as it is ſinne to doo accordingly: ſo alſo to doo contrary, is to him a damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſinne. For example. A Caluiniſt adoring the bleſſed Sacrament doth ſinne, becauſe he is perſwaded in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, he ought not, and that it is Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latrie. Contrary-wiſe, a Catholike be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of his conſcience, that Chriſte is there preſent, <hi>peccat non adorando,</hi> ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth in not adoring,
<note place="margin">In pſal. 98.</note> as S. Auſtin ſaith. <hi>Iacob. 4. Scienti bonum facere, &amp; non facienti peccatum eſt illi.</hi> He that knoweth to doo good,
<note place="margin">In pſa. 54.</note> and doth it not, to him it is ſinne. S. Auſtin. <hi>Qui noſti eſſe mala quae facis, &amp; tamen facis ea, nonnè viuus deſcendis ad inferos?</hi> Thou that knoweſt the thinges that thou doeſt are yll, and yet doeſt them, doeſt thou not go down into hel quick? Thou art in conſcience and knowledge a Catholike, in fact &amp; demeanour thou wouldeſt ſéeme an heretike, <hi>eſtnè ex fide?</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:7400:16"/>is it according to thy conſcience? <hi>eſtnè quod probas?</hi> Is it that thou do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt beſt alowe? <hi>ergò peccatum eſt, quia non ex fide, ergò iudicaſti teipſum in co quod probas.</hi> Therefore it is ſinne, becauſe it is not according to thy con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience. Therfore thou haſt condemned thy ſelf, in doing contrary to that thou alloweſt. But wouldeſt thou not ſéeme to allowe their doinges? <hi>Nolite errare,
<note place="margin">Galat. 6</note> deus non irridetur.</hi> Be not deceaued, God is not mocked. Why doo other in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curre diſpleaſure, but by diſalowing their procéedinges? how is that know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en, but by their abſence onely? (for ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny haue not occaſion to ſpeake their faith) <hi>ergò</hi> thou art quiet, becauſe thou doeſt ſéeme to allowe it, and that is ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered by thy preſence: to thée therfore is ſaide <hi>illud in ep. Cleri. Rom. apud Cipr. 31. Cùm totum fidei Sacramen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in confeſsione nominis Chriſti in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligatur digeſtum, qui fallaces in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſatione praeſtigias quaeſiuit, negauit. Et qui vult videri propoſitis aduerſus Euangelium, vel edictis, vel legibus ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſfeciſſe,
<pb facs="tcp:7400:17"/>hoc ipſo iam paruit, quòd videri paruiſſe ſe voluit.</hi> Whereas the whole miſterie of fayth is vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoode to conſiſt in confeſſing the name of Chriſte, he that hath ſought falſe ſleightes for excuſe thereof, hath deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. And he that wil ſéeme to haue ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled ſuch Statutes and lawes as are ſet forth againſt the Ghoſpel, in ſo do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing he hath obeyed them in very déede, foraſmuch as he would haue it ſéeme that he hath obeyed the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Who know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not that colde Catholikes come to Churche in England vpon this falſe principle:
<note place="margin">De Ciuit. dei lib. 6. cap. 10.</note> We muſt obeye a lawe? Saint Auſten writeth of Seneca, one familier with Saint Paule, but a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembler for feare of Nero. <hi>Eò damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilius fecit (colendo Idola) quòd ea quae fallaciter egit, ſic tamen egit, vt veraci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter egiſſe exiſtimaretur.</hi> He did it (mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning his woorſhipping of Idols) ſo much the more damnably, becauſe that which he did onely for a ſhewe, yet ſo he did it, that he would be thought to haue done it truely, and from his very heart.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:7400:17"/>
            <p>Here you may remember olde Elea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zarus,
<note place="margin">2. Mach. 5.</note> that would not ſéeme to breake anye litle point of Gods lawe, but dye rather a moſt cruel death. It is a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous hiſtorie done before the time of grace, and therefore ſhal condemne our diſſembling Catholikes nowe in great pointes, for feare of ſmal dammages. <hi>Non nam<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> aetati noſtrae dignum eſt fingere; vt multi adoleſcentes arbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trantes Eleazarum tranſiſſe ad vitam alienigenarum, decipiantur. &amp;c.</hi> It is a thing vnwoorthy of our age to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemble, whereby manye yonge men thinking that Eleazarus is reuolted to the life and Religion of Gentiles, maye be deceaued through my exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.</p>
            <p>But it is poſſible that thy conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence is indifferent to both religions,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="9"/> and ſo thou art excuſed from doing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thy conſcience.
<note place="margin">Iacob. 3.</note> 
               <hi>Nunquid fons de eodem foramine emanat dulcem &amp; amaram aquam?</hi> Doth a fountaine out of one and the ſelf-ſame ſpringe guſhe
<pb facs="tcp:7400:18"/>foorth ſwéete and ſower water? truth and hereſie? vnitie and ſchiſme? <hi>Nemo poteſt duobus dominis ſeruire.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Cor. 6.</note> No ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> can ſerue two maſters. And, <hi>Non po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtis bibere calicem Domini &amp; cali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cem dęmoniorum. Quae participatio iuſtitię cum iniquitate? aut quę con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uentio Chriſti ad Belial? aut quę pars fideli cum infideli?</hi> You cannot drinke of our Lordes cupp and the cupp of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uils? What partaking hath righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes with iniquitie? or what agrement is there betwéene Chriſte and Belial? Or what part hath a faithful ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with the faithleſſe or infidel? And what fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth? <hi>Propter quod exite de medio eorum, &amp; ſeperamini, dicit Dominus, &amp; immundum ne tetigeritis, &amp; ego re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipiam vos, &amp; ero vobis in patre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> For the which cauſe goe out from amonge them, and ſeperate your ſelues from them, ſaith our Lorde, and touche not that that is vncleane, and I wil receue you, and wil be to you a Father. As much to ſay, if you wil folow my reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion onely, I am your Father, your
<pb facs="tcp:7400:18"/>God. &amp;c. Otherwiſe,
<note place="margin">Eſai. 28.</note> 
               <hi>Coanguſtum eſt ſtratum, ita vt alter excidat, &amp; pallium breue non poteſt duos tegere.</hi> The bed is narowe, ſo that thou muſt néedes fal out, and a ſhort blanket cannot couer two. Which Saint Hierome doth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terprete of Chriſte, who is, as it were, <hi>Sponſus animae noſtrae,</hi> The Spouſe wedded to our ſoule: And therfore can not abide <hi>adulterum ſimul ſecum in codem ſtrato,</hi> an aduoulterer together with him in the ſame bed. He wil a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone haue vs, or not at al.
<note place="margin">3. Reg. 18.</note> 
               <hi>Si Baal ſit Deus, ſequimini eum; ſin Dominus ſit Deus, ſcquimini illum. Quouſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> clau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicatis in vtram<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> partem?</hi> If Baal be God, folowe him. If our Lorde be God, folowe him.
<note place="margin">Epheſ 4.</note> Howe long limpe you on both ſides? <hi>Vna fides, vnus De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us, vnus Dominus.</hi> One faith (ſaith S. Paule) one God, one Lorde.
<note place="margin">3. Reg. 3</note> The na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Mother <hi>(Catholica Eccleſia)</hi> ſaide not to Salomon: <hi>Diuidatur.</hi> Let the childe be deuided, but al or none. The Samaritanes woorſhipped the true God ſchiſmatically, and withal their
<pb facs="tcp:7400:19"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:7400:19"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:7400:20"/>owne bables: but it is ſaide <hi>(Ioh. 4.)</hi> of the Iewes that had the true woor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipp of one God, Catholikes, as it were. <hi>Non coutuntur Iudaei Samarita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis.</hi> The Iewes kéepe no companye with the Samaritanes.
<note place="margin">Deut. 22.</note> Againe, thoſe preceptes: <hi>Non arabis boue &amp; aſino: Non texes veſtimenta ex lino &amp; lana: non miſcebis duo ſemina in agro tuo.</hi> Thou ſhalt not plough with an oxe and an Aſſe together. Thou ſhalt not weaue garmentes of both linnen and woollen. Thou ſhalt not mingle two diuers ſéedes in thy fielde: and the like. What is the ſignification, but, <hi>Vae du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plici corde.</hi> Woe be to the double hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. And, <hi>Vir duplici animo inconſtans eſt in omnibus viis ſuis.</hi> A double har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted man is vnconſtant in al his waies. And,
<note place="margin">Eccl. 3.</note> 
               <hi>Vir ingrediens duas vias non ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bebit ſucceſſus.</hi> And, <hi>Cor prauum ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalizabitur in eis.</hi> A man that goeth in two wayes, ſhal not go forwarde, and a wicked heart ſhal ſtumble in them. And that which is terrible.
<note place="margin">Sophon. 1.</note> 
               <hi>Diſperdam de terra eos, qui iurant in deum &amp; in
<pb facs="tcp:7400:20"/>Melchom.</hi> I wil deſtroy the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that ſwear by God, and their wicked king. For ſo <hi>Melchom</hi> doth ſignifie by God in hart, by their prince in behauiour, which ſerue both, depende vpon both. &amp;c. <hi>In malitia ſua lętificauerunt regem,
<note place="margin">Oſcae. 7.</note> &amp; in mendaciis ſuis principes.</hi> They haue de lighted the king in their naughtines, &amp; princes by their lying or diſſembling. Of ſuch men as learne to diſſemble of their naughty paſtors, S. Auſten ſaith: <hi>Si indifferentem habuero errorem tuu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,
<note place="margin">De paſtor. cap. 7.</note> attendit qui fortis eſt, putat nihil eſſe ire in haereſim, quando aliquod co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum de ſeculo reduxerit, vnde mute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur. Statim mihi dicit fortis ille peritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus, &amp; hâc, &amp; hâc deus eſt. Quid inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt? homines inter ſe litigantes hoc fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerunt: vbicun<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> colendus eſt deus.</hi> If I ſhal thinke thy error indifferent, and that it is al one to doo this or that, he that is otherwiſe ſtronge, marketh it, and thinketh it is nothing to runne into hereſie, when ſome world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye commoditie ſhal appere, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by he maye be altered and chaunged,
<pb facs="tcp:7400:21"/>by and by this ſtoute man ſaith vnto me, God is both here and there, what difference is there? men by iangling among them ſelues haue made al this adoe. God is to be woorſhipped in euery place or congregation.</p>
            <p>It is ſcandalous,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="10"/> and maketh thy brother to ſinn, which is a very weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie conſideration, as appereth by our Sauiours <hi>Vae:
<note place="margin">Mat. 18.</note> Vae mundo à ſcanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis: Vae illi per quem veniunt ſcanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la.</hi> Woe be to the world by reaſon of ſtumbling blockes: Woe be to him that maketh other men to ſtumble. And,
<note place="margin">Marc. 9.</note> 
               <hi>Qui ſcandalizauerit vnum ex puſillis iſtis, credentibus in me, bonum eſt ei magis ſi circundaretur mola aſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naria collo eius, &amp; in mare mitteretur.</hi> He that is an occaſion why any one of theſe litle ones, that beléeue in me, doo ſtumble or ſinne, it were good for him, if a mil-ſtone were hanged about his necke, and that he were caſt into the Sea. <hi>Puſilli,</hi> Litle ones, are they that beléeue wel, and meane wel, and gladly would doo for the beſt, but are eaſilye
<pb facs="tcp:7400:21"/>moued to relent by authoritie or exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. Here remember once more olde Eleazarus, who therfore choſe to dye,
<note place="margin">2. Mach. 6.</note> becauſe yonge men ſhould not be bolde to breake Gods lawe, ſaying: Olde Eleazarus did ſo, why may not we? but, O woorthy Eleazarus, it was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired onely of thée to eate lawful meates, ſo that thou wouldeſt but ſéem to haue eate<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnlawful: yea (quoth he) therfore let me dye, rather then yonge perſons by thinking that I did it, of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fende damnably by occaſion of my diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſimulation. This man knewe before by inſpiration that <hi>Vae</hi> which Chriſte afterward pronounced <hi>ſcandalizanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus.</hi> And therefore leſſe meruaile (al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though meruailous) if S. Paule after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward ſpeake vehemently:
<note place="margin">1. Cor. 8.</note> 
               <hi>Si ęſca ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalizat fratrem meum, non manduca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bo carnem in aeternum.</hi> If meate of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fende my brother, or be occaſion of his finne, I wil not eate fleſh for euer: al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the meate of it ſelfe was good and lawful. <hi>Sic nam<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> peccantes in fratres, &amp; percutientes conſcientiam
<pb facs="tcp:7400:22"/>corum infirmam, in Chriſtum pecca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis.</hi> For you ſinning after that ſort a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt your brethren, and wounding their weake conſcience, ſinne againſt Chriſte: wherin was this daungerous ſcandal committed? marke the caſe like to ours. <hi>Si nam<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> quis viderit eum qui habet ſcientiam, in idolio recumbente<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, nonnè conſcientia eius cùm ſit infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma, aedificabitur ad manducandum i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolothita?</hi> for if a man ſhal chaunce to ſée him that hath knowledge ſitt in the temple of idoles, ſhal not his conſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce being weake, be edified and induced to eate idolatrous meates by thy exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple? if a weakling ſée thée (a man of ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compt and eſtimation) preſent in the Churche of heretikes, or at their ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, their conſcience being not ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye ſetled to deteſt hereſie, is he not ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily induced to frequent their conuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles with daunger of dayly corruptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and either to like the better, or to miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like the leſſe of their ſayinges and do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inges?
<note place="margin">Aug. epiſt. 154.</note> 
               <hi>Apparet illud eſſe prohibitum,</hi> (ſaith S. Auſten) <hi>nè in honorem alie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norum
<pb facs="tcp:7400:22"/>deorum aliqua re vtamur, áut vti exiſtimemur, ſic etiam accipiendo, vt quamuis animo contemnamus, eos tamen qui noſtrum animum ignorant, ad haec honoranda aedificemus.</hi> It is euident that this is forbidden, that we vſe not anye thing in the honour of ſtraunge Gods, or to be thought to vſe, taking it in ſuch ſort, that although in heart we deſpiſe it, yet we edifie and induce them that knowe not our hart, to honour the ſame thinges. This caſe concerneth al ſtates, vpon whoſe exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple any one Chriſtian ſoule dependeth: princes, prelates, paſtors, maſters, pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentes. Of princes let one Ieroboa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, who is alwayes me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tioned in ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture with this title of his ſcandalous apoſtaſie. <hi>Qui peceare fecit Iſrael,</hi> that made Iſrael to ſinne: which is proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye <hi>ſcandalum,</hi> or <hi>ſcandalizare.</hi> S. Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broſe to the Emperour Valentinian, <hi>epiſt. 30.</hi> vrgeth the like inconuenience if he did but yéelde a litle to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Panims requeſt. <hi>Totus hic Chriſtianorum pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riclitatur Senatus. &amp;c.</hi> This whole be<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ch
<pb facs="tcp:7400:23"/>of Chriſtian Senatours is in daunger to offende mortally by this meanes. And (which is much to be noted <hi>contra excuſandas excuſationes in peccatis:</hi> againſt al blinde excuſes to iuſtifie yll doinges, common nowe a dayes to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſh great faultes) wheras the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour might haue ſaide, I did not ſacrifice, nor induce any man to doo it: yet becauſe he permitted that onely to be done, wherof Idolatrie folowed, <hi>pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ganis vt erigerent aras,</hi> the Paynims to ſet vp Idolatrous aultars, he ſaith: <hi>Vox enim tua, manus tua.</hi> Thy word is thy hande. <hi>Et ſubſcriptio tua opus eſt tuum.</hi> And to ſubſcribe to the Pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nims licence, is as much as if thou haddeſt done it thy ſelfe. And againe: <hi>Quiſquis hoc ſuadet, ſacrificat, &amp; quiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quis hoc ſtatuit.</hi> Whoſoeuer geueth councel to it, doth ſacrifice to falſe Gods, and whoſoeuer doth decrée it. Sée howe farre this ſinne <hi>(ſcandalum)</hi> extendeth, not onely to the doers, but to them that councel, ſubſcribe, winke at it, permitt and diſſemble it. <hi>Apoc. 2.
<pb facs="tcp:7400:23"/>Habes illic tenentes doctrinam Bala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am, qui docebat Balac mittere ſcandalu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> coram filiis Iſrael, pugnabo cum illis in gladio oris mei.</hi> Thou haſt there that holde the doctrine of Balaam, who taught Balac how to geue occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that the children of Iſrael might ſinne: I wil fight againſt them with the ſword of my mouth. He threatneth the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters and Councellers, <hi>qui docebant mittere ſcandalum,</hi> as Balaam, not onely the prince him ſelfe and chiefe doer Balac. Of
<note n="*" place="margin">Vide ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emplum Miſeni &amp; Vitalis, qui à Ro. pont. miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſi Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinopo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lim, cum Petro hae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retico co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runt, qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalum po<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pulo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derint, vt putauerit Pontifice<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Rom. cum haeretico co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>muni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſſe. Euagr. li. 3. cap. 21.</note> prelates I wil geue examples afterward in more conueni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent plaee, leaſt I dwel in this reaſon to longe. Of Paſtours, S. Auſten (<hi>de paſtoribus ca. 7. to .9.) Si fortè dixerit aliquis Donatiſta, non tibi do filiam meam, niſi fueris de parte mea; illi opus eſt vt attendat et dicat: Si nihil mali<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>eſſet de parte eorum, non contra illos dicerent tanta paſtores noſtri, non pro illorum errore ſatagerent.</hi> If perhaps ſome Donatiſt ſhal ſay (to a colde Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike) I geue thée not my daughter vnleſſe thou be of my ſide, it ſtandeth
<pb facs="tcp:7400:24"/>this man vpon to take good héede, and to ſay with him ſelfe: If there were no harme on their ſide, our Paſtors or preachers would not ſpeak ſo much a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them, they would not be ſo ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt to confound their error. It folow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth: <hi>Si ergò ceſſemus et taceamus, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traria locuturus eſt: vti<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ſi malu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſſet in parte Donati, loquerentur contrà, redarguerent eos, ſatagerent lucrari il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>los, ſi errant reuocarent illos, ſi percu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, quaererent illos. &amp;c.</hi> If therefore we ceaſſe and holde our peace, he wil ſaye contrary: Verily if there had béene any euil in Donatus faction, our Paſtors and Curates would ſpeake againſt it, would rebuke them, if they be loſt would ſéeke them. &amp;c. Of Parentes. <hi>Ciprianus de lapſis. Nonne illi (paruu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>li) cùm iudicii dies venerit, dicent: Nos nihil fecimus, nec derelicto cibo et po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culo domini</hi> (the bleſſed Sacrament) <hi>ad profana contagia ſpontò properaui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus; perdidit nos aliena perfidia, pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentes ſenſimus homicidas. Illi nobis eccleſiam matrem, illi parentem deum
<pb facs="tcp:7400:24"/>negauerunt, vt dum parui et improui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di, et tanti facinoris ignari, per alios ad conſortium criminis iungimur, aliena fraude caperemur.</hi> Wil not they (the children) when the day of iudgement ſhal come, ſay? We haue done nothing of our ſelues, neither, forſaking y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> meat and the cupp of our Lorde (the bleſſed Sacrament) haue we of our owne ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corde haſtened to profane infections, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther mens infidelitie hath vndoon vs, we haue felt our owne parentes men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtears, they haue denied vs the Church our Mother, and God our Father, that whiles we being yonge, and foreſeing no daunger, and ignorant that it was ſo heynous a fault, by the motion of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers are made partakers of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> crime, by other mens pollicie might ſo be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trapped. This place concerneth moſt kind of perſons, &amp; were to be handled at large, becauſe Parentes maye many waies geue their childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to fal into hereſie &amp; ſchiſme (but I wold gladly end this firſt part concerning reaſons:) briefly, if they geue example,
<pb facs="tcp:7400:25"/>by communicating, if they permitt their children, or rather commaunde them, thereby to excuſe them ſelues, imagining that it is venial in them becauſe of their age: if they doo not forbid them and teache them the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, if they ſende them to ſchooles or vniuerſities, where they muſt néedes heare and ſée, and doo that they ſhoulde not. &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Nuptię cum infidelibus prohiben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="11"/> et cum hereticis.</hi> Mariage with Infidels, and with heretikes is forbid, becauſe of the daunger in peruerting one the other. <hi>Et contractę diſcindi poterunt ac debent, illę quoad vincu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum, iſtę quoad cohabitationem, ſi co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitare non liceat ſine iniuria Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toris.</hi> And being contracted maye not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding, and ought to be ſundred, thone to be no mariage, the other not to liue together at al, if they cannot liue together without iniurie of their Maker: that is, if thone wil néedes make thother offende God.
<note place="margin">2. Cor. 6.</note> 
               <hi>Nolite iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gum ducere cum infidelibus.</hi> Drawe
<pb facs="tcp:7400:25"/>not in one yoke with Infidels. Which is moſt properly ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>de coniugibus, et. 1. Cor. 7.</hi> and <hi>Tertullian ad vxorem,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Euſcb. li. 4 cap. 16.</note> and theccleſiaſtical hiſtorie of a vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous godly matrone that departed from her huſband. And our Sauiour him ſelfe.
<note place="margin">Mat. 19.</note> 
               <hi>Qui reliquerit vxorem propter me, centuplum accipiet.</hi> He that forſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth his wife for my ſake, ſhal receaue a hundred folde. <hi>Qui non oderit,
<note place="margin">Luc. 14.</note> non eſt me dignus.</hi> He that hateth her not for my ſake, is not woorthy of me.
<note place="margin">Deut. 13.</note> And Moyſes: <hi>Si vxor quae eſt in ſinu ruo.</hi> If thy wife that fléepeth in thy boſome wil perſuade thée error, caſt thou the firſt ſtone at her. If the wife and her huſbande may not kéepe company, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the one is a wicked infidel or he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retike, of whom it is ſaide: <hi>Et adhę<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rebit vxori ſue.</hi> And he ſhal cleaue to his wife. And if the ſonne muſt vppon paine of damnatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> forſake the Father, and the daughter her mother, becauſe they are of a contrary beliefe (for <hi>Qui diligit eos plus me,</hi> and, <hi>Qui non odit patrem et matrem, non eſt me dig</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:7400:26"/>He that loueth them better then me: yea, he that doth not hate father and mother (in this caſe) is not woor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of me.
<note place="margin">Luc. 12.</note> 
               <hi>Putatis quia pacem veni mittere? non dico vobis, ſed ſeperatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem.</hi> Thinke you that I came to ſende peace vpon the earth? no, I tel you truth, but diuiſion and diſſenſion: mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, that for his ſake the ſon ſhould leaue his father, the daughter her mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, the wife her huſbande, one frende forſake another. If, I ſay, this be ſo, much more heretical conuenticles are to be abhorred.</p>
            <p>Al ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> profeſſors of hereſie or know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en heretikes are <hi>ipſo facto excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicati,</hi>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="12"/> in ſo doing they are excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicate forthwith, without further ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, as appereth in Councels, decrées, <hi>et in bulla coenę domini.</hi> In their prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers and ſermons their profeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt, <hi>ergò</hi> then eſpecially we muſt ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteine from them, <hi>quia participare cum excommunicato in diuinis etiam ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicè, graue peccatum eſt:</hi> becauſe to communicate or to be partaker with
<pb facs="tcp:7400:26"/>an excommunicate perſon in thinges pertaining to Gods ſeruice, albeit af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter a catholike maner (as whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lagiens had al their ſeruice and ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies catholike) is by the iudgement of learned diuines and the conſent of the Churche a gréeuous ſinne, howe much more gréeuous is it to communicate with them, when their ſeruice and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of praier is wholly heretical? Yea, the firſt caſe <hi>de reſeruatis in bulla Coe. Domini, eſt hęreſis, &amp; comprehendit eos qui praeſumunt legere libros hęre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticorum, qui<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> imprimunt, et domi ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bent, et demùm omnes fautores hęreti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corum: ergò à pari,</hi> to frequent their conuenticles where they pray &amp; preach is comprehended.</p>
            <p>It is exco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munication to enter into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Iewes Sinagoge at the time of their ceremonies, wherin euery day,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="13"/> as S. Hierome writeth, they pronounce a ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemne curſe <hi>contra Ieſum Nazarenu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Ieſus of Nazareth, ſo they cal him of contempt &amp; deſpite. The like is ſaid of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>ſchiſmatical Grecians in Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nice: much more is it to be conceued of
<pb facs="tcp:7400:27"/>haunting heretical conuenticles, wher the bleſſed Sacrament, the vicar of Chriſte, are impudently blaſphemed: much more,
<note place="margin">1. Cor. 5.</note> I ſay, as appereth by the Apoſtles diſtinction, <hi>de fornicariis hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ius mundi,</hi> and, <hi>ſi is qui frater nomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, eſt fornicarius.</hi> Of them whom he calleth fornicatours of this world, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidels or Paynims: and of chriſtian brethren that are fornicatours: of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he meant not, but of this latter. <hi>Nè commiſceamini cum illis,</hi> Kéep no com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany with them. &amp;c. but more of this compariſon hereafter. Here commeth to hand another reaſon.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Scripſi vobis non commiſceri,
<note place="margin">1. Cor. 5 14.</note> ſi is qui frater nominatur, eſt fornicarius, aut auarus, aut maledicus. &amp;c. cum e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuſmodi nec cibum ſumere.</hi> I wrote to you not to kéepe company with anye ſuch, as being a Chriſtian man, is a fornicatour, or couetous, or foule ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker, with ſuch a one I ſay not to take meate. And <hi>2. Theſſal. 3.</hi> generallye: <hi>Denunciamus autem vobis, fratres, in nomine Domini Ieſu Chriſti, vt ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trahatis
<pb facs="tcp:7400:27"/>vos ab omni fratre ambulante inordinatè. &amp;c.</hi> We earneſtly and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſely declare vnto you (brethren) that you withdrawe your ſelues from eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye brother that liueth vnorderly And, <hi>Per epiſtolam hunc notate, &amp; nè com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſceamini cum illo.</hi> Geue me a note of him by your letters, and kéepe no company with him. Why? <hi>vt confun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>datur,</hi> to ſhame him. He talketh of leſſe ſinnes then hereſie. And is it the waye to ſhame heretikes, and ſo to reclaime them, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their ſayinges and ſingings are honoured with our preſence? To abſent our ſelues is, no doubt, a confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to them, and doth aſtoniſh them, although they be obſtinate.</p>
            <p>Euery Catholike muſt confeſſe that the Church of Chriſt vpon earth is vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="15"/> the members wherof muſt néedes be tyed together <hi>aliquo ſignaculorum vel Sacramentorum viſibilium conſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Li. 19. ca. 11 contra Fauſtum.</note> with ſome ſocietie of viſible ſignes or Sacramentes, as S. Auſten ſaith: èrgò they that ſecretly in heart are Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholikes, and viſibly in Sacramentes
<pb facs="tcp:7400:28"/>and ceremonies communicate with heretikes, flatly declare y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> they are not to be accompted of Chriſtes viſible and onely Church: which place being wel vrged, muſt néedes condemne them by their. Catholike opinion of the viſible Churche. For if al ſhould hide their faith, how ſhould the Churche appere? If others doo (God be thanked) innu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merable, and they doo not, how are they the children of one mother, the mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of one body? Or what priuiledge haue they, wheras it is neceſſary that many alwaies doo proteſt viſibly their religion, to be exempted from that ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> profeſſion? They cannot poſſibly cauel againſt it: for, <hi>Reliqui mihi ſeptem millia qui non curuauerunt genua an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te Baal.</hi> I haue left me ſeuen thouſand that haue not bowed their knées before Baal. An heretical obiection for their inuiſible Churche, is meant of them that in Hieruſalem euen then ſerued God openly in the Temple,
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> when Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as complained that in Samaria a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monge the tenne Tribes,
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>Relictus ſum
<pb facs="tcp:7400:28"/>ego ſolus.</hi> Or he ſpake it of the good men in the tenne Tribes. (S. Auſten <hi>Collat. contra Donat. cap. 20.</hi>) of zeale, becauſe he knewe but fewe.</p>
            <p>If nothing els did moue,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="16"/> yet verye zeale againſt the enemyes of Chriſte and his Churche ſhould cauſe a good Chriſtian to abſteine. <hi>Zelus domus tuę comedit me.</hi> The zeale of the houſe of God hath eaten me. And, <hi>Odiui eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiam malignantium, &amp; cum impiis no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſedebo. Lauabo inter innocentes ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus meas, &amp; circundabo altare tuum Domine.</hi> I hate the congregation of wicked men, &amp; with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vngodly I wil not ſitt. I wil waſh my hands among innocents, and compaſſe thy aultar, O Lord. That is: I wil embrace it with both hands, not geuing one to thée, and the other to thy aduerſarye. <hi>Dilexi de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corem domus tuae, &amp; locum habitatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis gloriae tuae.</hi> I haue loued the beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of thine houſe, and the place where thy glory dwelleth. Hath a cold Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like this zeale to Gods houſe againſt
<pb facs="tcp:7400:29"/>Sinagoge? to whom it may iuſtly be ſaide: <hi>Si videbas furem, currebas cum eo: &amp; cum adulteris portionem tuam ponebas. Exiſtimaſti iniquè quòd ero tui ſimilis.</hi> If thou ſaweſt a thiefe, thou diddeſt runne with him: and with the aduoulterous thou diddeſt take parte. Thou haddeſt a wicked ſurmiſe that I wil be like to thy ſelfe: a good gentle God to fauour thy ſinne, as thou doeſt fauour hereſie. <hi>Arguam te, &amp; ſtatuam contra faciem tuam.</hi> I wil lay it to thy charge, be thou ſure, and cal thée to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compt for it in the dreadful day.</p>
            <p>And becauſe men doo flatter them ſelues many wayes in this caſe,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="17"/> and thinke it great wiſedome and ſmal of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence to hide their conſcience for ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uauntage, by yéelding a litle. Let vs conſider certaine other wayes of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting to Infidels, not ſo wel knowe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to the ignorant,
<note place="margin">After the Admirals death Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritans did wear croſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes in Fraunce.</note> and yet make a mortal ſinn. <hi>Caietan, in ſummula, tit. Habitus mutatio. Si differentia certa diſtinctiua Chriſtianorum &amp; aliorum eſt, ita vt quilibet vtens tali habitu fateatur ſua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <pb facs="tcp:7400:29"/>fidem, mortale eſſet peccatum, puta, Chriſtianum deferre ſuper veſtes cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racterem O ex aliquo timore, vbi hoc eſt proprium ſignum Iudęorum; quia hoc nihil aliud eſt, quàm ex timore fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teri ſe Iudaeum.</hi> If there be a certaine diſtinct marke, whereby to know Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians and others a ſundre, ſo that any man by vſing that habite, thereby doth proteſt his faith, it were a mortal ſinn, for example, if a Chriſtian man for feare ſhould weare vpon his outwarde garment this letter O in that place where it is a peculier marke of the Iewes:
<note place="margin">The mark of here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tikes, cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiae. Apo. 19. of Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholikes ſignu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                  <g ref="char:cross">✚</g> Ezech. 9. If both beare one marke, howe shal Chriſt ſai: Cognoſco oues meas I knowe my sheep.</note> for that is nothing els but of feare to confeſſe him ſelfe a Iewe. Or if a Puritan abhorring from a fryers wéede, would for feare weare it, being a moſt certaine badge of a papiſt, he ſinneth mortally according to S. Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas concluſion <hi>de ratione errante,</hi> in my eight reaſon. Can there be a more manifeſt diſtinction of Catholikes and heretikes, then their Churches, their Sacramentes, their prayers, their ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons? In S. Auſtens time when it
<pb facs="tcp:7400:30"/>was demau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded, <hi>Quâ itur ad catholica<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>?</hi> Which is the waye to the Catholike Churche? were not their Churches plainly ſo diſtinct, that to aſke the way to either, was a token of his religion that aſked: like as the ſchiſmatical Samaritanes iudged Chriſte to be of the Iewes religion,
<note place="margin">Luc. 9.</note> 
               <hi>Quia facies eius erat euntis in Hieruſalem.</hi> Becauſe his face looked as if he were going to Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem. And therefore he could get no interteinment among them.</p>
            <p>It is al one to communicate with the deuil and with his miniſters. Sée then howe eaſily a man maye ſinne in this caſe, whereas, <hi>tollere ſignum</hi> (as they terme it) by that meanes to helpe the perſon bewitched, is, in the opinion of great learned men, a certaine co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication with the deuil. S. Hierom <hi>in vita S. Hilarionis</hi> noteth this eſpecially in the cure that he did vpon a maid be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>witched <hi>per tormenta verboru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentoſas figuras ſubter lime<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> domus pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ellae defoſſas,</hi> By tormenting wordes and monſtrous figures digged into the
<pb facs="tcp:7400:30"/>ground vnder the threſſhal of her doore. <hi>Noluit autem</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>ſanctus ante<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quàm purgaret virginem, ſigna iubere perquiri, nè ſolutis incantationibus, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsiſſe dęmon videretur.</hi> The holye man would not bid them looke out the ſignes or figures, leaſt it might ſéeme that the deuil departed by vndoing the inchauntmentes Alas howe common is this nowe adaies and many other meanes, eſtéemed very honeſt wayes, by ſignes, wordes, ceremonies, yea, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe they coniure flatly, and of purpoſe conſult with the deuil, they thinke the reſt is no communication with him: right ſo in our caſe you may conſider, where a man doth communicate with hereſie, and deny his faith by many in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>direct and couert wayes, neuer without mortal ſin, by wilful preſence, by Ox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forde proteſtations, <hi>quatenùs conſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tit verbo dei,</hi> as farre as it agreeth with the worde of God, by ſéeming to receaue although he doo not: by geuing his name to the vicar as hauing recea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued: by conceuing a new ſenſe whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his
<pb facs="tcp:7400:31"/>wordes import falſhood, &amp; muſt néedes ſounde conſent to the hearers, as being aſked of an heretike. Is the bodye of Chriſte in the bleſſed Sacrament? no forſooth, meaning in his viſible quanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. &amp;c. by whatſoeuer ſubtil and ſecret meanes of ſéeming to fauour their opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions. So he that in praying for the Quéene, vſed this ſtile, ſupreme gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of al perſons eccleſiaſtical and temporal: Although it be true in his ſenſe, yet his purpoſe was to haue it ſéeme, as though it were al one with the common ſtile. And ſo there be wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters that thinke S. Peter ſaying: <hi>Neſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cio hominem,</hi> ſpake it in this ſenſe: <hi>Neſcio purum hominem:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hieron. in 4. Math. &amp; Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>philactus in 22. Luc.</note> but neither did he ſo meane, and if he did, yet the hearers vnderſtoode him in the ſenſe that they vrged, and therfore it was ſo alſo a flatt denyal. <hi>Vide Auguſtinum varia genera mendaciorum lib. contra mendacium cap. 3. &amp; deinceps.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Another reaſon may be, becauſe this diſſimulation and indifferencie per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taineth to olde hereſies.
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="19"/> Firſt Baſili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des,
<pb facs="tcp:7400:31"/>
               <hi>(Niceph. li. 4. cap. 2.)</hi> among other monſterous heretikes, <hi>res nullo in diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crimine ponere docuit, <hi>adiaphorein,</hi> perinde at<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> tempore exigente, abſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> exceptione omni praeciſè fidem abiu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rare liceret.</hi> He taught men to be indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent to anye religion, as if it were lawful (the time ſo requiring) preciſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye without al exception to abiure the faith. The ſecond <hi>Helceſaitarum. (Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeb. li. 6. cap. 31. ex Origene) fidem ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gare indifferens quiddam eſſe. Qui e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nim interiore cogitatione rectè de fide ſentiat, tametſi ore cùm neceſsitas illu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> cò detruſerit, fidem perneget, eum ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men animo firmè illi adhaeſuru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> That to denye the faith is an indifferent thing, for he that in his heart inward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye hath a true beliefe, although with mouth, when neceſſitie vrgeth him, he denye his faith, yet in his minde he is readie to ſticke to it ſtedfaſtlye. Theſe make their grounde, neceſſitie, as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nye colde Catholikes doo, thinking ſo to be excuſed, and therfore, as S. Cipri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an writeth <hi>de lapſis</hi> in his time: <hi>Non
<pb facs="tcp:7400:32"/>expectauerunt ſaltem vt interrogati<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>negarent, ante aciem multi victi. &amp;c.</hi> They did not ſtay ſo longe as to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amined firſt, and the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> denye their faith, many yéelded before they beganne to fight. They preuent the law, leaſt they ſhould be vrged to their paine, calling it neceſſitie, when they muſt eyther doo it, or incurre a litle damage of diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure or libertie. But let them learne, that it was the perſuaſion of the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fane Count Magnus ſeruaunt to Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lens the Arrian Emperour, to the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike prieſtes and Deacons of Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>andria.
<note place="margin">Theodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritus li. 4. cap. 20.</note> 
               <hi>O miſeri, obſequimini, Arria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nae opinioni aſſentite. Nam diuinum nume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, licet illa quam colitis religio ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra ſit, ſi non veſtra ſponte ſed neceſsita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te adducti, ab ea diſcedatis, veniam vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis daturum eſt. Etenim in his quae ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsitate peccantur, relinquitur excuſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioni locus, Sed cùm ſua ſponte quiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam deliquerit, carere reprehenſione non poteſt.</hi> O wretched men, obeye a lawe, agrée to the Arrian religion: for the diuine godhead, although your re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion
<pb facs="tcp:7400:32"/>be true, if you reuolt from it, not of your owne accord, but by com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulſion, wil pardon you: for in ſuch of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences as are committed of neceſſitie, ſome excuſe wil be taken: but when a man ſhal offend wilfully, that cannot lacke blame and reproufe. But how li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle thoſe glorious Confeſſors wer mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued with this ethniſh perſuaſion, appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth in the ſtory. S. Auſten to ſignifie, that no neceſſitie in this caſe excuſeth,
<note place="margin">In laſp. 30</note> 
               <hi>Qui timendo mori mentitur, moritur antequàm moriatur, qui ideò mentie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>batur vt viueret.</hi> He that fering to dye, lyeth or diſſembleth, is dead before he dye, who therefore lied or diſſembled that he might liue. The thirde hereſie is <hi>Priſcilianiſtarum,</hi> of whom S. Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten writeth,
<note place="margin">Contra mond. ca. 6</note> that being demaunded their religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, they anſwerd, Catholiks, that is of the contrary to their profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, becauſe they would y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> better ſearch what was done among y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Catholikes. Whervpon certaine Catholikes thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king they might doo the ſame towardes thoſe heretikes by diſſembling in their conuenticles,
<pb facs="tcp:7400:33"/>to learne their miſteries,
<note place="margin">Non in verbis tan tùm eſt mendaciu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſed factis, vt prophe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tia.</note> gaue occaſion to S. Auſten to write <hi>contra mendacium,</hi> againſt lying or diſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling, as him ſelfe telleth <hi>lib. 2. retract. 60.</hi> concluding that it was not lawful in any wiſe.</p>
            <p>To ende, and, as it were, to bind faſt the concluſion of al theſe reaſons with the verdit of the Church, and eccleſiaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical Fathers of our time, when this queſtion was moued in the Councel of Trent, to ſatiſfie the doubtful conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, chiefly of our countryme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, Twelue of the beſt learned (one <hi>Petrus a Soto</hi>) choſen by the Councel to decide it, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced, <hi>omninò non licere,</hi> that it was in no caſe lawful. Being in England I ſaw their ſhort diſcourſe in writing. It is alſo the iudgement of the beſt learned Fathers and Profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſours in Rome, Ieſuites. And of ſo many as are ſound Cotholike diuines, of vpright iudgement, that haue no foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh pietie, to ſooth the feareful humour of their carnal frendes.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="chapter">
            <pb facs="tcp:7400:33"/>
            <head>¶ The 2. Chapter. Examples out of Scripture.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Apoſtaſie of Iero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boam, and the tenne Tribes is famous by theſe wordes: <hi>Erexit altare contra altare.</hi> He ſet vp another al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tare againſt the true aultar in Ieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem. He did ſacrifice him ſelfe out of Ieruſalem, made prieſtes other then Leuites. &amp;c.
<note place="margin">3. Reg. 13.</note> God therefore ſending his prophet to rebuke him, gaue ſtrait co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement, that he ſhould not eate nor drink with them, nor tary among them, which he dulye and truely obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, although the king him ſelfe inui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted him to his table. But being depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from thence, and fallen into the company of one thereaboutes, that would néedes interteine him, and cauſe him to eate, and becauſe he refuſed vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon Gods commaundement, tolde him that he alſo was the prophet of God, and did warrant him againſt al diſple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure
<pb facs="tcp:7400:34"/>and offence. This good meaning man belieued him, did eate and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate with the Samaritane: and what folowed? he was told by &amp; by y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he ſhould dye for it before he came home. A lion méeteth him in the way, and not hurting the aſſe, killed the credulous and diſobedient man, for communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting with ſchiſmatikes. A goodly exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple for Catholikes againſt the vngod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye perſuaſions of their frendes that ſay vnto them in this ſort: Why are you ſo ſcrupulous? is it ſo great a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to come to Churche?
<note place="margin">2. Eſdr. 6. is a notable example to reſiſt the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuaſion of falſe fren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des.</note> am not I Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike aſwel as you? I warrant you. Let them take héede of theſe falſe Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholikes more then of open heretikes, remembring that this man of God, whom Ieroboam the king could not perſuade, was perſuaded by one that named him ſelfe a prophet. S. Auſten. <hi>ep. 23. Quàm multi volebant eſſe Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholici manifeſta veritate commoti, &amp; offenſionem ſuorum reuerendo, quoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diè differebant.</hi> How many wold glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye haue bene Catholikes, becauſe ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt
<pb facs="tcp:7400:34"/>truth did moue them, and fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the diſpleaſure of their frendes, dayly differred it? Is it not verified here,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 36.</note> 
               <hi>Amici mei aduerſum me appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinquauerunt.</hi> My frendes approched againſt me?</p>
            <p>Againe, Elias and Elizeus, Oſeas and Amos liued among the ten ſchiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matical tribes to preache vnto them, but did not communicate with them in their vnlawful Sacrifice,
<note place="margin">Leuit. 17.</note> which was lawful onely in the Temple of Ieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem. <hi>Oſeae. 4.
<note place="margin">Amos. 5. &amp; Oſeae. 9</note> Nolite ingredi in Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gala, &amp; nè aſcenderitis in Beth-anen.</hi> Enter not into Galgal, and go not vp to Beth-anen: that is, <hi>domum iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatis,</hi> the houſe of iniquitie: or, <hi>domu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Idoli,</hi> the Idols houſe, becauſe of Iero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoams golde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> calues, which before was called Bethel. <hi>Domus Dei,</hi> The houſe of God. Againe, <hi>Si fornicaris tu Iſrael,</hi> If thou playe the harlott, that is, if thou runne after falſe religion, O Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael,
<note place="margin">Aug. lib. 1. contra Creſcon, cap. 32.</note> you Samaritanes or tenne Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bes, manifeſt heretikes and Schiſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tikes. (<hi>Sunt enim Samaritani veluti haeretici Iudaeorum:</hi> for the Samari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the
<pb facs="tcp:7400:35"/>Samaritanes are as heretikes fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Iewes) <hi>Non delinquat ſaltem Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da.</hi> Let not the Catholike Iuda offende by communicating with them. <hi>Parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceps idolorum Ephraim, dimitte eum.</hi> Ephraim (the ten tribes) taketh part with Idols, let him go, folow him not. S. Hierom in his Comment.
<note place="margin">In cap. 4. Oſcae.</note> 
               <hi>Super hę<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticos prona intelligentia eſt, ad quos, vel de quibus dicitur. Si ſemel fornica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris, haeretice, ſaltem tu eccleſiaſtice nè delinquas, nè ingrediaris in Galgala, haereticorum conciliabula, non eſt ibi domus dei, ſed domus Idoli.</hi> Concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning heretikes the vnderſtanding of this place is eaſie, to whom or of who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it is ſaide. If thou heretike playe the fornicatour from Chriſte, and his Churche, yet thou that art a Catholike man offend not with him, enter not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Galgal, that is, heretical Conuenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles. There is not the houſe of God, but the houſe of an Idol. Thus farre S. Hierome. Marke nowe this briefe compariſon. The Temple of Ieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem which onely had lawful Sacrifice,
<pb facs="tcp:7400:35"/>with ſhe Catholike Church, <hi>extra qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> non benè offertur, etſi ſacrificium va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leat.</hi> Out of the which Sacrifice is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer wel offred, although it ſelfe be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies of value. Beth-anen with the heretical Sinagoges which before were Bethel: the houſes of God, Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike Churches: The tenne Tribes with flat heretikes: Iuda, or the two Tribes in Ieruſalem with Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likes. Conſider the Prophetes wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des and the Doctors interpretation, and for our purpoſe it is very plaine. <hi>Tractat hunc locum Balduinus egregiè in hiſtoria ſua de collatione Donatiſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum &amp; Catholicorum, quam ſubiunxit Optato,</hi> which is much woorth the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding.</p>
            <p>The next example may be olde To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bie, <hi>Qui, cùm coeteri omnes irent in Bethel ad adorandos vitulos, hic ſolus fugit conſortia omnium, &amp; pergebat in Ieruſalem ad templum Domini. &amp;c. Hęc &amp; his ſimilia ſecundùm legem dei obſeruabat puerulus.</hi> Who, when al o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers went to Bethel to woorſhip the
<pb facs="tcp:7400:36"/>calues, he alone fled their company and went to Ieruſalem, the Temple of our Lorde. &amp;c. Theſe and other like thinges he obſerued according to the lawe of God being but a litle one. After when he was in Niniuée, <hi>Nunquam conta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minatus eſt in ęſcis eorum.</hi> He was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer polluted with their meates forbid by the lawe. Being vndoubtedly one of that number of whom God ſaide to E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lias: <hi>Reliqui mihi ſeptem millia qui<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>non curuauerunt genua ante Baal.</hi> I haue left to my ſelfe ſeuen thouſande that haue not bowed their knées be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Baal. O what an honour was it in ſuche an vniuerſal Apoſtaſie when Elias ſaide: <hi>Relictus ſum ego ſolus.</hi> I am lefte alone, to haue the glorious teſtimonie of Almightie God in the leſſer number of conſtant men. <hi>Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qui mihi.</hi> I haue left to me. Such are theſe fewe good Catholikes, which eyther beyonde the Seas or at home ſéeke to the Catholike Churche. They ſhal haue Tobyes bleſſing, an Angel
<pb facs="tcp:7400:36"/>to direct them in al their doinges, and the king Sennacherib ſhal (ſpite of his téeth) not hurt them.
<note place="margin">Heb. 1.</note> 
               <hi>Nolite time<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re puſille grex, Pater nam<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> meus pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rauit vobis Regnum.</hi> Feare not litle ſwéete flocke, for my Father hath pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared you a kingdome.</p>
            <p>Iudith foloweth, whoſe godlye and conſtant wiſedome if our Catholike gentlewomen woulde folowe, they might deſtroye Holofernes, the maſter heretike, and amaſe al his retinew, and neuer defile their religion by com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municating with them in anye ſmal poynt. She came to pleaſe Holofer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes,
<note place="margin">Iudith. 11.</note> but yet in her religion ſhe woulde not yéelde ſo muche as to eate of his meates, but brought of her owne with her, and tolde him plainelye, that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in his houſe, yet ſhe muſt ſerue her Lorde and God ſtil, deſiring for that purpoſe libertie once a day to goe in &amp; out y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> gate.
<note place="margin">Iudith. 12.</note> 
               <hi>Non potero manducare ex his quae praecipis mihi, ne veniat ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per
<pb facs="tcp:7400:37"/>me offenſio.</hi> I maye not eate of that which thou commaundeſt me, leaſt I incurre Gods diſpleſure. Which her conſtancie (a wonderful thing to tel) was the very means afterward, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by ſhe caried away his head ſafely, the porters preſuppoſing that ſhe went forth (as before) to pray to her God. He hoped wel to haue had the company of her body, and ſo to poſſeſſe her altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: but God did ſo direct her religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous mind, that ſhe confounded him and al his, not once touching of his meats: Her good maid waited vpon her al this time. And ſurely one conſtant Iudith ſhal eaſily make many like ſeruaunts, a thing much to be wiſhed, for the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike bringing vp of yonge gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>women, who otherwiſe are in daunger of Holofernes, and his vngratious mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters.</p>
            <p>For al yonge perſons the ſtorye of Daniel, and the other children is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenient, who refuſed alſo to eate of the kings meates, <hi>ne communicando pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luerentur,</hi> leaſt by co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>municating with
<pb facs="tcp:7400:37"/>them they might be polluted: which pleaſed God ſo wel, that they were in better liking after rootes and herbes, then the reſt after fleſh and fiſh.
<note place="margin">Daniel. 1. &amp; 6.</note> And concerning prayers, he was ſo farre from ioyning with Infidels, that he would not intermitt his owne daylye prayers toward the temple in Ieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem, when he knewe it was death by the kinges commaundement.</p>
            <p>The zeale of Matthathias and his ſonnes,
<note place="margin">1. Mach. 1. &amp;. 2.</note> 
               <hi>nè praeputium adducerent cum Gentilibus,</hi> rather then they would be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come vncircumciſed like the Gentiles: the death of Eleazarus rather then he would ſéeme to communicate:
<note place="margin">2. Mach. 6.</note> the care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful diligence of Eſdras and the reſt <hi>in ablegando mulieres alienigenas,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Eſdr. 9. &amp;. 2. Eſd. 13</note> in put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting away their forreine wiues, which ſignifie ſchiſmes and hereſies, as in the Prouerbes is plaine: the death of the ſeuen Machahées and their woorthye mother rather then they would co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicate:
<note place="margin">2. Mach. 7. Vide Ian<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenium in ca. 2.5.6.7.9.11.</note> the wiſe mans councel there ſo often to inculcate abſtaining from the company <hi>mulieris alienae, blandae, pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chrae,
<pb facs="tcp:7400:38"/>ſed ſtultae:</hi> of the woman that is a ſtraunger, and ſpeaketh faire, and is beautiful, but a very foole (hereſie vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedlye) the fal of Salomon ſo wiſe, ſo high in Gods fauour, <hi>Ex con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuetudine &amp; coniugiis foeminarum a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lienigenarum,</hi> By familiaritie and mariage of forreine women, the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe commaundement of God to the contrary. <hi>Non inibitis cum illis foedus.</hi> You ſhal neyther make nor meddle with them. <hi>No<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> dabitis filios veſtros fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liabus eorum.</hi> You ſhal not geue your ſonnes to their daughters, becauſe they wil peruert them, the ſame perillous effect ſo certainly enſuing, as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pſalme maketh mention,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 105.</note> 
               <hi>Commiſti ſunt inter<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gentes, &amp; didicerunt opera eorum, &amp; factum eſt illis in ſcandalu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> They min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gled them ſelues among the Gentiles, and learned their workes, and it was an occaſion to them of heynous ſinne: So many preceptes <hi>de non tangendo immundo,</hi> not to touche anye vncleane thinge, and if they did, to be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleane afterward: the zeale of the good
<pb facs="tcp:7400:38"/>Leuite, which would not ſtay in Iebus although it was towarde night.
<note place="margin">Iudicu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. 19. verſ. 12.</note> 
               <hi>Non ingrediar oppidum gentis alienae.</hi> I wil not enter into the towne of a for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reine Nation, that are not of the ſons of Iſrael.
<note place="margin">Geneſ. 34. verſ. 1. &amp;. 2.</note> 
               <hi>Dina egreſſa in vrbem alie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nigenarum, mox violata.</hi> Dina the daughter of Iacob wandring abrode into Sichem a towne of ſtraungers and Infidels, by and by defloured and corrupted: the anſwere of Ioſeder and Zorobabel to the Gentiles that offred to helpe them in building the Temple. <hi>Non poteſtis aedificare nobiſcum,
<note place="margin">1. Eſdr. 4. verſ. 3.</note> nos ſoli aedificabimus.</hi> You may not build with vs, we alone wil build: y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtraight charge to take nothing of the Anathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma,
<note place="margin">Ioſue 7. v. 13. &amp;. 25.</note> the death of Acham for the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye: the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundement to kil olde and yonge, not to ſpare the very infant. <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atus qui tenebit &amp; allidet paruulos tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>os ad petram.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Deut. 2.</note> Bleſſed is he that ſhal holde, and ſhal ſquiſe thy yonge ones againſt the rocke, the leaſt infant of that harlott Babilon. And,
<note place="margin">Cantic. 2. verſ. 15.</note> 
               <hi>Capite nobis vulpeculas paruulas, quae de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moliuntur
<pb facs="tcp:7400:39"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:7400:39"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:7400:40"/>vineam meam.</hi> Catche vs theſe litle foxes that ſpoile my vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard,
<note place="margin">Deut. 14.</note> aſwel the litle as the great, for they doo much harme alſo. <hi>Qui minima neglig it, paulatim defluit.</hi> He that is negligent in leſſer pointes, by litle and litle falleth to greater enormities.
<note place="margin">Deut. 16.</note> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, <hi>non rades caput in circulum, no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> incides carnes.</hi> Thou ſhalt not ſhaue thy head in compaſſe, thou ſhalt not cut or hewe thy fleſhe (becauſe it was a faſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhion of the Paynims) the paring of the captiue womens nailes and cut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting her heare, the great praiſe of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nye kinges in Iuda: <hi>veruntamen ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celſa non abſtulit,</hi> but he tooke not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way ſacrifices made vpon hilles, one point lacking to a perfect religious prince: that Salomon built a ſeueral houſe for Pharaos daughter and his wife,
<note place="margin">3. Reg. 7.</note> for reuerence to the temple, and arke of God, no Gentile to dwel nighe it:
<note place="margin">Exod. 4.</note> that Moyſes ſent awaye <hi>vxorem Madianitidem,</hi> his wife that was a Madianite and ſtraunger when he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came <hi>Dux populi Dei</hi> in Egipt:
<note place="margin">Heb. 11.</note> and
<pb facs="tcp:7400:40"/>that he would not be eſtéemed the ſonn of Pharao his daughter, but renoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing al the glory of Egipt, dealt onely with the people of God, that the verye name of <hi>Incircumciſus</hi> was odious &amp; abhominable. Theſe and other like <hi>(quae omnia in figura contingebant il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis)</hi> (Al which chaunced to them in fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gures (doo they not ſignifie that we ought to auoyde al ſocietie and felow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipp of error, and not to communicate with them in any ſmal poynt of reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, nor to reſerue any part thereof as indifferent, yea, rather to forſake wife and al deareſt frendes, then to commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicate with infidelitie?</p>
            <p>Laſt of al, to conclude this part of Scriptural examples,
<note place="margin">Epi. 76. fig. 3.</note> S. Ciprian doth much amplifie the crime of ſchiſme by the gréeuous puniſhment of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which conſented onely, and tooke anye part with Chore, Dathan, and Abyro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. <hi>Om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes omninò cum authoribus coniungi, qui fuerint eorum peccato contamina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti.</hi> That al are in puniſhment to be ioyned with the principal doers that
<pb facs="tcp:7400:41"/>ſhalbe polluted with partaking their ſinne. He concludeth thus: And when the ſonnes of Aaron <hi>offerentes alienu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ignem,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Leuit. 10.</note> did ſo offende, that the very <hi>thu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ribula eorum,</hi> their cenſars were tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned into <hi>laminas,</hi> and might not be v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, but kept for a memorial to the ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror of others: are not we afraide <hi>coo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perantes alienis oblationibus, precibus, concionibus, erroribus?</hi> Aſſiſting and furthering by our preſence heretical oblations, praiers, ſermons, other their errors. Here might be added out of the newe teſtament the primitiue example of the Chriſtians.
<note place="margin">Act. 1. &amp;. 4</note> 
               <hi>Hi omnes erant per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeuerantes vnanimiter in oratione.</hi> They continued with one accord euery one of them in prayer to God. And, <hi>Multitudinis credentium erat cor vnu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; anima vna. Coeterorum autem ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo audebat ſe coniungere illis.</hi> Of the number that beléeued there was one heart and one minde. And of the reſt that did not beléeue none durſt ioyne him ſelfe with them: according to the Pſalme. <hi>Qui inhabitare facis
<pb facs="tcp:7400:41"/>vnius moris in domo.</hi> That maketh his people to dwel in his houſe al of one maner and opinion. Is this ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued where heretikes and Catholiks méete in prayer together?
<note place="margin">In. 9. Oſeae</note> 
               <hi>Haereticoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> conciliabula</hi> (ſaith S. Hierome) <hi>non domus Dei appellantur, ſed ſpeluncae latronum.</hi> Heretical conuenticles are not called the houſe of God, but dennes of ſtrong théeues. But it is very likely, ſome man here wil ſay, that theſe for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer authorities are againſt Gentiles and Paynims, not againſt heretikes.
<note place="margin">In the third ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and his anſwer</note> Of this point I wil ſaye more after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde, whether of theſe are moſt to be ſhunned. In the meane time this I ſaye. That which in the olde Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is ſpoken literally of Gentiles and Idolatours, miſtically is referred of al auncient Fathers to heretikes in the newe lawe, as ſhal appere by the eccleſiaſtical examples next folowing, wherein it is manifeſt, that Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans did as muche abhorre from here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tikes, as the Iewes before from Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles,
<pb facs="tcp:7400:42"/>and no meruaile, becauſe Chriſte commaunded ſo in plain wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des:
<note place="margin">Mat. 18. verſ. 11.1</note> 
               <hi>Si eccleſiam non audierit, ſit tibi ſicut Ethnicus.</hi> If he wil not heare the Churche, let him be to thée as an Eth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nike.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="chapter">
            <head>¶ Examples out of eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Hiſtories.</head>
            <head type="sub">¶ The third Chapter.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>F S. Iohn in my firſt reaſon. <hi>Euſeb. li. 4. ca. 13. ex Irenaeo</hi> writeth, <hi>Ioanne<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Domini Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipulum, cùm Epheſi ad balnea ſe confer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret, intus<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> videret Cerinthum haereti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum, ſe mox è balneo illotum proripu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſſe, &amp; dixiſſe: fugiamus ociùs, nè bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neum in quo eſt Cerinthus veritatis aduerſarius extemplò corruat.</hi> That S. Iohn our Lordes Diſciple going to the Bathes at Epheſus, and ſeing the heretike Cerinthus within, immediat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye leaped out of the bathe vnwaſhed, and ſaide: Let vs flée hence in al haſte,
<pb facs="tcp:7400:42"/>leaſt the bathe wherin Cerinthus the enemy of truth is, fal preſently. In the ſame place, of S. Policarpe S. Iohns ſcholler, <hi>Marcioni in eius conſpectum venienti ac roganti, Noſce nos amabo, Reſpondit, Noui quidem primogenitu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Sathanae.</hi> When Marcion the heretike came into his ſight, and ſaid ambitiouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye to him: Knowe vs, Sir, I beſéeche you. I know thée (quoth he) to be an olde babe, or the firſt begotten of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan. And be addeth generally of others: <hi>Talem nam<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> tùm Apoſtoli,
<note place="margin">Niceph. li. 3. ca. 30.</note> tùm illo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum diſcipuli adhibuerunt cautionem, vt nè ſermonem quidem cum aliquo illorum qui veritatem ſuis commentis adulterare nitebantur, aliquando con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre vellent, ſicut Paulus admonet, hę<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticum hominem deuita. &amp;c.</hi> For the Apoſtles and their ſcollers were ſo wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye and circumſpect in this caſe, that they would not ſo much as once reaſon the matter with any of them that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deuoured by their leaſinges to corrupt the truth, according to S. Paules ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monition: Shunne the man that is an heretike and auoyde him.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:7400:43"/>
            <p>And therfore Ignatius the Apoſtles ſcholler alſo, writeth, <hi>epiſt. 6. ad Phila<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delphenſes. Fratres, ne erretis: Si quis eum ſectatur qui ſe abſciderit à verita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te, regnum dei non haereditabit.</hi> My brethren, be not deceaued: If a man folow his faction that hath cut off him ſelfe from the truth, he ſhal not inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite the kingdome of God. And leaſt they might vnderſtand him of conſent in opinion, he addeth: <hi>Et qui non abſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedit à mendaci concionatore, in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hennam condemnabitur. Nec enim à piis diſcedendum, nec cum impiis co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mercia habenda.</hi> And he that goeth not awaye from a falſe preacher, ſhalbe damned into hel, for neither muſt we depart from the godlye, nor haue anye dealing with vngodlye and wicked men.</p>
            <p>Of Origen Euſebius telleth <hi>(li.
<note place="margin">Niceph. li. 5. Cap. 4.</note> 6. ca. 3.) quòd neceſsitate compulſus in eadem familia degere cum Paulo quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam heretico, tamen per idem tempus, euidentia catholicę ſuę opinionis iudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cia oſtendere non dubitauit.</hi> That
<pb facs="tcp:7400:43"/>although of neceſſitie he was forced to liue in one houſe with one Paule an heretike, yet at the ſelfe-ſame time he doubted not to ſhewe euident tokens of his Catholike opinion. Wherin? <hi>Nam cùm frequens multitudo, non hęretico<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum tantummodò, ſed noſtrorum eti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am, propter ſingularem dicendi vim quę in Paulo ineſſe videbatur, ad eum accederent, Origenes tamen nunquàm induci poterat, vt precibus vnà cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> illo intereſſet.</hi> For when a great multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, not onely of heretikes, but of our men alſo, for a ſinguler grace of vtte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance that ſéemed to be in Paule, came vnto him (as our Catholikes gladlye run to fine heretical ſermons) yet Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gen could neuer be induced to be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent at prayer &amp; diuine ſeruice w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> him. Why ſo? <hi>Quippe qui ab ineunte ętate &amp; eccleſię canonem obnixè obſeruaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſet, &amp; (vt ipſe in quoda<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> libro loquitur) erroru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> doctrinas fuiſſet ſemper deteſta tus.</hi> As one who from his youth both had ſtraitly obſerued the Canon of the Church, and (as himſelfe ſpeaketh in a
<pb facs="tcp:7400:44"/>certaine booke) had alwaies deteſted erroneons doctrine. Two thinges are here to be noted, that he had that zeale of a childe, and eſpecially that it was the Canon or rule of the Church ſo to doo:
<note place="margin">Vide Can 44.45.</note> which rule is plaine in the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons of the Apoſtles. <hi>Can. 63. Si quis clericus aut laicus Sinagogam Iudaeo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum aut haereticorum conuenticulum ingreſſus fuerit, vt preces cum illis con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iungat, deponitor, &amp; à communione ſecluditor.</hi> If anye of the Clergie or laye man ſhal enter into the Iewes Sinagoge, or the conuenticle of here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tikes,
<note place="margin">Vide ep. Firmilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni apud Cipr. 75. a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertiſsimu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nium con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſuetudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. nu. 7. fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtra iam dubitat. &amp;c.</note> to praier among them, let him be depoſed and excommunicated. If a Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiller ſay it toucheth not them that are preſent onely, and ſay their own prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers: the gréeke readeth to <hi>ſuneuxasthai</hi> to praye with them, or <hi>proſeuxasthai,</hi> to pray <hi>ſimpliciter</hi> without any addition. And Origen folowing the Canon, <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duci non poterat, vt precibus vnà cum illo intereſſet.</hi> Could not be induced to be preſent onely at prayer with the he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retike.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:7400:44"/>
            <p>Heraclas biſhop of Alexandria was Origens chief ſcholler, &amp; as it wer, Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>techiſt vnder him. <hi>Euſeb. li. 6. ca. 12.</hi> Of him Dioniſius Alexandrinus hauing ſpoken of heretical bookes not to be read, but with great iudgement, ſaith:
<note place="margin">Euſeb. li. 7 cap. 6.</note> 
               <hi>Iſtum Canonem iſtud<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> exemplum a beato Papa noſtro Heracla cepi. Ille nam<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> eos qui ab eccleſia abſceſsiſſent, cùm eſſent accuſati, quòd conſuetudine cuiuſdam eorum qui aliena<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> à ſide doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trinam tuebantur, multum vſi fuiſſent, Eccleſia eiecit. &amp;c.</hi> This Canon or rule (ſaith he) and this example I receaued of our holy Father Heraclas: for he excommunicated them that were de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted out of the Catholike Churche, when they were accuſed to haue kept company verye much with any of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that did mainteyne contrary doctrine to the true faith.</p>
            <p>Athanaſius that mightie Champio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> againſt the Arrians comming to Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oche where one Leontius was biſhop, <hi>Eum, vt à Catholica fide auerſum de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uitauit, at<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> cum illis qui Euſtathiani
<pb facs="tcp:7400:45"/>vocabantur, communicauit, conuentu in ędibus priuatis peracto.</hi> Shunned him as one turned from the Catholike faith, and he communicated with them that were called Euſtathians (becauſe they helde with their Catholike Biſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop Euſtathius depriued) making aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblies in prinate houſes. And <hi>Sozo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men. lib. 3. ca. 9.</hi> of the ſame, he did ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther pray with Catholikes in priuate houſes, then with Leontius in the Churche. Of which Leontius by the way it is not amiſſe to note what a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembler and double dealer he was, that they nowe a dayes which are like vnto him,
<note place="margin">Athanaſ. apud The od. lib. 2. cap. 24.</note> may be aſhamed. <hi>Etenim cùm cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum &amp; laicam multitudinem in duas partes diuiſam cerneret,</hi> For when he ſawe that the Clergie and laye multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude were deuided into two partes, (ſome Arrians, ſome Catholikes, or Homuſians) and that the one company ſange <hi>Gloria Patri, &amp; Filio, &amp; Spiritui Sancto,</hi> Glory be to the Father, and to the Sonne, and to the holy Ghoſt, to make them equal: the other <hi>per filium
<pb facs="tcp:7400:45"/>in ſpiritu ſancto.</hi> Glory be to the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by the ſonne in the holy Ghoſt, to make them vnequal. <hi>Ipſe totam glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficationem tacitus ſecum recitauit.</hi> He ſaide ſecretly to him ſelfe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whole <hi>Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria Patri</hi> (becauſe he would offend ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther part) &amp; in the end only pronounced <hi>In ſecula ſeculorum,</hi> ſo loude, that they which were next him, might heare it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Eulogius primarius pręſ biter Ediſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenorum,</hi> a prieſt of Edeſſa,
<note place="margin">Theodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, li. 4. cap. 16.</note> one of the chiefe, whoſe praiſe is in the eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal hiſtory, being exhorted by Modeſtus that perſecuted Catholikes vnder Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lens the Arrian Emperour, in theſe wordes: <hi>Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munica cum Imperatore.</hi> Communicate with the Emperour, doo as he doth, ſhunne him not becauſe he is an Arrian, anſwered: <hi>Nunquid cum imperio eſt ſacerdotis dignitatem conſecutus?</hi> I pray you, Sir, quoth he, hath he with the Empire obteined alſo prieſtly or biſhoply dignitie? mening y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they muſt folow their Catholike Biſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop Barſes who was depriued, &amp; not y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Emperor. The gentlema<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> being offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
<pb facs="tcp:7400:46"/>at this aunſwere, I ſaide not ſo, you dolt, quoth he: <hi>Sed vos, vtì, quibuſcum communicet Imperator, cum iiſdem communicetis, adhortatus ſum.</hi> But I exhorted you al to communicate with them, with whom the Emperour him ſelf doth communicate, meaning with Lupus and other Arrian Biſhops: and ſo baniſhed foure ſcore of them at once. Of whom the two chiefe, this Eulogi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us and Protegines being ſent, as God would haue it, <hi>ad Antinoen in The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bais,</hi> a prouince in Egipt, after they perceaued that the Biſhop of that Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie was of their religion, they commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicated with the Clergie there in ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical aſſemblyes at Churche and otherwiſe. Marke, They did forſake the eccleſiaſtical Conuenticles of Arri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Biſhops, and being baniſhed for it, finding there a Catholike Biſhopp, ſtraight they communicated with him. Is not this our caſe?</p>
            <p>The petition of Alexander Biſhop of Conſtantinople is memorable,
<note place="margin">Theodor. li. 1. cap. 14.</note> whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Emperour Conſtantine was ſedu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced
<pb facs="tcp:7400:46"/>by the Arrians to permit that Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us might be receaued into the Church, and the Catholike Communion, <hi>Iſta duo à deo poſtulauit, ſic loquutus. Si Arius cras in Eccleſia conuentus aget, dimitte me ſeruu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> tuu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; nè ſimul per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das pium cum impio: ſin clemens par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces eccleſiae tuae, conſidera verba Euſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bianorum, &amp; nè des in ruinam haeredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatem tuam: tolle Arium de medio, nè illo in eccleſiam ingreſſo, tùm haereſis vnà cum eo ingreſſa videatur, tùm de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inceps impietas pietatis locu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> occupet.</hi> He requeſted theſe two things of God, ſpeaking thus: If Arius to morowe ſhal make conuenticles in the Church, let me thy ſeruaunt depart, and deſtroy not the godly man together with the vngodly: but if thou wilt mercifullye ſpare thy Churche, conſider the wordes of the Euſebians (Arrians) and geue not ouer thine heritage to ruine and decaye. Take Arius out of the waye, leaſt if he enter into the Churche, both hereſie may ſéeme to haue entred toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with him, &amp; in time wicked blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemie
<pb facs="tcp:7400:47"/>againſt God may poſſeſſe the place of Gods true religion. He wiſhed to dye rather then to be in the Church with Arius and his company. What folowed? <hi>Arius ingreſſus latrinas, poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cente ventris neceſsitate, crepuit medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us. Alexander conuentum cum omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus fratribus celebrare, preces fundere. &amp;c.</hi> Before y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> time was come to make their aſſemblye, Arius going to a houſe of office, becauſe he was taken ſhort as he was in the ſtréete, there powred out his bowels. Alexander that Catholike Biſhop aſſembled his brethren y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie together, prayed and gaue thankes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Paulus praeſbiter Euſtachii Antio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheni Epiſcopi hac de re laudatur, quòd ſe nunquàm haereticorum com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munione polluerat.</hi> Paulinus a Prieſt of Antioche vnder the Biſhop Euſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chius is very famous, and hath a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guler co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mendation for this point, that he neuer defiled him ſelfe by communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cating with heretikes. <hi>Hieron.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To come from the Clergie to the laye multitude, which is néerer to our
<pb facs="tcp:7400:47"/>purpoſe. <hi>Septimana ſacroſancta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tecoſten ſubſequenti, populus (Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>andrinus) vbi ieiunauerat, in coemite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rium proptereà ad orationem egredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, quòd omnes Georgii deteſtaren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur communionem.</hi> In Whitſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wéeke the people of Alexandria after they had faſted (as the faſhion then was, and nowe is, in the Churche) go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth out into the Churchyarde, to praye for this occaſion, becauſe al of them de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſted communicating or being in the Churche with George the heretical Biſhopp: wherein they were ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant, proteſting thereby the Catholike faith againſt the Arrian Biſhop, that they ſuffered diuers and gréeuous per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutions, as Athanaſius telleth. <hi>lib. 2. cap. 14. apud Theodoritum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>De Samoſatenſibus ſic idem Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor. lib. 4. cap. 14. Poſteaquàm Ariani gregem Paſtore longè optimo (Euſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bio) priuârant, &amp; alterum in eius fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogârant locum (Eunomium,) nemo ex vrbis incolis, vel preſſus aegeſtate, vel diuitiis affluens, famulus vel arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fex,
<pb facs="tcp:7400:48"/>agricola vel conſitor, vir vel mulier, iuuenis vel ſenex, ad conuentu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eccleſiaſticum accedere voluit, ſed epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcopus ſolus agebat. Quippe nemo aut in eius venit conſpectum, aut cum eo ſermonem contulit, licet diceretur vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tam apud eos valdè modeſtè inſtituiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe.</hi> After that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Arrians had depriued y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> flocke of their excellent and moſt ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous Shepperd (Euſebius their Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike Biſhop) and had ſtalled ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in his roome (Eunomius,) none of the inhabitantes there, poore or rich, ſeruaunt or artificer, huſbandman or grafter, man or woman, yonge or olde, would come to the Churche, but the Biſhop was there al alone: for no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> would either come into his ſight, or talke with him, albeit he was reported to haue vſed him ſelfe very modeſtly &amp; quietly among them. This example ſerueth againſt them that co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>municate with their heretical Biſhop or vicar, becauſe he is a gentle perſon forſoothe, and his wife a verye honeſt woman: ſuch fonde reaſons fooliſh Catholikes haue.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:7400:48"/>
            <p>I might adde here the zeale of that people that would not waſh in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bathe where the Biſhop waſhed.
<note place="margin">Theodor. ibidem.</note> 
               <hi>Sed aquam hereticae nequitie contagione infecta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſſe rati, eam in cloacam emittunt, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uam<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ſibi infundi imperant.</hi> But ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing the very water was infected with the filth of heretical wickednes, caſt it out into the ſinke, and commau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded newe water to be powred in. And that the very boyes and children play<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at the bal in the ſtrete, which chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to fal vnder the aſſes féete whervp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon Lucius the Arria<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Biſhop did ride, would not play with it againe, til they had ſenſed it vp and downe in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> flame of the fire, ſo to purge it. But I wil adde one example more of the multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude abhorring eccleſiaſtical conuenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles or co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming to Church among ſuch perſons.</p>
            <p>Whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Liberius the Biſhop of Rome was baniſhed,
<note place="margin">Theodor. lib. 2. ca. 17.</note> and one Felix placed for him, <hi>Tametſi fidem Niceni Concilij ſeruauit integram, tamen quia cum A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rianis liberè communicauit, nemo ex
<pb facs="tcp:7400:49"/>Romae habitatoribus in eccleſiam, dum ille intùs erat, ingredi voluit.</hi> Although he mainteyned euery point of the Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cene Councel concerning faith, yet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he fréely communicated with Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians, none of the Inhabitantes of Rome would enter into the Church ſo long as he was within. Which was ſignified to the Emperour Conſtanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us <hi>per praeſtantes foeminas,</hi> by women of good calling, who firſt threatned their noble huſbands, that vnleſſe thei did obteine of his grace, that their Biſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhopp Liberius might returne, they would forſake them and go where he was. Afterward by the aduiſe of their fearful huſbandes, them ſelues went to intreate the Emperour, richlye ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parelled like vnto Iudith, the ſooner to moue him, as in déede they did, and Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berius was called home. A woorthy ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample for noble gentlewomen to fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe: Note moreouer, that al true Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholikes then refuſed to communicate with Felix, not becauſe he was an he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retike, but becauſe he was content to
<pb facs="tcp:7400:49"/>communicate with them, and to be made Biſhopp by them. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is written of him thus: <hi>Foelix pro Liberio ab Arianis factus Ponti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fex, non tàm ſectae diuerſitate, quàm communionis &amp; ordinationis conni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uentia maculatur.</hi> Felix being made Biſhop of Rome by the Arrians in Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berius place, blotted his eſtimatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, not ſo much for diuerſitie of ſect or opinie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as for yéelding to communicate with them, and to be conſecrated Biſhop of them. By occaſion whereof it ſéemeth very expedient in this place to adde ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples of ſuch glorious Catholikes that refuſed to receaue the Sacramen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes at heretikes handes, for that alſo pertaineth to this queſtion, and to the ſtate of our countrey.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ Sacramentes not to be receaued of heretikes or ſchiſmatikes.</head>
               <p>AFter that Euſebius was firſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priued, and after a Martyr,
<note place="margin">Theodor. li. 4. ca. 14.</note> the
<pb facs="tcp:7400:50"/>aforenamed Samoſatenſis agreed to haue Antiochus his ſiſters ſonne their Biſhop, <hi>Virum multis rectè factis no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilitatum, &amp; qui praeclatè pro diuina doctrina decertaſſet. Ita<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> cùm omnes ad vnum Antiocho ſuffragati eſſent, &amp; ad ſacram menſam deduxiſſent, coegiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> genua flectere, ſimul ac conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus vidit Iouianum (qui aliquandò co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munioni Arianae adhaeſerat) dexteram ſibi imponentem, manum eius repulit, imperauit<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> vt à numero eorum qui ipſum conſecrarent, ſegregaretur, dix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>it<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ſe nullo modo ferre poſſe dextra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> illam ſibi imponi, que ſacra miſteria per blaſphemiam conſecrata recepe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rat.</hi> A man for<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> many good déedes verye famous, and one that had woorthelye ſtoode in the maintenance of Gods di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine doctrine. Therfore, when al, with out exception had geuen their voices to Antiochus, and had brought him to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy table (the aultare) and made him knéele, caſting his head backe as ſoone as he ſawe Iouian lay his hande vpon him (who ſomtime had communicated
<pb facs="tcp:7400:50"/>with the Arians) he thruſt away his hande, and willed that he might be ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perated from the number of them that ſhould conſecrate him, ſaying that he would by no meanes ſuffer, that the ſame hande ſhould be laide vpon him that had receaued the bleſſed Sacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t conſecrated by a tonge that had conſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to blaſphemy: meaning that he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing otherwiſe a Catholike, yet had ſaide Maſſe among the Arrians. It ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth againſt ignorant Catholikes that receaue the bleſſed Sacrament conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crated by our ſchiſmatical prieſtes,
<note place="margin">Vide ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emplum Satiri quod ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitur.</note> and thinke it is very wel done.</p>
               <p>Moſes the Eremite a very wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful man by the meanes of Mania Quéene of the Saracenes was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained to be their Biſhop,
<note place="margin">Sozom. li. 6. cap. 38.</note> muche a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his wil, of humilitie refuſing. <hi>Quòd ſi verò mihi hoc munus, cùm ſim planè eo indignus, dei voluntate deſeratur, eum teſtor, quod tuas manus ſanguine ſanctorum virorum reſper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſas mihi non impones.</hi> But if it be the wil of God (quoth he) that this office
<pb facs="tcp:7400:51"/>muſt néedes be put vpon me, whereas I am altogether vnwoorthy of it, I cal him to witnes, that thou ſhalt not laye thy handes vpon me that art ſprinkled with the bloud of holy men. He ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth to Lucius biſhopp of Alexandria that perſecuted Catholikes vnder Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lens the Arrian. <hi>Magiſtratus igitur Romani, reiecto Lucio, eum ad epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos qui iam tum aetatem in exilio de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gebant, recta deducunt, à quibus fac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus eſt epiſcopus.</hi> Whervpon the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates of Rome reiecting Lucius, bring him ſtraight to the Catholike Biſhops, which at that time liued in baniſhment, of whom he was conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crated Biſhop.</p>
               <p>What a woorthy Emperour Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doſius Magnus was,
<note place="margin">Socrat. li. 5. cap. 6.</note> who hath not heard at the leaſt? <hi>Is cùm propter mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bi grauitatem baptizari properaret, primu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſciſcitabatur ab epiſcopo (Theſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalonicenſi) quam fidem amplexaretur. At cùm epiſcopus reſpondiſſet, opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onem Arij minimè per Illyrium per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaſiſſe, ſed omnes illius loci Nicenam
<pb facs="tcp:7400:51"/>fidem ſemper obſeruaſſe, Imperator ab Aſcholio (epiſcopo) libentiſsimo ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo baptiſmum recepit.</hi> He, when vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> occaſion of daungerous ſicknes made haſt to be baptiſed, firſt of al he aſked the biſhop (of Theſſalonica) of what re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion he was. And when he had aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, that Arius opinion had not paſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſed through Illyria, but that al therea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boutes did alwayes kéepe the Nicene fayth, the Emperour moſt gladly rece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued Baptiſme of him. Adde here by the waye,
<note place="margin">Li. 4. ca. 62 de vita e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ius.</note> that Euſebius hiſtorie of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantine the great his baptiſme at Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comedia by the Arrian Biſhops is not allowed, becauſe it is in no caſe likely, that ſo Catholike an Emperour that made ſuch lawes againſt the Arians and their bookes, would be baptiſed of them, but rather, as the Catholike tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is, of Silueſter Biſhop of Rome,
<note place="margin">Melch. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Canus de hiſto. li. 11.</note> where is to be ſéene to this daye <hi>Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſterium Conſtantini,</hi> The Fonte of Conſtantine. But becauſe ſome man maye thinke that the Baptiſme of the Arrians was iuſtlye refuſed, and
<pb facs="tcp:7400:52"/>and of neceſſitie, <hi>Propter formam ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borum mutatam,</hi> albeit I think Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doſius neuer conſidered ſo déeply, but onely that they were heretikes, <hi>(quę<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rebat enim de fide epiſcopi, no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> de for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma baptiſmi)</hi> let vs adde ſuch a Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monie to the former aboue mentioned as admitteth no cauel.</p>
               <p>Satyrus a vertuous gentleman and brother to S. Ambroſe,
<note place="margin">D. Ambr. de obitu fratris.</note> ſayling into A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frike, <hi>nondum perfectioribus initiatus miſteriis,</hi> (eyther <hi>Catechumenus</hi> or <hi>Neophitus</hi>) lately made a Chriſtian, carying about him a conſecrated hoſte, which other gaue him, more auncient Chriſtians, in great daunger of drow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, was by it ſo miraculouſly preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, that he longed to receaue that ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred miſterie into his mouth, which before he neuer had done, as it ſéemeth. <hi>Nam qui tantum miſterij coeleſtis in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoluti in orario pręſidium fuiſſet ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertus, quantum arbitrabatur, ſi ore ſumeret, &amp; toto pectoris hauriet arca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no.</hi> For he that had tried ſo great ayde of that heauenly miſterie, only wrap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped
<pb facs="tcp:7400:52"/>vp in a napkin, what did he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue would be, if he might take it in his mouth, and ſuck it with the whole ſecrete of his heart. But notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding his excéeding deſire, would he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue it of euery prieſt trow you? <hi>Sed non ita auidus fuit vt eſſet incautus. Aduocauit ad ſe epiſcopum, perconta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> eſt ab eo, vtrumnam cum epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pis Catholicis, hoc eſt, cum Romana ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſia conueniret: &amp; fortè in ſchiſmate regionis illius eccleſia erat; Lucifer e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nim (Epiſcopus) ſe à noſtra communio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne diuiſerat. Ita<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> eò tranſire maluit, v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bi tutò poſſet exoluere (quod vouerat) &amp;c.</hi> But he was not ſo gréedie, that he would be vnaduiſed or héedleſſe. He cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the Biſhopp to him, and aſked of him, whether he did agrée with the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike biſhops, that is, with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Church of Rome or no: Nowe it happened that the Churche of that countrey was in ſchiſme, becauſe Lucifer their Biſhop had deuided him ſelfe from communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cating with vs. And therefore (ſaith S. Ambroſe of his brother) he rather
<pb facs="tcp:7400:53"/>choſe to paſſe ouer the Seas thither where he might ſafely performe that which he had vowed concerning the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceauing of the bleſſed Sacrament. It is long to tel al,
<note place="margin">Hier. cont. Lucifer.</note> but much woorth the reading. This Lucifer was a very fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Catholike Biſhop and maintey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of the Nicene fayth, but in the end a Schiſmatike, and authour of the Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciferians. This gentleman rather then he would receaue the bleſſed Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of him, aduentured the Seas a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine into Italie, where he receaued of Catholikes. S. Ambroſe maketh it a proufe <hi>ſummae eius in Dei cultum ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruantię,</hi> of his ſinguler reuerence to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward the woorſhipp of God, <hi>qui nulla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> veram putauit niſi verae fidei gratiam.</hi> Who thought that to receue of a ſchiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matike or heretike had no effect of grace Not as though grace depended of the miniſter, but becauſe he that witting<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>municateth with ſuch miniſters, maketh him ſelf vnwoorthy and vnapt to receaue ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tal grace.
<note place="margin">Notandu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note> Note here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withal this ſentence of S. Ambroſe:
<pb facs="tcp:7400:53"/>
                  <hi>Scimus pleroſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> auiditate ſtudii prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termittere cautionem.</hi> We know that many men for greedy zeale are nothing warie and circumſpect in theſe caſes, as they ſhould be, againſt ſuch as care not, ſo they may be confeſſed and receaue of a prieſt,
<note place="margin">Eccleſi. 7.</note> whether he be ſchiſmatical or no. The wiſe man ſaith: <hi>Noli eſſe iuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus nimiùm:</hi> Be not ouer iuſt, but in time and place, and other circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. S.
<note place="margin">Epiſt. 77.</note> Ciprian doth comfort certaine Confeſſours prieſtes, who being con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned <hi>ad fodinas,</hi> to digge in mine pittes, and gladlye would haue ſaide Maſſe, but could not, not to thinke it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny damage, their Confeſſion &amp; Martyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome to ſupply the Sacrifice, or rather to be a ſufficient Sacrifice. When it cannot be done, but by communicating with heretikes, <hi>ſolutio diuinae gratiae in affectu &amp; fide eſt,</hi> ſaith S. Ambroſe.
<note place="margin">Vbi ſupra</note> Our good purpoſe and intent due to God for his grace beſtowed vppon vs, maye be perfourmed in affection and faythful deſire, when we cannot doo the thinge it ſelfe that we purpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed.
<pb facs="tcp:7400:54"/>that we purpoſed. And that yonge no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble gentleman is much praiſed, who méeting the bleſſed Sacrament when an heretike caried it, would not adore, leaſt ſo he might ſéeme to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>municate with him. So, to heare Maſſe is good, but to hear the Maſſe of a ſchiſmatical prieſt, or of him that is ſuſpended for kéeping a concubine, is expreſly forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den.
<note place="margin">Pſal. 98.</note> 
                  <hi>Honor Regis iudicium diligit.</hi> The honor of the prince loueth diſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and iudgement. A good thing done vndiſcretly, &amp; without due circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, doth not honor God nor pleaſe him. This by the way: nowe to our former purpoſe of the Sacramentes.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Athanaſius in epi. ad omnes Ortho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doxos. Cùm eccleſię miniſtri perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionem patiuntur, populi impietatem Arianorum execrantes, malunt ita morbis contabeſcere ac periclitari, qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Arianorum manus ſuis capitibus im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poni.</hi> When ſpiritual men that haue cure of ſoules ſuffer perſecution, the people deteſting the wickednes of the Arians, wil rather pine awaye with
<pb facs="tcp:7400:54"/>ſicknes, and abide al daunger, then ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer the Arians to laye their handes on their heades. He ſéemeth to ſpeake of the Sacramentes of penance &amp; anoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling: for he ſaith: <hi>Eos abſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> viſitatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis obſequio infirmari.</hi> That they are ſicke, and that there is no prieſt to vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite them. And becauſe they were wont alſo <hi>ſumere viaticum,</hi> to take their wayfare the bleſſed Sacrament, the caſe is like, which they choſe rather to lack vndoubtedly at the point of death, then to take it of an Arrian. One place more to this purpoſe may not be omit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Victor Vticenſis li. 2. de Arianorum perſecutione Vandalica.</hi> When Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike Biſhops and prieſtes were ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried away-into baniſhment, <hi>Innumera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilis populus occurrentes, &amp; ſuos infan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tulos veſtigiis martyrum proiicientes, iſta voce clamabant. Quibus nos miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ros relinquitis, dum pergitis ad coro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nas? Qui hos baptizaturi ſunt paruu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>los fontibus aquę perennis? Qui nobis poenitentię munus collaturi ſunt, &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:7400:55"/>reconciliationis indulgentia obſtrictos peccatorum vinculis ſoluturi? Qui nos ſolennibus orationibus ſepulturi ſunt morientes? A quibus diuini ſacrificij ritus exhibendus eſt conſuetus? &amp;c.</hi> An innumerable multitude of people run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to méete them, and caſting their infantes at the Martyrs féete, cried out in this maner: To whom doo you leaue vs poore wretches, whiles you go to be crowned? who ſhal chriſten theſe litle ones in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fontes of euerlaſting water? who ſhal beſtowe vpon vs the benefite of penance and lowſing vs from al the bandes of ſinne by pardoning and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciling vs? who ſhal burye vs when we dye with ſolemne prayers? who ſhal celebrate the accuſtomed ceremony of the diuine ſacrifice? in effect, who ſhal ſay Maſſe. &amp;c. Some man might haue aunſwered, there are other to doo it in their roomes. Yea, but they knew right wel, that they were al heretikes, and therefore they mourned for want of the Sacramentes, as being determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned not to communicate with them.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:7400:55"/>
               <p>To conclude with a Canon of the Apoſtles concerning the Clergie,
<note place="margin">Can. 45.</note> eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially whoſe good example is an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction to the people. <hi>Epiſcopum aut pręſ biterum qui hęreticorum baptiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma aut ſacrificium ſuſceperit, deponi pręcipimus.</hi> A Biſhop or a prieſt that ſhal take the Baptiſme or ſacrifice of heretikes, we geue expreſſe commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement that ſuch a one be depoſed: <hi>ton dexamenon</hi> him that doth alow it by pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, winking at it, not ſhunning the parties, not preaching againſt them, frequenting their conuenticles: for it foloweth: <hi>Quę etenim conuentio inter Chriſtum &amp; Belial? aut quę particula fideli cum infideli?</hi> For what agre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is there betwéene Chriſte and Belial? or what litle portion or ſocie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie hath the faithful man with the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidel? vnleſſe you wil vnderſtand it of falſe Baptiſme and polluted Sacrifice, which may alſo be the ſenſe and mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning.</p>
               <p>By theſe few examples in ſtede of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther innumerable, doth appere how ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actly
<pb facs="tcp:7400:56"/>practiſe of Chriſtian people hath al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes agreed with ſcripture and with reaſon for auoyding of heretikes and their conuenticles.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="4" type="chapter">
            <head>¶ Aunſweres to the chiefe obiections.</head>
            <head type="sub">¶ The fourth Chapter.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Ut let vs ſée moreo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, for the better ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſfying of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whom this former diſcourſe of reaſon, Scripture and practiſe doth not ſatiſfie what they are wont to pleade for their diſſimulation,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 140.</note> 
               <hi>ad excuſandas excuſationes in peccatis.</hi>
            </p>
            <div n="1" type="objection">
               <head>¶ The firſt Obiection.</head>
               <p>NAaman Syrus healed of his leper by Elizeus,
<note place="margin">4. Reg. 5.</note> and beléeuing nowe in one true and liuing God, deſired not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding, that whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his prince did go into the Temple of Remmon to adore, becauſe he was wont to leane
<pb facs="tcp:7400:56"/>vpon his ſhoulders, he might alſo be preſent there to doo his king that accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomed ſeruice. To whom the Prophet aunſwered: <hi>Vade in pace.</hi> Go in peace. That is (ſay they) be bolde and make no ſcruple of conſcience in that matter.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="answer">
               <head>¶ The Aunſwere.</head>
               <p>THis is a great place with noble me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that gladly would yéelde a litle to pleaſe their prince, ſo they might doo it by example of ſcripture, and the autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie of a prophet. <hi>Nam quod exemplo fit, iure fieri putatur.</hi> That which is done by ſome former exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple, is thought to be done lawfully, as the Oratour ſaith. Is thought to be lawful, not that it is alwayes lawful, becauſe the caſe may be altered. Briefly, what the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phete meant by this ſhort anſwere is not eaſily defined. Very probably this may be ſaide: firſt, that <hi>Vade in pace,</hi> Go in peace, is the common hebrewe phraſe for <hi>Vale,</hi> Fare you wel. <hi>Exo, 4. 1. Reg. 20. 2. Reg. 15. Iudith. 8.</hi> as we ſay: God ſpéede you wel. And, <hi>Gen. 29.
<pb facs="tcp:7400:57"/>Valetnè?</hi> Doth he wel? <hi>Valet.</hi> very wel. In the hebrew. <hi>An pax eſt ei?</hi> Is he in peace? <hi>Pax.</hi> In good peace. And to our Ladye the bleſſed virgin: <hi>Aue Maria.</hi> Hayle Mary. In hebrew, <hi>Pax tibi Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria.</hi> Peace be to thée Mary. And, <hi>Dicite, Pax huic domui.</hi> Say ye, Peace be to this houſe. So, that <hi>Vade in pace,</hi> is not to bid him be bolde and feare not, but to wiſh him to doo wel. And in this ſenſe the prophet did not aunſwere to his petition:
<note place="margin">4. Reg. 4.</note> why ſo? becauſe it was not reuealed vnto him ſo farre, as whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he ſaieth: <hi>Anima eius in amaritudine eſt, &amp; Dominus celauit à me.</hi> Her ſoule is in great anguiſh, and our Lord hath concealed it from me. And S. Chriſoſt. <hi>in 2. Eſa. Prophetae pro diuerſa qualita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te temporis, dum minimè adſpirare<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tur, quaſdam enunciabant inciſiones.</hi> The Prophetes as the qualitie of the time diuerſly required, whiles they were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpired with the ſpirite of God, ſo farre they vttered certaine ſentences and pée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of their prophecies. &amp;c. So that they had not at al times to aunſwere
<pb facs="tcp:7400:57"/>euery queſtio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, or to graunt al requeſts:
<note place="margin">Num. 22. &amp;. 23. 3. Reg. 22.</note> but as Baalam &amp; Micheas ſaide, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer God did put into their mouth, that they would ſpeake &amp; muſt ſpeake. But to graunt that he did anſwer him, yet it is ſo wiſely tempered, that he might neither preſume much vpon it, as flatly graunted, nor take an occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to reuolte, as flatly denied ſo ſmal a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt, as it did ſéeme to him, and was in déede in compariſon of his former Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latrye: which circumſtance with the reſt is much to be conſidered. He was but then conuerted from Idalatrye to beléeue in the true God, he might by that toleration doo much good to the conuerting of others. He requeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted onely to doo his accuſtomed ſeruice to the Prince. &amp;c. If it had béen denyed, <hi>Nouum hoc vinum veterem vtrem fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cilè rupiſſet, linum fumigans extinxiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſet. Qui nimiùm emungit, elicit ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guinem.</hi> This newe wine might eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly haue broken the olde bottel, might quickly haue put out altogether y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> towe that yet ſoultered, and was verye like
<pb facs="tcp:7400:58"/>in time to burne very cléere. He that ſtraineth to much, fetcheth bloud. And therfore they that pleade vpon this ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, muſt conceaue the caſe thus: A vehement heretike lately conuerted, much depending vpon his Lorde or Prince, and requeſting that he maye for a time attend only vpon him in the Churche, eſpecially if his ſeruice be pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culier to ſome one thing, to beare the ſworde, the maſe, the Canapie, Verge, Traine, booke. &amp;c. to ſuch a one ſo like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to Naaman, it might perhaps be ſaide in their ſenſe: <hi>Vade in pace.</hi> And, as I remember, Lira vpon that place doth ſo define. But this is pappe for in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fantes and yonge Catholikes,
<note place="margin">Hebr. 5.</note> 
                  <hi>Perfec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torum autem</hi> (ſuch as our men ought to be) <hi>eſt ſolidus cibus: corum qui pro conſuetudine exercitatos habent ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus ad diſcretionem boni &amp; mali.</hi> But for the perfect, ſtronge meate is more conuenient: for ſuch, I ſaye, which of longe cuſtome and bringing vp haue their ſenſe and vnderſtanding exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to diſcerne betwéene good and euil.
<pb facs="tcp:7400:58"/>They haue for the moſte part béene borne and brought vp in Catholike religion, they are no conuertites. If they therefore claime childrens pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiledge, you muſt aunſwere them with S. Paule. <hi>Cùm deberetis magiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tri eſſe propter tempus, rurſùm indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getis vt vos doceamini, quae ſint eleme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta exordii ſermonum dei, &amp; facti eſtis quibus lac opus ſit, no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſolido cibo. Om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis nam<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> qui lactis eſt particeps, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers eſt ſermonis iuſtitiae: paruulus nam<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> eſt.</hi> Whereas for your time you ought to be maſters and teachers, you haue néede to be taught againe your ſelues what are the principles and firſt letters of Gods wil and commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. And you are become ſuch as haue néede of pappe, rather then ſtronge meate: for whoſoeuer is a milkſopp, he is ignorant of that that ſhould make him a perfect iuſt man, for he is a very babe. Another aunſwere better then theſe is, that he meant to adore y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> true God by open proteſtation in the Idols temple. And ſo may a Catholike pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſting there, that he defieth their here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical
<pb facs="tcp:7400:59"/>ſeruice, and commeth to praye af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Catholike maner, which were to edifie rather then to geue offence. But they wil ſaye:</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="objection">
               <head>¶ The ſecond Obiection.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>TV fidem habes?
<note place="margin">Rom. 14.</note> penes teipſum ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be coram deo.</hi> Haſt thou faith? haue it to thy ſelfe before God. <hi>ergò</hi> Saint Paule geueth them leaue, yea, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundeth them to kéepe their conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to them ſelfe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="answer">
               <head>¶ The Aunſwere.</head>
               <p>IT muſt be tolde them that it is two faultes, to doo yl, and to maynteyne it as wel done by the Apoſtles authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. A great abuſe not to conſider the circumſtance of ſcriptures, but as they would wiſh it to ſignifie, ſo to expound it, as the Poet ſaith, <hi>Quod nimis mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeri volunt, hoc facilè credunt.</hi> That which poore wretches are too deſirous of, they beléeue it eaſily. The Apoſtle talketh <hi>de Idolothytis,</hi> meates offered to Idols, defining thus, that <hi>Idolum
<pb facs="tcp:7400:59"/>nihil eſt, &amp; nihil commune per ipſum,
<note place="margin">1. Cor. 8. Rom. 14. 1. Cor. 10.</note> ſed omnia munda.</hi> An Idol is nothing, and no meate is vncleane of it ſelf, but al meates are cleane, <hi>&amp; omnia licent,</hi> al meates are lawful. Al might be ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten of them that did know thus much: whom he calleth <hi>habentes ſcientiam,</hi> ſuch as haue knowledge: But becauſe there were other weaklings, not ſo wel inſtructed <hi>(non in omnibus eſt ſcientia,</hi> al haue not knowledge) y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> in conſcience thought the eating of <hi>Idolothita</hi> to be an honor to the Idol, &amp; yet did eate thereof, <hi>(quidam conſcientia vſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> nunc Idoli quaſi Idolothitum manducant, &amp; conſcientia eorum cùm ſit infirma polluitur. Qui nam<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> diſcernit, ſi man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducauerit, damnatus eſt, quia non ex fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de.</hi> Some in conſcience making euen yet ſome accompt of an Idol, eate it as idolatrous meate, and their conſcience being weake is defiled, for he that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth a difference, if he doo eate, is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned, becauſe he doth not according to his beléefe and conſcience, becauſe his faith and conſcience is, that it ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noreth the Idol, &amp; therfore they ſhould
<pb facs="tcp:7400:60"/>not eate therof.) And becauſe theſe me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> would not of them ſelues haue eaten it, but did it by the example of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, <hi>qui habebant ſcientiam &amp; fidem,</hi> that did according to their knowledge and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, and might doo it lawfully but for ſcanual to their weake brethren: therfore S. Paule willeth them alſo to abſteine, rather then cauſe the other by their example to eate alſo, and ſo to ſinne, <hi>Quia exiſtimantes eſſe commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne, &amp; comedentes, ideò peccabant.</hi> For they that thought it vncleane, and yet did eate, did therfore ſinne: wheras the others, <hi>habentes ſcientiam nihil eſſe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mune per ſe,</hi> knowing that nothing is vncleane of it ſelfe, did not offend in eating, but in geuing the weaker ſort occaſion to eate. <hi>Omnia ſunt munda, ſed malum eſt homini qui per offendi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culum manducat.</hi> Al thinges are clean, but it is yl for the ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that eateth with geuing offence &amp; ſcandal, that maketh his brother to ſinne by that meanes, whereas the thing is indifferent in it ſelfe. <hi>Eſca enim nos non commendat
<pb facs="tcp:7400:60"/>deo.</hi> Meate doth not make vs commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable. And therefore if thou be neuer the better for eating, <hi>vt quid tua liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas ab aliena conſcientia iudicatur?</hi> why doeſt thou vſe this libertie of thine, to wound thy brothers conſcience? <hi>Sic e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nim peccantes in fratres, &amp; percutien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes eorum conſcientiam infirmam, in Chriſtum peccatis.</hi> For, ſinning after that ſort againſt your brethren, and wounding their weake conſcience, you ſinne againſt Chriſte. This is the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles whole drifte <hi>de Idolothitis,</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning meates offred to Idols. Nowe to our purpoſe, wheras theſe <hi>habentes ſcientiam,</hi> that haue knowledge, did ſaye: We knowe, <hi>Omnia munda mun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dis.</hi> Al are cleane to the cleane, we haue no ſuch ſcrupuloſities, why ſhoulde we abſtaine as though we were weaklin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges? Nay, we wil eate rather to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt our knowledge and our conſcience. To this S. Paule aunſwereth: <hi>Tu fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem habes? penes teipſum habe coram deo.</hi> Haſt thou a ſtronge faith and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect knowledge in theſe thinges? it is
<pb facs="tcp:7400:61"/>enough for thée that God doth knowe that thou art none of theſe weaklings. But becauſe it is indifferent, and God doth not looke for it, nor like thée anye thing y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> better for eating, <hi>(Ne<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> nam<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ſi manducauerimus, abu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dabimus, ne<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ſi non manducauerimus, deficiemus.</hi> For neither if we eate ſhal we gaine thereby, neither if we eate not, ſhal we léeſe by it,) abſtaine from thy brothers conſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, who not hauing knowledge, thinketh that it is <hi>pollutum ex Idolo,</hi> and made vncleane by being offered to the Idol, and by thy example eateth, &amp; ſo ſinneth againſt his conſcience. If thou anſwere me, let him looke to that, what is it to me? I know it is not vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleane, and <hi>Idolum nihil eſt,</hi> that an I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dol is a thing of nothing, and therfore I eate with a ſafe conſcience. O (ſaith he) but <hi>Si quis dixerit, Hoc immolatu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſt Idolis,
<note place="margin">1. Cor. 10.</note> noli manducare propter illu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; propter conſcientiam: Conſcienti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am autem dico non tuam, ſed alterius.</hi> If any man ſhal ſay, this was offered to Idols, eate not of it for his ſake, and
<pb facs="tcp:7400:61"/>for conſcience: conſcience I ſaye not thine owne, but that other mans, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he thinketh it is vncleane and vnlawful. Otherwiſe if thou boaſt thy knowledge, to the ruine of thy weake brother, <hi>Scientia haec inflat,
<note place="margin">1. Cor. 8.</note> charitas au<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tem aedificat.</hi> This knowledge doth puffe vp and make proud, but it is cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie that edifieth: So that the Apoſtle briefly ſaith thus: In thinges indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent that may be omitted without ſin, although thou knoweſt it may lawful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye be done, yet doo it not <hi>cum ſcandalo fratris,</hi> to cauſe thy brother to fal, that is, if thy doing put him in daunger of ſinning, or make him to ſinne: for ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample. Thou knoweſt that to faſt vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon Sunday, in many caſes, is indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent before God, and therefore thou do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt often vſe it amonge other dayes. But if anye man leſſe ſkilful, liuing with thée,
<note place="margin">D. Aug. cp. 86. ad Caſulanu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note> 
                  <hi>non habens diſcretionem boni &amp; mali,</hi> hauing not iudgement to diſcerne betwéene good and euil, as Saint Paule (the Apoſtle) ſaith, be
<pb facs="tcp:7400:62"/>offended, thinking that thou doeſt fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour manichieſme, and therby him ſelf is induced to thinke their faſt lawful, or not to eate by thy example, when in his conſcience it ſéemeth vnlawful: in this caſe, <hi>Meliùs non ieiunatur die dominico,</hi> It is better not to faſt vpon the Sunday. <hi>Tu fidem habes? penes te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ipſum habe coram deo.</hi> Is it thy fayth and conſcience, that thou maieſt? wel, be it betwéene God and thée. Againe, to come néerer our purpoſe. A very lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Doctor of Diuinitie, and ſounde Catholike may lawfully come to here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical ſermons for the better confuting of them, when he hath heard their rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons: and he may alſo lawfullye be ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, ſo that to him it is indifferent. If he know other ſome of leſſe knowledge and conſtancie, that by his ſo doing thinketh he fauoureth their hereſie, or alloweth their ſayinges, or doth not greatly miſlike, or if he doo, yet that he, or any other ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> may boldly be preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, ſo that they alſo either think the better of them, or abſtaine not from them, he
<pb facs="tcp:7400:62"/>thought to refraine. So that by this caſe it appereth, that S. Paules place is to our purpoſe altogether, and cleane contrary to their purpoſe that alleage it: for the Apoſtle in things indifferent willeth vs to doo that which may not be ſcandalous to our brother. But ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther this point <hi>de vitandis haereticis,</hi> of auoyding heretikes, is indifferent, as the ſcriptures aforeſaide and examples declare: and if it were, they chooſe that which muſt néedes <hi>ſcandalizare magis,</hi> as I haue ſhewed before in the tenth reaſon: for not to come there, cannot poſſibly make any other man to ſinne. And to come there, not onely poſſiblye, but very likely and in maner certainly maketh others to ſinne by example.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="objection">
               <head>¶ The thirde Obiection.</head>
               <p>BEcauſe ſome ſcriptures and reaſons afore mentioned,
<note place="margin">Idolaters and here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tikes are to be shu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned alike.</note> literally concerne Idolatrie, they wil ſaye, it pertaineth nothing to the caſe <hi>de vitandis haereti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis,</hi> of ſhunning heretikes: for if the queſtio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> were of communicating with
<pb facs="tcp:7400:63"/>Idolatours, they would dye manye deathes rather then yéelde.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="answer">
               <head>¶ The Aunſwere.</head>
               <p>THat which they graunt (becauſe they muſt néedes) of auoyding Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latours ſacrifice and ceremonies, ſhal flatly conuince them, to auoid heretiks and their conuenticles, equally at the leaſt, and peraduenture much more. S. Hierome throughout al his commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taries vpon the Prophetes, applieth that miſtically to hereſies &amp; heretikes, which literally is ſpoken of Idols and Idolatours, vſing commonly this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face:
<note place="margin">Oſeae. 4.</note> 
                  <hi>Super hęreticos facilis interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatio eſt.</hi> The meaning of this place being referred to heretikes is very ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie,
<note place="margin">Amos. 5.</note> namely to our purpoſe, that, <hi>Nolite ingredi in Galgala. &amp;c.</hi> Enter not into Galgal in any wiſe, aboue mentioned at large.
<note place="margin">1. Ioh. 5.</note> Againe, he that ſaide: <hi>Filioli, cuſtodite vos à ſimulachris.</hi> Children, kéepe your ſelues from Idols, ſaide of an heretike,
<note place="margin">Ioh. 2.</note> 
                  <hi>Nolite recipere eum in do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum, nec Aue ei dixeritis: Quinam<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan>
                     <pb facs="tcp:7400:63"/>dicit illi, Aue, communicat operibus eius malignis.</hi> Receaue him not into your houſe, neither ſaye vnto him ſo much as God ſaue you, for he that ſo ſayeth, communicateth with his wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked workes. And he that ſaide: <hi>Fugite ab Idolorum cultura.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Cor. 10.</note> Flée from the woorſhipping of Idols, ſaide alſo of he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retikes: <hi>Declinate ab illis, hos deuita,
<note place="margin">Rom. 16. 2. Tim. 3. Tit. 3.</note> haereticum hominem poſt vnam &amp; ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cundam correptionem deuita.</hi> Turne aſide from them: And againe, Audid al ſuch: And againe, Shunne him that is an heretike, after he hath béene once or twiſe warned. And that he meaneth of whatſoeuer co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>municating and ſocietie with either of both, he declareth:
<note place="margin">2. Cor. 6.</note> 
                  <hi>Quae participatio iuſtitiae cum iniquitate? aut que ſocietas luci ad tenebras? Quae conuentio Chriſti ad Belial? aut quae pars fideli cum infideli? Qui conſenſus templo dei cum idolis? vos nam<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> eſtis templum dei viui, propter quod exite de medio eorum, &amp; ſeperamini. &amp;c.</hi> What part hath righteouſnes with iniquitie? Or, what felowſhipp is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twéene light and darkneſſe? What
<pb facs="tcp:7400:64"/>agrement betwéene Chriſt and Belial, what portion hath the faithful with the faithleſſe: howe doth the temple of God agrée with Idols? for you are the temple of the liuing God. wherefore depart from among them, and ſeperate your ſelues. Howe many wayes doth he expreſſe, that there ought to be no communicating <hi>inter fidelem &amp; infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delem,</hi> betwéene the faithful and the faithleſſe: which comprehendeth the heretike aſwel as the Idolatour. And our Sauiour him ſelfe moſt plainelye: <hi>Si eccleſiam non audierit,
<note place="margin">Mat. 18.</note> ſit tibi ſicut ethnicus.</hi> If he wil not hear y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Church, let him be to thée as an heathen: <hi>tibi,</hi> to thée, ſpeaking to his diſciples that wer Iewes. Abhorre from him as from a Gentile.
<note place="margin">Ioan. 18.</note> howe is that? <hi>Nolebant ingre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di praetorium, nè contaminarentur.</hi> They would not enter into Pilates court, who was a Heathen, leaſt they ſhould be defiled. And Cephas <hi>ſubtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hebat &amp; ſegregabat ſe à gentibus.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Galat. 2.</note> Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phas or Peter withdrewe and ſepera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted him ſelfe from the Gentiles: why?
<pb facs="tcp:7400:64"/>
                  <hi>timens eos qui ex circum ciſione erant,</hi> for feare of offending the Iewes. The Iewes abhorred nothing ſo much as a Gentile, ſo we muſt abhorre the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenticles of heretikes.
<note place="margin">Epiſt. 76. figur. 2.</note> S. Ciprian vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that place <hi>(Math. 10.) In viam gentiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> né abieritis, &amp; in Ciuitates Samarita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norum nè intraueritis.</hi> Goe not into the way of Gentiles, and enter not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Cities of Samaritanes, ſaith, that he would not haue added, of the Samaritanes, but that he made Schiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matikes equal with Gentiles. <hi>Adden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do, &amp; Ciuitates Samaritanorum debe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re omitti, oſtendit ſchiſmaticos Genti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lib us adaequari.</hi> By adding (ſaith he) that they ſhould paſſe by and leaue the Cities of Samaritanes alſo, he decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth that ſchiſmatikes and Gentiles are of equal accompt: for the Samari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tanes were ſchiſmatikes fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Iewes. And, <hi>de vnitate eccleſiae,</hi> he declareth very excellently, how hereſie &amp; ſchiſme ſuccéeded into the very place, &amp; the ſelf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſame degrée that Idolatry had before time. <hi>Chriſti aduentu proſtratus ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>micus
<pb facs="tcp:7400:65"/>vidensidola derelicta, &amp; per ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mium credentium populum ſedes ſuas ac templa deſerta, excogitauit nouam fraudem, vt ſub ipſo chriſtiani nominis titulo fallat incautos, haereſes inuenit et ſchiſmata, quibus ſubuerteret fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem, veritatem corrumperet, ſcinderet vnitatem. etc.</hi> The enemy Satan being ouerthrowen by the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming of Chriſt, ſeing Idols forſake<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and that his Sées and Temples were left deſert, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the great multitude of faithful people, he deuiſed a newe ſubtiltie, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the very title and name of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anitie to deceaue the vnwarye. He found out, I ſay, hereſies and ſchiſmes, whereby he might ouerthrowe fayth, corrupt the truth, deuide the vnitie of the Catholike Churche. S. Ambroſe to ſignifie, that they are very Infidels, ſaith:
<note place="margin">De incar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nat. cap. 2.</note> 
                  <hi>Quadam nuncupatiua fidei ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manitate, parricidialibus gladiis nos cupiunt vulnerare.</hi> With a certaine brotherly affinitie or likenes of one faith they couet to wound vs, as if one brother ſhoulde drawe his ſworde a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
<pb facs="tcp:7400:65"/>his other brethre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And praiſeth his brother Satyrus, <hi>quòd non arbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trabatur fide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſſe in ſchiſmate,</hi> becauſe he thought there was not a right &amp; per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect faith in ſchiſme, much leſſe in here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie. S. Auſten:
<note place="margin">In pſal. 88 ſub finem</note> 
                  <hi>Amemus Dominu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um noſtrum, amemus Eccleſia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eius: il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum ſicut Patrem, iſtam ſicut matrem: ſed matrimonium hoc magna charitate compaginatur: nemo offendit vnum, et promeretur altera<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: nemo dicat, ad ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la quidem vado, ſed tamen Eccleſiam dei non relinquo, Catholicus ſum: ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens matrem, offendis patrem. Alius item dicit. Abſit à me, non conſulo ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilegium, non ſeruio lapidibus, ſed ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men in parte Donati ſum. Quid tibi prodeſt non offenſus pater, qui offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus vindicat matrem?</hi> Let vs loue our Lord God, let vs loue his Church: him as a father, her as a mother. This Matrimonie is knitt together with great charitie. No man offendeth the one, &amp; hath the fauor of the other. Let no man ſay: I go to Idols in déede, but for al that I doo not forſake the Church of God, I am a Catholike ſtil, although
<pb facs="tcp:7400:66"/>thou ſticke to the mother, yet thou of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendeſt againſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Father. Some other ſaith: I aſke no councel of Southſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, (God forbid) I woorſhip no ſtockes nor ſtones, but for al that I am of Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natus ſide (a ſchiſmatike and an here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tike) what doth it auaile thée not to of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend directly againſt the father, who is offended notwithſtanding, and wil pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh the iniurie done to the mother. To committ Idolatrie he maketh a ſinne againſt God: to be in ſchiſme, a ſinne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Churche of God. Whether a man doo thone or thother, he ſaith, it offendeth God al one.</p>
               <p>Thus farre it ſéemeth the caſe is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qual,
<note place="margin">Heretikes more to be shu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ned then Pai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nims or Iewes.</note> and that they are to be ſhunned alike. Nowe, <hi>ex abundanti,</hi> to proue, that the heretike and ſchiſmatike is woorſe then the Gentile or the Iewe, and therfore to be more eſchewed, theſe may ſéeme verye plaine argumentes. S.
<note place="margin">1. Cor. 5.</note> Paule: <hi>Scripſi vobis in epiſtola, nè commiſceamini fornicariis, non vti<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> fornicariis huius mundi, aut idolis fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uientibus, ſed ſi is qui frater nomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur,
<pb facs="tcp:7400:66"/>eſt fornicarius, aut auarus. &amp;c. cum eiuſmodi nec cibum ſumere.</hi> I wrote to you in an Epiſtle, not to kéepe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany with fornicatours, I meane not the fornicatours of this world (Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dels and Gentiles) or woorſhippers of Idols: but if he that is our Chriſtian brother, be a fornicatour, or couetous, with ſuch a one that you doo not ſo much as eate and drinke. Is it not eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent that he willeth them to abſtayne from a falſe chriſtened brother, rather then from a flat Panym, and that for leſſer ſinnes then hereſie? Againe, the Church permitteth them to liue, &amp; that by the Apoſtles authoritie, <hi>Quid mihi de iis qui foris ſunt iudicare?</hi> What haue I to doo to iudge of them that are without? meaning al that were not Chriſtians: but the heretike is puni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed with death. Whether is more abhorred?
<note place="margin">Li. 6. ca. 37.</note> See the eccleſiaſtical hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of Euſebius, where Dioniſius the famous Biſhopp ſayth, that to ſuffer Martyrdome for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> auoiding of ſchiſme is more commendable then for the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>auoyding
<pb facs="tcp:7400:67"/>of Idolatry, becauſe in the one is the ſafetie of our ſoule, in the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is the ſaluation of the whole Churche. It is a notable place. And S. Auſten proueth, that ſchiſme offended God more then Idolatrye by the ſelfe-ſame reaſon, becauſe it was more grée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uouſly puniſhed, as in Chore, Dathan, and Abyron, then in Aaron, and them that woorſhipped the calfe. Againe, of the Iewes and heretikes, the ſame Doctour writeth:
<note place="margin">In pſ. 45.</note> 
                  <hi>Quòd haeretici of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendant ad lapidem iam montem fac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum, miſeriores Iudęis qui faciliùs ad lapidem tum paruum, et paulò antè abſciſſum offenderunt.</hi> Heretikes ſtu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble at the ſtone that is now growen to be a mightie hil, being more miſerable the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Iewes, who, no meruaile, if they ſtu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bled more eaſily at the ſtone as then being litle, and cutt out of the quarrye a litle before. He alludeth to Daniels prophecie of our Sauiour to be borne of the Virgin. The Iewes ſtumbled at the beginning when the Church be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ganne: but heretikes ſtumble nowe at
<pb facs="tcp:7400:67"/>it, when it filleth the whole world. If then they be woorſe then the Iewes, <hi>ergò</hi> muche more then the Panims which are Infidels onely <hi>negatiuè,</hi> ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatiuely, as S. Thomas termeth it, becauſe they haue not heard of Chriſte and his Church, according to thoſe pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces: <hi>Si non feciſſem in eis ſigna,
<note place="margin">Ioh. 15.</note> quae nemo alius fecit, peccatum non habe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent (nempè obſtinatae infidelitatis) nunc autem viderunt et oderunt.</hi> If I had not wrought among them tokens, ſuch as no other man did, they ſhoulde not haue ſinned (to witt, the ſinne of obſtinate infidelitie) but nowe they haue ſéene, and yet hate me. And, <hi>Si coeci eſſetis, non haberetis peccatum.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ioh. 9.</note> If you were blinde in déede, and had neuer heard of me, you ſhould not haue ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned of obſtinate infidelitie. <hi>Nunc verò dicitis, quia vidimus, peccatum veſtru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> manet.</hi> But nowe ye ſaye, that we ſée very wel, therefore your ſinne remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth. And therfore he ſaith:
<note place="margin">Math. 11.</note> 
                  <hi>Terrae So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domorum remiſsius erit in die iudicii quàm tibi.</hi> There ſhalbe more fauour
<pb facs="tcp:7400:68"/>Sodomites in the daye of iudgement then to thée. The greater puniſhment is alway a token of the greater ſinne, eſpecially after this life. Now it is cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, that this obſtinate infidelitie is greater in the heretike, then eyther in Iewe or Paynim.</p>
               <p>Againe, al authours of hereſies, and Catholikes peruerted by them, are A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtates, and reuolters from their firſt Chriſtian profeſſion, <hi>ergò</hi> woorſe then they that neuer profeſſed the name of Chriſt.
<note place="margin">2. Pet. 2.</note> 
                  <hi>Si refugientes coinquinationes mundi in cognitione Domini Ieſu Chriſti.</hi> If they that flye from worldly vnclennes by the knowledge of Ieſus Chriſte (as when Painims are chriſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned) <hi>hi rurſus implicati ſuperantur, fac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta ſunt eis poſteriora deteriora priori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus: melius nam<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> erat illis non cog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noſcere viam iuſtitię, quàm poſt agni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> retrorſum conuerti. &amp;c.</hi> If they, I ſay, intangled againe with them, be ſo ouercome, this later reuolt maketh them in woorſe caſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> before they firſt beléeued: for they had béen better not to
<pb facs="tcp:7400:68"/>know the way of righteouſnes, then after they knowe it to turne backe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine. And, <hi>Immundus ſpiritus egreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus de homine. &amp;c.</hi> An vncleane ſpirite being departed out of man (when by Baptiſme the ſpirite of Infidelitie and paganiſme is driuen out) <hi>non inueni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ens requiem, dicit: Reuertar in domum meam vndè exiui.</hi> Not finding anye reſt, ſaith: I wil returne into my houſe from whence I departed, and ſo with ſeuen other ſpirites woorſe then him ſelfe (to ſignifie what a heynous offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce reuolting hereſie is) reentreth, <hi>&amp; facta ſunt poſteriora illius hominis deterio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra prioribus.</hi> And the later ſtate of that man is farre woorſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> former was. If woorſe, <hi>ergò</hi> the more to be auoided.</p>
               <p>But the greateſt reaſon is, the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter daunger that enſueth of communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cating with heretikes, that beare the name of Chriſtians, then with Pai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nims which are manifeſt Iufidels, as S. Auſten deduceth of theſe ſcriptures. <hi>Si enim inimicus meus maledixiſſet mihi, abſcondiſſem me forſitan ab eo:
<note place="margin">S. Aug. in Pſal. 40.</note>
                     <pb facs="tcp:7400:69"/>tu verò notus meus, qui dulces mecum capiebas cibos, veniat mors ſuper il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>los. etc.</hi> For if mine open enemie had reuiled me, I might perhaps haue hidd me from him, but thou art my familier acquaintance, that diddeſt eate meate with me ſwéetely, let death come to ſuch. And, <hi>Homo pacis meę in quo ſperaui, magnificauit ſuper me ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plantationem.</hi> The man that ſéemed to be at peace with me, in whom I tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted, wrought mightilye to ſupplant and vndermine me. But let that one place of the ſame Doctor ſuffice for a number vppon theſe wordes: <hi>Ab his qui appropinquant mihi.</hi> From them that approche vnto me, ſhe ſaieth: <hi>Ab his qui longè ſunt à me,
<note place="margin">In pſ. 54.</note> facilis cautio eſt. Non me tàm citò fallit, qui dicit, veni Idolum adorare, multùm à me longè eſt. Chriſtianus es? Chriſtianus (inquit) ex propinquo aduerſatur, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pè eſt, redime in pace animam meam ab his qui appropinquant mihi.</hi> I can eaſtly beware of them that are farre off from me. He doth not deceaue me ſo ſoone that ſaieth: Come, woorſhipp an
<pb facs="tcp:7400:69"/>Idol, he is very farre from me, a Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile and Panime. But I ſaye to an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, art thou a Chriſtian? Yea forſooth, a Chriſtian, ſaith he. This felow ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth very néere me, he may quicklye ouerthrowe me. Redéeme and deliuer, O Lord, my ſoule from them that af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter this ſort approche, and come néere vnto me. Here it is plaine, that he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſireth to be deliuered from the heretike or ſchiſmatike, more then from the Panim or Idolatour. <hi>Ciprianus.
<note place="margin">Lib. de vni<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tate eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiae.</note> Non aperta tantùm pericula metuenda ſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, facilior cautio eſt, vbi manifeſtior for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mido eſt, plus cauendus eſt inimicus. cùm latenter obrepit. etc.</hi> Not onely open daungers are to be feared. A man may ſooner take héede, when the feare is more manifeſt. We muſt be more circumſpect for the enemie, when he créepeth towarde vs ſecretly. And ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, becauſe the caſe is like in auoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding both, or more vrgent againſt the heretike, I wil conclude this anſwere with S. Ambroſe, <hi>Ferendu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nè iſtud,
<note place="margin">Epiſt. 30.</note> vt Ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tilis ſacrificet, et Chriſtianꝓ interſit?</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:7400:70"/>Is it to be borne that a Gentile doo ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice, and a Chriſtian be preſent at it? euen ſo is it tolerable, that an heretike praye or preache, or miniſter Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes, and a Catholike to be preſent?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="objection">
               <head>¶ The fourth Obiection.</head>
               <p>IF they were Arians or the like old famous condemned heretikes, if thei did denye the Godhead of Chriſte his incarnation, or any principal article of the Créede, I would flée from them as from Infidels.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="answer">
               <head>¶ The Aunſwere.</head>
               <p>THis point is much to be conſidered, becauſe the ignorance of men is ſuch,
<note place="margin">Caluiniſts and Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theranes are as much to be abhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red as any olde con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned heretikes.</note> that they thinke it hardly to be hereſie, vnleſſe it be expreſlye againſt the Trinitie, and the articles of the Créede. Firſt therfore to this out of S. Auſten <hi>ad Iulianam viduam,</hi> to Iulian a widowe. <hi>Illud optimè nouimus, cum omnibus veſtris cultores vos eſſe &amp; fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſſe individuae Trinitatis:
<note place="margin">Epiſt. 143.</note> Sed non hinc ſolùm error humanus obrepit, vt
<pb facs="tcp:7400:70"/>aliquid ſentiatur de indiuidua Trinita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te: ſunt nam<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> &amp; alia in quibus perni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioſiſsimè erratur, ſicut hoc eſt. &amp;c.</hi> We knowe that very wel, that you and al yours are and haue béene woorſhippers of the vndeuided Trinitie: But not thereof onely créepeth in humane er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror, if a man be falſely perſuaded con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Trinitie: for there are o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther pointes alſo wherin error is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted verye daungerouſly, as this is one, he meaneth <hi>pelagianiſmum con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra gratiam dei,</hi> The hereſie of Pelagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us againſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> grace of God. It is plaine that this hereſie againſt the grace of God is againſt no article of the Créede expreſly, and yet I trowe they wil not communicate with a Pelagian: who was in his time ſo abhorred, eſpecially in our countrey, that wiſe men thinke the name of grace, ſo often in our En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh phraſe, begann to the deteſtation of his hereſie, as paſt grace, he lacketh grace, vngratious, grace and vertue make a man. &amp;c. Againe in another place: <hi>Dicent rudiores: Nonnè iſti
<pb facs="tcp:7400:71"/>quos vocatis haeretici, eandem Trinita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem confitentur, in eundem Chriſtum credunt? atqui id fecerunt antiqui hae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retici, quorum tame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> opiniones ipſa ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurditate ſua iacent.</hi> The ruder ſort wil ſay (ſuch as our ſimple Catholiks are) Theſe who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you cal heretikes, I praye you doo they not confeſſe and acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge the ſelf-ſame Trinitie that you doo, doo they not beléeue in the ſame Chriſte? yes, but ſo did very auncient and olde heretikes too, whoſe opinions notwithſtanding are come to nothing for the very abſurditie of them.
<note place="margin">Li. 2. Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nit. cap. 17</note> S. Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten hath the like place. <hi>Hoc qui cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dunt, nec tamen in catholica fide, ſed in ſchiſmate aliquo aut haereſi credu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. &amp;c.</hi> Whoſoeuer beléeueth al articles of the Créede, and is otherwiſe a ſchiſmatike or an heretike, or not in the Catholike Churche, it auayleth him nothing. And in the ende of his booke concerning he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſies, hauing reckoned vp al hereſies vnto his time, <hi>Multùm adiuuat cor fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dele noſſe quid credendum non ſit, eti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amſi diſputandi facultate id refutare
<pb facs="tcp:7400:71"/>non poſsit. Omnis ita<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> Chriſtianus Catholicusiſta non debet credere. Sed non omnis qui iſta non credit, conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quenter debet ſe Chriſtianum iam pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tare vel dicere.</hi> It doth much helpe the heart of a faithful man to know what he ought not to beléeue, although he ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not by the way of diſputation refute it. Euery good Chriſtian Catholike man therfore ought not in any caſe to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>léeue any of theſe foreſaid hereſies: but euery one that doth not beléeue theſe, may not therfore by &amp; by thinke or cal him ſelfe a good Chriſtian. Why ſo? If he condemne al olde hereſies againſt Chriſt, &amp; the Trinitie, is not that ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient? Noe, <hi>Poſſunt enim</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>&amp; haereſes aliae quae in hoc opere noſtro commemoratae non ſunt, vel eſſe.</hi> For there may be other hereſies alſo which are not me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tioned in this Treatiſe, ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther now be (which he had not hard of) <hi>vel fieri,</hi> or be coyned hereafter vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worlds end, <hi>quaru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> aliqua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> quiſquis te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuerit, Chriſtianus Catholicus no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> erit.</hi> Of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which whoſoeuer ſhal mainteine
<pb facs="tcp:7400:72"/>one, he ſhal not be a Chriſtian Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like man. Note the ſame, <hi>quarum ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam,</hi> to maintein any one error ſtub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bornly, is hereſie, eyther of thoſe opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions there named, or any that might riſe afterwarde. And becauſe it is here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, therfore the mainteyner thereof is to be auoided, euen as an Arrian, <hi>iux<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta illud, Hęreticum hominem deuita.</hi> Auoyde the man that is an heretike. Whatſoeuer his error be, as the ſelfe ſame Doctor declareth excellently for this purpoſe,
<note place="margin">De fide ad Petrum. cap. 44.</note> ſaying: <hi>Haec quadragin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta capitula fideliter crede, &amp; ſi quem contraria his dogmatizare cognoueris, tanquam peſtem fuge, &amp; tanquam hae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticum abiice. Ita nam<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> iſta quae hìc poſuimus fidei Catholicae congruunt, vt ſi quis non ſolùm omnibus, ſed etia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſingulis voluerit contraire, in eo quòd ſingulis horum contumaciter repug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nat, hęreticus, at<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ex hoc omnibus Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicis anathematizandus appareat. &amp;c.</hi> Theſe fortie articles beléeue faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, and if thou ſhalt know any man to holde contrary opinions to theſe, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoyde
<pb facs="tcp:7400:72"/>him as a plague or peſtilence, and caſt him off for an heretike: for theſe poyntes which we haue put, doo ſo agrée iumpe with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Catholike faith, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> if a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wil gain-ſay, not only al, but any one of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by it ſelf, in that he doth ſtubbornly ſtande againſt anye one of them, it is euident he is an heretike, and therefore to be abandoned and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curſed of al Catholike men.</p>
               <p>Let vs examine a litle thoſe two te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimonies. In the firſt <hi>de haereſibus</hi> he ſaith, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> he that holdeth any one of thoſe points, is no Chriſtian Catholike ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: but there you haue Iouinian condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and Aerius, whoſe hereſies our Calueniſtes mainteyne at this day, <hi>er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gò</hi> they muſt be abhorred aſwel as Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians. In the ſecond he ſaith, that he which doth not beléeue euery one of thoſe fortie articles by him rehearſed, is to be abhorred as an heretike. Reade them, and you ſhal finde that our here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tikes denye very many of them, albeit he addeth of euery one, <hi>Firmiſsimè te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne, &amp; nullatenùs dubita.</hi> Holde it for a
<pb facs="tcp:7400:73"/>moſt aſſured certaintie, and doubt in no wiſe. It is plain the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that there may growe, and dayly doo, ſundry hereſies, that are not expreſſely againſt the arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles of the Créede: Vnleſſe you wil ſaye, they are al againſt that article: <hi>Credo in Eccleſiam catholicam,</hi> in this ſenſe, I beléeue al that the Catholike Church beléeueth, and ſo there may be as many hereſies, as are verities in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Catholike faith:
<note place="margin">Quicu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> vult.</note> 
                  <hi>Quam niſi quis inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gram inuiolatam<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ſeruauerit, abſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> du bio in aeternum peribit.</hi> Which fayth vnleſſe a man doo kéepe whole &amp; with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out breache, without doubt he ſhal pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh euerlaſtingly: why? but becauſe he is an heretike.
<note place="margin">2, 2. q. 5. 3.</note> And S. Thomas conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion is wel knowe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. <hi>Qui errat in vno ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulo, de nullo fidem habet.</hi> He that er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth or beléeueth not any one article of the Catholike faith, he in very déede, to ſpeake truely and properlye, beléeueih none: becauſe the Catholike Church be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>léeueth aſwel al as one. And therfore if he did beléeue vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, he ſhould
<pb facs="tcp:7400:73"/>beléeue euery one: if that be not his ground, he beléeueth not, but foloweth fancie and his owne reaſon. For this cauſe Iconoclaſter or Image breakers are auncient heretikes, becauſe they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied that article of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> catholike Church <hi>de venerandis imaginibus,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">So Euno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mius, Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gilantius, Iouinia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus.</note> of reuere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce to be geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to Images, and are condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by the ſecond Councel of Nice, as Arius was by the firſt: they for their hereſie againſt the Church, he for his hereſie againſt the perſon of Chriſte. So that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> caſe of both hereſies is equal, of that that is flatly againſt Chriſt the head, and that that is againſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Church the bodye. Is that poſſible? yea. <hi>Qui vos ſpernit, me ſpernit.</hi> He that deſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth you, deſpiſeth me. And, <hi>Saul! Saul! quid me perſequeris?</hi> Saul, Saul, why doeſt thou perſecute me? when he did perſecute his Church. And, <hi>Ego ſum veritas</hi> (ſaith he) I am truth: as of the Church is ſaide: <hi>Firmamentum &amp; co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumna veritatis,</hi> that ſhe is the ſtay and piller of truth: <hi>ergò</hi> euery opinion
<pb facs="tcp:7400:74"/>againſt the truth, is againſt Chriſte &amp; his Churche equallye. And, <hi>Spiritus ſanctus quem mittet pater in nomine meo, ille docebit vos omnem veritate<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, quia de meo accipiet, &amp; annunciabit vobis.</hi> The holy Ghoſt, whom the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther wil ſende in my name, he ſhal teach you al truth: for he ſhal receaue of that that is mine, and declare vnto you. If Chriſte ſent the holy Ghoſt to direct the Churche into al truth from time to time <hi>(Habeo nam<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> multa di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere, ſed non poteſtis omnia portare modò.</hi> For I haue many things (ſaith he) to tel you, but preſently you cannot beare them al) whoſoeuer ſtubbornlye reſiſteth one article of the Catholike Churche,
<note place="margin">1. Ioh. 4.</note> reſiſteth Chriſte. <hi>Omnis ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritus qui ſoluit Ieſum, ex Deo non eſt.</hi> Euery ſpirite that deuideth Ieſus, is not of God. He deuideth him that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth not accompt of his body y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Church.
<note place="margin">Epheſ. 4.</note> And, <hi>Ipſe dedit quoſdam quidem Apoſtolos, quoſdam prophetas, alios verò Euangeliſtas, alios autem Paſtores &amp; Doctores, ad conſummatione<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſanc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torum,
<pb facs="tcp:7400:74"/>in aedificatione<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> corporis Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſti. &amp;c.</hi> He gaue ſome to be Apoſtles, ſome Prophetes, other ſome Euange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſtes, others Paſtors and teachers, to make vp the number of Saintes, to the edifying of the body of Chriſte. Why? <hi>Vt iam non ſcimus paruuli ſluctuan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, et circumferamur omni vento doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trinae. etc.</hi> That nowe we be no more litle ones wauering and caried about with euery blaſt of doctrine. Therfore Chriſte gaue vs Councels, Fathers, Popes, Biſhops, not to ſwarue from y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> truth: if we doo, is it not a denying of Chriſte? And therfore he ſaide: <hi>Si Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiam non audierit, ſit tibi tanquam ethnicus.</hi> If he wil not hear y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Church, eſtéeme him as an Heathen or Gentile. As much to ſay, <hi>Si me non audierit,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luc. 10.</note> If he wil not heare me: for, <hi>Qui vos au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit, me audit.</hi> He that heareth you, hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth me. And, <hi>Vbicun<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> duo vel tres congregati ſunt in nomine meo, ego ſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in medio eorum.</hi> Whereſoeuer be two or thrée gathered together in my name, I am in the middes of them. And
<pb facs="tcp:7400:75"/>wheras S. Iohn writeth of the Sama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritanes,
<note place="margin">Ioh. 4.</note> 
                  <hi>Multi crediderunt in eu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> prop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter verbum mulieris teſtimonium per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibentis.</hi> Many beléeued in him vpon the womans worde, that bare witnes, (which woman is a plaine figure of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Church) he addeth: <hi>Cùm veniſſent er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gò ad illum Samaritani, dicebant mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieri: Quia iam non propter tua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> loque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lam credimus, ipſi nam<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> audiuimus &amp; ſcimus.</hi> When the Samaritanes were come vnto him, they ſaide to the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man: Nowe we doo not beléeue vpon thy report, for our ſelues haue hearde and doo knowe. So that the teſtimonie of the Churche, and the teſtimonie of Chriſt alwayes concurre and agrée vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon al truthes.
<note place="margin">In pſa. 88.</note> And therfore S. Auſten ſaide very excellently. <hi>Matrimonium hoc magna charitate compaginatur. Nemo offendit vnum, &amp; promeretur alteram.</hi> This matrimonie is coupled with great charitie and loue. No man offendeth againſt the one, and winneth the other.
<note place="margin">Epiſt. 49.</note> And S. Ciprian. <hi>Confeſſor Chriſti nec dici, nec eſſe iam poteſt, qui
<pb facs="tcp:7400:75"/>eccleſiam Chriſti negauit. Nam cùm Paulus dicit, Erunt duo in carne vna, Sacramentum hoc magnu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in Chriſto &amp; eccleſia, quomodò poteſt eſſe cum Chriſto, qui cum ſponſa Chriſti, at<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> in eius eccleſia non eſt?</hi> He can neither be called, nor be in very déede a Confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſor of Chriſte, that hath denied the Church of Chriſt. For wheras Paule ſaith: They ſhalbe two in one fleſhe, This is a great Sacrament in Chriſt and the Church, howe can he be with Chriſte, that is not with the ſpouſe of Chriſt, and in his Church.
<note place="margin">Ad virgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metriade<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. He calleth it S. Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centii &amp; D. Anaſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſii fidem, the faith of S. Inno centius and B. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſtaſius.</note> And S. Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rome <hi>ad Damaſum</hi> of the Churche of Rome, which he alwaies maketh one with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> catholike Church. <hi>Qui tecum no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> colligit, ſpargit. Hoc eſt, qui Chriſti non eſt, Antichriſti eſt.</hi> He that gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth not with thée, ſcattereth: that is, He that is not with Chriſt, perteineth to Antichriſt. Marke. <hi>Qui cum eccleſia Romana non colligit.</hi> He that gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth not w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the Church of Rome: what is that to ſay? <hi>Qui chriſti non eſt,</hi> He that is not with Chriſt: ſée howe they runne
<pb facs="tcp:7400:76"/>ſtil together.
<note place="margin">De obitu fratris.</note> And S. Ambroſe ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of the Luciferians ſchiſmatikes onely, no heretikes, ſaith, that they had not <hi>fidem in Chriſtum,</hi> any true faith in Chriſte.
<note place="margin">Ambroſ. ibidem. Cuin Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicis, hoc eſt, cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Romana Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conueni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re. To a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree with Catholiks and to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree with the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che of Rome, is al one.</note> 
                  <hi>Quia etſi fidem erga deum tenerent, tamen erga dei eccleſiam non tenerent. Etenim cùm propter eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am Chriſtus paſſus ſit, et Chriſti cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus eccleſia ſit, non videtur ab eis ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hiberi Chriſto fides, à quibus euacua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur eius paſsio, corpus<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> Chriſti diſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hitur.</hi> Becauſe albeit toward God they kept their faith, towarde the Churche they did not kéepe it: For whereas Chriſt did ſuffer for the Churche, and the Churche is the body of Chriſte, it ſéemeth that they doo not beléeue in Chriſte, by whom his paſſion is made fruitleſſe, and the body of Chriſte diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted in péeces. And therfore he prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth his brother Satyrus excéedinglye for not communicating with them. This point is much to be conſidered of them,
<note place="margin">Euſeb. hiſt li. 6. ca. 37.</note> that eaſily abhorre ſuch as blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheme Chriſte, but thinke it is a ſmal matter, or rather knowe not what it
<pb facs="tcp:7400:76"/>is to reſiſt or diſcredite y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Church. And therfore an Arian they would abhorre perhaps, a Marcioniſt, an Ebionite, that helde hereſies directlye againſt Chriſt, not a Lutheran, a Zuinglian, a Calueniſt. &amp;c. that blaſpheme the Church. But hitherto I haue proued, that they are to be auoided alike.
<note place="margin">In pſa. 30. conc. 2.</note> Now that they are more to be ſhunned and abhorred, when S. Auſten writeth thus in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> former compariſon of Chriſt and his Church: <hi>Obſcuriùs dixerunt Prophetae de Chriſto quàm de eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>a, puto proptereà, quia videbant in ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritu, contra eccleſiam homines facturos eſſe particulas, &amp; de Chriſto non tanta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> litem habituros, de eccleſia magnas co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentiones excitaturos.</hi> The Prophetes ſpake more darkly of Chriſt then of the Church: therfore I ſuppoſe becauſe they foreſaw in ſpirit, that men would make partes againſt the Church, and that they would not ſtriue ſo bitterlye concerning Chriſt, but concerning his Church they would rayſe great trage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies. Doth he not meane, that the here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies
<pb facs="tcp:7400:77"/>againſt the Church ſhould be more perillous, then againſt the perſon of Chriſt, becauſe the prophets arme vs a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> more ſtrongly, &amp; informe vs more plainly. Again, more dau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gerous, becauſe vnder the name &amp; profeſſion of Chriſt they ſeduce the ſooner, which I handled partly in my aunſwere to the third obiection, and wil ſay more to the obiection folowing: but this one argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment muſt of force conuince. The Aria<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and other auncient heretikes, ech deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed but one article of Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> faith, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in al other pointes Catholike: theſe men, beſides y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> renewing of many olde conde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ned errors (which are wel know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en) they ſhake moſt pointes of Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Catholike religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſtanding al vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatiues, ſcoffing ſchoolmaſters, prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers of al licentious libertie, of who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> may be ſaide that which Leo magnus writeth of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Manichées,
<note place="margin">Ser. 5. de iciu. 10. m.</note> who were al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies accompted ſomwhat more then heretikes: <hi>Cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in cunctis peruerſitatibꝰ multiforme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> teneat principatu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (diabolꝰ) arce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> tame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſibi in iſtoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſtruxit inſania, &amp; latiſsima<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in eis aula<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in qua ſe exul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tantiùs
<pb facs="tcp:7400:77"/>iactaret, inuenit: vbi no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnius prauitatis ſpecie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſed omniu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſimul er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> impietatu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> mixtura<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> generaliter poſsideret. Quod enim in paganis pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phanu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, in Iudęis carnalibꝰ coecum. etc. hoc in iſtos quaſi in ſentina<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> quanda<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> omniu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſordium concretione confluxit.</hi> Whereas in al peruerſe &amp; wicked pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deuil bereth rule many waies, yet he hath built his topp towre in the madnes of theſe good felowes, and hath found in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a very large court, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in he might make mery, &amp; vaunt him ſelfe, as in whom he had poſſeſſion, not of one kind of naughtines, but a gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral mixture of al errors &amp; impieties to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether: for that which is prophane in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Gentiles, &amp; blind in the carnal Iewes, that ſame with al other filth clammed together hath runne into them like ſtreames into a ſinke. And ſurely for their life and maners,
<note place="margin">2. Tim. 3. 2. Pet. 2.</note> reade S. Paule <hi>&amp; ep. Iudae,</hi> foretelling y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> nature of la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter heretikes, you ſhal ſée y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> al concurre in ours. But I had rather proue my co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cluſion, by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> multitude of their errors.
<pb facs="tcp:7400:78"/>S. Auſten <hi>de origine animae ad Vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centium,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Li. 3. ca. 15.</note> hauing reckoned vp eleuen of his falſe articles, <hi>Haec (inquit) ſi perti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naciter ſingula defendantur, tot haereſes facere poſſunt, quot opiniones nume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantur. Quocircà conſidera quàm ſit hoc horrendum, vt omnes ſint in vno homine, quę damnabiles eſſent in ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gulis ſingulae.</hi> Theſe (ſaith he) eche one by it ſelfe, if they be ſtubbornly defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, maye make ſo many hereſies, as there be opinions in number. And ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider what a horrible thing this is, for al to be in one man, wheras eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye one in diuers men were damnable. His place aboue alleged is like to this.
<note place="margin">Ca. 44. de fide ad Pe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>trum.</note> Now if a man would ſcanne Luthers opinions and Caluines, howe manye errors ſhal he there finde in one of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that were eche one by it ſelfe damnable in diuers men, and very manye haue béene alreadie condemned in others? And therfore if Arius for one error, by their owne confeſſion ought to be ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horred, let them conſider, <hi>quàm horren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di ſunt illi,</hi> what horrible heretikes
<pb facs="tcp:7400:78"/>they are, and how much to be abando<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, in whom ſo many hereſies doo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curre, ſo many that it is very like An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt himſelf named (<hi>arnoumai</hi> I deny al) is next,
<note place="margin">Apoc. 13. de nume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro beſtiae.</note> whoſe next foreru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ners theſe are in denying al, and <hi>in omni ſeducti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>one iniquitatis</hi> (as S. Paule ſaith) <hi>iis qui pereunt,</hi> in al deceipt of iniquitie to them that periſh: for of thoſe olde ſingle hereſies it was ſaide in the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles time,
<note place="margin">2. Theſ. 2.</note> 
                  <hi>Miſterium iam operatur ini<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>quitatis.</hi> The miſterie of iniquitie doth worke, or is in woorking euen nowe, as it did in al hereſies downewarde, but <hi>tum reuelabitur filius iniquitatis, quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dò inſtat dies Domini.</hi> Then the ſonne of iniquitie ſhalbe reuealed, when the day of our Lorde is at hande: then (to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> later dayes) he ſhal come with his maine force. S. Baſil doubted in his time,
<note place="margin">Ep. 70. &amp; 71.</note> 
                  <hi>Nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eccleſias ſuas prorſus re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liquit Dominus? an nouiſsima hora eſt. &amp;c.</hi> Hath God vtterlye forſaken his Churches? Is the laſt houre come? But reade him, and you ſhal ſée that the he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retikes which he complaineth of, were
<pb facs="tcp:7400:79"/>very tolerable in reſpect of ours. So that if equal euils, are equally to be eſchewed, and the greater, the more: it foloweth, that Caluiniſtical conuenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles are as much, at the leaſt, and by al good reaſon much more to be abhorred then Arians, Pelagians. &amp;c. But be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe our queſtion is chiefly of freque<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting their praiers, vnderſtande this, that not only auncient ſchiſmatikes, of whom it is certaine, (as <hi>Donatiſtae, Luciferani</hi>) but the heretikes alſo <hi>Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ani, Macedoniani, Pelagiani,</hi> kept al ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical ſeruice and ceremonies like the Catholikes. And yet what zeal the good Chriſtians then had, not to come into the Churche where ſuch were pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, you may remember by the eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſtical examples aforeſaide.
<note place="margin">Cap. 3.</note> How much more theſe, where nothing is like, but al of purpoſe and in deſpite made vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like, not without blaſphemie, as when they ſay: From al Papiſtrie good Lord deliuer vs, meaning al Catholike reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion. May a Catholike man be preſent at this, more then a Chriſtian at the
<pb facs="tcp:7400:79"/>Iewes curſe pronounced euery day in <hi>Nazarenum &amp; Nazarenos?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Cor. 10.</note> againſt Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus of Nazareth and the Nazarenes? As they ſpeake in deſpite of Chriſt and Chriſtians, ſo our heretikes in deſpite of the Church, and Catholiks, <hi>vt pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentibꝰ loquor, vos ipſi iudicate quod dico.</hi> I ſpeake as to wiſe men, Your ſelues be Iudges of that that I ſaye.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="objection">
               <head>¶ The fift Obiection.</head>
               <p>THere be many good men of them, godly prayers, Pſalmes, Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, although ſomewhat be lacking, yet that which they haue is good, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greing with the Catholikes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="answer">
               <head>¶ The Aunſwere.</head>
               <p>MAny good men? Are they better then Angels?
<note place="margin">Gal. 1.</note> 
                  <hi>Si Angelus de coelo euangelizet vobis: Si quis vobis euan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelizauerit praeter id quod accepiſtis, Anathema ſit.</hi> If an Angel from hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen
<pb facs="tcp:7400:80"/>from heauen preache vnto you, if any whoſoeuer he be ſhal preach otherwiſe then that you haue receaued, be he ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curſed: Any man or Angel whatſoeuer he be. And becauſe many folowe their good vicar, which before ſaid Maſſe, and now preacheth the contrary for aduan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, and ſaith the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munion, S. Paule addeth of him ſelfe, <hi>licet nos.</hi> If we our ſelues, and the reſt Apoſtles come and preache contrary to that we firſt prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched, <hi>Anathema ſit.</hi> Be he accurſed. But are they gentle perſons, ſwéete men? no meruaile: <hi>Eiuſmodi pſeudoa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtoli ſunt operarij ſubdoli,
<note place="margin">2. Cor. 11.</note> tranſſigu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantes ſe in Apoſtolos Chriſti, &amp; non mirum: ipſe nam<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> Sathanas tranſfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gurat ſe in Angelum lucis. Non eſt er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go magnum ſi miniſtri eius tranſfigu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentur velut miniſtri Iuſtitiae.</hi> Suche falſe Apoſtles are craftie woorkers, tranſforming them ſelues into the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles of Chriſt, and no meruaile, for Satan him-ſelfe tranſformeth him-ſelf into an Angel of light, and therefore it is no great matter, if his miniſters be
<pb facs="tcp:7400:80"/>miſſhapen as the miniſters of Iuſtice or righteouſnes. Such common places are infinite. But <hi>Apoc. 9</hi> They are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed excellently vnder the names of Locuſtes, <hi>ſimilitudines locuſtarum ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miles equis paratis in proelium.</hi> The formes of theſe Locuſtes were like hor ſes redie to the ſkirmiſh, they are hoat and vehement. <hi>Super capita eorum tanquam coronae,</hi> Vpon their heads as it were crownes (not crownes in déed) <hi>ſimiles auro,</hi> like to golde (not golde) al their triumph and victorie in pulpets is counterfait: <hi>Facies earum tanquam facies hominum.</hi> Their faces are as it were the faces of men. They ſéeme ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye ſwéete men, <hi>&amp; habebant capillos ſicut capillos mulierum,</hi> and they had heare like to womens hear. They haue wife and children, and liue honeſtlye forſooth in wedlocke, and extol Matri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monie wonderfully, which pleaſeth maried men excéedingly. <hi>Vox alarum ſicut vox curruum equorum multoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> currentium in bellum.</hi> The voyce of their winges like the voice of manye
<pb facs="tcp:7400:81"/>chariots and horſes running to the campe (their vehemencie in pulpettes) But what foloweth? <hi>Et habebant cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das ſimiles ſcorpionum, &amp; aculei erant in caudis earum.</hi> And they had tayles like to Scorpions, and their ſtinges were in their tayles. The ende and ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect is to ſeduce men to euer laſting da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation.
<note place="margin">Rom. 16.</note> 
                  <hi>Per dulces benedictiones ſedu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cunt corda multorum.</hi> By ſwéete bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſinges they ſeduce the hearts of many.
<note place="margin">Ep. 7. vel 190.</note> S. Auſten. <hi>Ab ea (eccleſia) ſeperati, qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> diu contra illam ſentiunt, boni eſſe non poſſunt, quia etſi aliquos, corum bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nos videtur oſtendere quaſi lauda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biliter conuerſatio, malos cos ip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſa facit diuiſio, dicente Domino, Qui mecum non eſt, aduerſum me eſt.</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſeperated and deuided from the Church, as long as they haue a contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye opinion to it, they cannot be good: for although their conuerſation after a ſort laudable make a ſhewe that they are good, the very ſchiſme and diuiſion maketh them naught, according to our Lordes ſaying: He that is not with
<pb facs="tcp:7400:81"/>me, is againſt me. S. Ciprian.
<note place="margin">Epiſt. 52.</note> 
                  <hi>Quiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quis ille eſt, &amp; qualiſcun<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> eſt, Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus non eſt, qui in Chriſti eccleſia non eſt &amp;c.</hi> Whoſoeuer he be, and what maner of man ſoeuer he be, a Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he is not, that is not in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Church of Chriſt. Sée S. Auſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                  <hi>ep. 120. ca. 27. Nec tales ſunt quos facilè contemnas</hi> They ar not ſuch (ſaith he) as a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> mai make light of, they appere wonderful Saint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like. &amp;c. S. Ambroſe.
<note place="margin">Li. 3 de ſpiritu ſancto. Cap. 18.</note> 
                  <hi>Etſi multi nomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent ſe Chriſtianos, nomen vſurpant, non omnes mercedem habent. Et Cain obtulit ſacrificium, &amp; Iudas oſculum, ſed audiuit: Iuda, oſculo filium homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis tradis? hoc eſt, amoris pignore ſce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus imples, &amp; pacis inſtrumento odia<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſeris, et charitatis officio mortem irro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gas? non agnoſco nomen meum, vbi non agnoſco doctrinam meam.</hi> Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though many name them ſelues Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, and vſurpe the name, al haue not the rewarde. Caine offered Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, and Iudas a kiſſe, but he hearde theſe woordes: Iudas, doeſt thou be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traye the Sonne of man with a kiſſe?
<pb facs="tcp:7400:82"/>that is: Doeſt thou worke miſchiefe with a pledge or token of loue? and do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt thou ſowe hatred with that which is an inſtrument of peace? and by ſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blance of frendly charitie art thou au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thour of death? I acknowledge not my name, where I doo not acknowledge my doctrine. Marke how they are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared <hi>cum oſculo Iudae.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ep. 2.</note> Ignatius. <hi>Non Chriſtiani ſed Chriſtempori, qui ex nomine Chriſti quęſtum faciunt, erro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris venenum alliuentes dulcibus allo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiis. &amp;c.</hi> They are not Chriſtians, but merchants of Chriſte, that make gaine by the name of Chriſt, annoynting the poyſon of error with ſwéete wordes. Briefly, what greater ſhewe of vertue and true Chriſtianitie may be made in outwarde apperance, then if they dye willingly for Chriſtes ſake, not in a falſe opinion, but in the maintenance of a truth: as many heretikes haue in the perſecution of Pagan Emperours.
<note place="margin">Devnita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te eccleſiae</note> Of whom S. Ciprian writeth, that it nothing auaileth them, no, although they dye in the honour of Chriſte a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
<pb facs="tcp:7400:82"/>Idols. If they be ſchiſmatikes, heretikes, or out of the Church, which is S. Paules doctrine.
<note place="margin">1. Cor. 15.</note> Who preſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing al other good thinges to be in man, yet, <hi>Si charitatem non habeam,</hi> If I haue no charitie, although I woulde be burned for Gods ſake, <hi>nihil mihi prodeſt,</hi> it auaileth me nothing. He hath not charitie that is not in the vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of the Catholike Churche, as Saint Auſten doth largely declare. <hi>(Ep. 204.)
<note place="margin">Aug. 204.</note> Foris ab Eccleſia conſtitutus, &amp; ſepera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus à compage vnitatis, &amp; vinculo cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritatis, aeterno ſupplicio punireris, eti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amſi pro Chriſti nomine viuus incen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dereris: hoc eſt enim quod ait Apoſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus. Etſi tradidero corpus. &amp;c.</hi> For as concerning Fores Martirs, wherein they glory moſte as an argument of their true confeſſion, S. Auſten ſaith:
<note place="margin">Aug. in Pſal. 68.</note> 
                  <hi>Non perſecutionem pati, non teneri, non flagellari, non includi, non pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribi, non occidi laus eſt: ſed habendo cauſam bonam iſta pati, haec laus eſt: laus nam<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> eſt in cauſae bonitate, non in poenae acerbitate.</hi> It is no praiſe to
<pb facs="tcp:7400:83"/>ſuffer perſecution, to be taken, to be ſcourged, to be impriſoned, to loſe goods and landes by proclamation, to be put to death: but for hauing a good cauſe to ſuffer theſe things, that is praiſe woor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie: for praiſe conſiſteth in the goodnes of the cauſe, not in the ſharpnes of the puniſhment. But if none of theſe ſhewes may make a man bold to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate with them as good Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, how is it ſaide: <hi>Ex fructibus eoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> cognoſcetis eos.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">How here tikes are diſcerned from Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholikes. Ex fructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus, By their frui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes.</note> By their fruites you ſhal knowe them? Looke vpon their o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinions, and ſée the fruit or ſequele of them, and from what ſpirite they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>céede, and you ſhal eaſilye proue their ſpirites, <hi>An ex Deo ſint.</hi> Whether they be of God. To denye al authoritie of Councels and Fathers, to folowe their owne iudgement, ſelf-wil and wiſedome. &amp;c. Is it not the moſt certain fruit of exceſſiue pride? To preache a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt merite of Chriſtian workes, is it not the meane to neglect al goodnes, by a fooliſhe ſecuritie of faith? to make chaſtitie impoſſible, vowes vnlawful,
<pb facs="tcp:7400:83"/>and therfore to breake them: virginitie of no merite before God more then ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trimonie, no difference of meates or dayes, no faſting, &amp;c. Is it not the fruit of licentious mindes, and the redy way to riotous libertie, to Epicures bru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſhnes, to Atheiſme. &amp;c. Contrarywiſe, looke vpon al Catholike articles, euery one procéedeth from holy inſpiration, and tendeth to perfection of vertue and godlines.</p>
               <p>But they haue good praiers, pſalmes, &amp;c. S. Auſten. <hi>Quid prodeſt,
<note place="margin">In pſa. 102</note> quia hym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num cantat lingua tua, ſi ſacrilegium exhalat vita tua?</hi> What auaileth it, that thy tonge ſingeth a pſalme, if thy life breathe out ſacrilege? Al heretikes and Schiſmatikes are <hi>ſacrilegi,</hi> rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of al ſacred and holy ordinances. And, <hi>Quid prodeſt ſi domiuu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fiteris,
<note place="margin">In pſal. 88</note> Deum honoras, ipſum praedicas, fili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um eius agnoſcis. &amp;c. et blaſphemas eccleſiam eius?</hi> What doth it profite, if thou confeſſe our Lorde, honoureſt God, praiſeſt him, acknowledgeſt his Sonne, and ſo forth, and in the meane
<pb facs="tcp:7400:84"/>time doeſt blaſpheme his Church. S. Hierome. <hi>Quicquid loquuntur &amp; pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tauerint ſe in laudem dei dicere, vlula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus lu porum &amp; vaccarum inſanientiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſonitus eſt.</hi> Whatſoeuer they ſpeake and thinke that they ſay to the praiſe of God, is the howling of wolues, and the belowing noyſe of mad kine: in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpreting theſe wordes: <hi>Non clama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerunt ad me in corde ſuo, ſed vlulaba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in cubilibus ſuis.</hi> They cried not to me in their heart, but they ſhal howle in their cabbins. That which they ſing or ſay,
<note place="margin">In. 8. O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeae, &amp; in 4.</note> although it be verye good, God doth abhorre it. <hi>Nolo per os veſtrum nominis mei fieri mentionem, quod I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolorum recordatione pollutum eſt.</hi> I wil haue no mentio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> made of my name by your mouth, which is polluted by often naming of Idols. Interpreting that, <hi>Ne<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> iuraueritis, viuit Dominus.</hi> Neither ſhal you ſweare, As the Lorde liueth. <hi>Non eſt ſpecioſa laus in ore peccatoris.</hi> Praiſe is nothing ſéemly or pretious in the mouth of a ſinner. And, <hi>Hic populus labiis me honorat, cor au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem
<pb facs="tcp:7400:84"/>eorum longè eſt à me.</hi> This peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple honoreth me with their lippes, but their heart is farre from me. <hi>Non om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis qui dicit, Domine! Domine!</hi> Not euery one that ſaieth, Lorde, Lord, ſhal enter into the kingdome of heauen. Many Prophetes and virgins ſhal ſay in the later day: <hi>Domine, domine, ape<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri nobis, nonnè in nomine tuo prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tauimus, dęmonia eiecimus?</hi> Lorde, Lorde, open to vs, haue not we prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cied in thy name, and caſt out deuils? haue not we done many goodly things, and that in thy name? His anſwere is: <hi>Amen dico vobis, neſcio vos.</hi> Verily I ſay to you, I know you not: that is, <hi>No<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> probo.</hi> I doo not allowe you. Notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding al this: <hi>Diſcedite à me opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rii iniquitatis in ignem aeternum.</hi> De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part from me ye workers of wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes into euerlaſting fire. <hi>Modicu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentum totam maſſam corrumpit.</hi> A litle leuen ſpilleth al the dowe. <hi>Ad que<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> reſpiciam niſi contritum ſpiritum, &amp; trementem ſermones meos?</hi> To whom ſhal I haue a regarde, but to him that
<pb facs="tcp:7400:85"/>is of a contrite heart, and trembleth at my wordes? Otherwiſe if vertue and ſinceritie be wanting, <hi>Qui immo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lat bouem.</hi> He that offreth an oxe to me (a good thing) <hi>quaſi qui interficiat ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minem,</hi> euen as he that killeth a man. he pleaſeth me no better.
<note place="margin">Eſay. 66.</note> 
                  <hi>Qui mactat pecus, quaſi qui excerebrat canem. Qui offert oblationem, quaſi qui ſanguine<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſuillum offerat. Qui recordatur thu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris, quaſi qui benedicat idolum.</hi> He that doth ſacrifice a ſhéepe, is al one with him that knocketh out the braines of a dogge. He that offereth cake-bread, as if one ſhould offer ſwines bloud. He that burneth frankincenſe, and he that bleſſeth an Idol, both pleaſe me alike. A goodly place to proue, that God doth abhorre heretikes praiſe, be their wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des neuer ſo gaie, their prayers, their preachinges, as much as if they ſhould ſpeake blaſphemie.
<note place="margin">Pſal. 49.</note> 
                  <hi>Quare tu enarras iuſtitias meas, &amp; aſſumis teſtamentum meum per os tuum?</hi> Why doeſt thou preach of my iuſtice, and takeſt my te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament through thy mouth? If thou
<pb facs="tcp:7400:85"/>ſaweſt a thiefe, thou diddeſt runn with him. &amp;c. Peter for ſaying, <hi>Tues Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtus filiꝰ dei viui,</hi> Thou art Chriſt the ſonn of the liuing God, was made head of the Church. And, <hi>Beatus es Simon bar-iona.</hi> Bleſſed art thou Simo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſonne of Iona: but when the wicked ſpirite ſaideeuen as much in the ſame words, he was rebuked and commaunded to hold his peace. In like maner, although their prayers and ſeruice were al one with ours, (as it is in déede cleane con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary) yet they in opinion and other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe being not Catholike, al is nothing woorth. Ignatius.
<note place="margin">Epiſta.</note> 
                  <hi>Nemo bonum dixe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, qui bonum malo admiſcet.</hi> No ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> can cal him good, that mingleth good with that which is naught. S.
<note place="margin">In pſa. 54.</note> Auſten of the Donatiſtes &amp; Catholikes, <hi>vnum alleluia reſonamus,</hi> we ſing one Allelu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ia, &amp; many other thinges he reckoneth, wherin they agrée: but becauſe they wer ſchiſmatiks out of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Church, it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaileth not. And <hi>ſuper illud pſ.
<note place="margin">Pſal. 54.</note> In mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis erant mecum.</hi> In many things they were with me, he reckoneth vp many
<pb facs="tcp:7400:86"/>Sacramentes and ceremonies, <hi>in qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus omnibus</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>erant mecum, ſed non omninò mecum: in ſchiſmate, non mecum: in haereſi, non mecum. Sed in hiis paucis, in quibus non mecu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, non proſunt eis multa, in quibus mecu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> In al the which thinges they agreed with me, but not with me altogether: in ſchiſme, not with me: in hereſie, not with me. And for theſe fewe wherein they are not with me, thoſe many doo nothing auaile them, wherein they are with me. So Luther of the Zuingli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans (whom I alleage <hi>non ad authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatem, ſed ad confuſionem noſtrorum Catholicorum.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Cop. dial. 6. cap. 15.</note> Not for his authoritie, but that our Catholikes may be aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to ſée the heretikes iudgement in this point) (better then theirs) <hi>fruſtrà illi in deum Patrem, &amp; filium, &amp; ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum ſanctum, &amp; Chriſtum ſeruatorem credunt, omnia (inquam) haec nihil illis proſunt quandò hunc vnum negant articulum, eum<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> falſi inſimulant, dum de Sacramento Chriſtus ait, Hoc eſt corpus meum.</hi> They in vaine beléeue in God the Father, and the Sonne, and
<pb facs="tcp:7400:86"/>the holy Ghoſt, and Chriſt our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, al this, I ſay, doth auaile them no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing. Wheras they denie this one ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle and accuſe it as falſe,
<note place="margin">De fide cap. 1.</note> when Chriſt ſaith of the Sacrament, This is my body. S. Ambroſe. <hi>Vinci illi vel facilè poſſunt, vel facilè vitari, quorum pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma propoſitione omne conſilium pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toris proditur. At verò hi quibus mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta nobiſcum paria ſunt, facilè poſſunt innoxias mentes &amp; ſoli Deo deditas, fraudulenta ſocietate percutere, dum maloru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſuorum virus per bona noſtra defendunt. Nihil enim periculoſius his haereticis eſſe poteſt. &amp;c. vndè vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menter nobis cauendum eſt, nè ſe vel ſenſibus vel auribus noſtris huiuſmodi aliquid latenter inſinuet, quia nihil tàm cogit in mortem, quàm ſub obtentu fidei fidem violare.</hi> They may eyther be ouercome eaſily, or eaſily auoyded, by whoſe firſt propoſition or ſentence al the purpoſe of their heart is diſclo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed: but they that haue many thinges equal with vs, may eaſily by falſe fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhipp wounde ſimple ſoules that thinke no harme, and are geuen onely
<pb facs="tcp:7400:87"/>to pleaſe God, whiles they defende the poyſon of their owne euil by ſuch good thinges as they borowe of vs: for no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing can be more perillous then ſuch heretikes. Whervpon we muſt be ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry circumſpect, that no ſuch thing en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in ſecretly and ſwéetly into our ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes or eares, for nothing doth driue a man ſo forcibly to death, as vnder the colour of faith to deſtroy fayth, or by ſéeming a good Chriſtian man to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuade hereſie. Let vs therfore ſay with Dauid. <hi>Cum hominibus operantibus iniquitatem, non communicabo cum electis eorum.</hi> With men that woorke iniquitie, I wil not communicate with their choſen brethren. I wil neither make nor meddle with them that ſéem the beſt of them, and moſt ſanctiſh or Angelical. <hi>Oleum peccatoris non im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinguet caput meum.</hi> Their ſwéet oy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led words ſhal not drop vpon my head.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="objection">
               <head>¶ The ſixt Obiection.</head>
               <p>TO come to their praiers onely ſée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth
<pb facs="tcp:7400:87"/>a ſmal thing, and to forſake Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentes, wife, children. &amp;c. is very much. And therfore, if preſence onely wil ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe the matter, it ſéemeth more expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient to yéelde.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="answer">
               <head>¶ The Aunſwere.</head>
               <p>HEre be two pointes, thone, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther leſſer pointes of religion may be neglected, preſuppoſing them to be litle or leſſe: thother, howe farre we may be affected toward fleſh and bloud, when they hinder faith and religion. To the firſt: The truth is, it is no ſmal point: For if Catholike Chriſtians haue alwaies auoided the company of heretikes in euery place, and in euery thing, by the Apoſtles co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundement, if the Catholike ſeruice, not only of an heretike, but of a ſchiſmatike. &amp;c. as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore appereth by my examples &amp; ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, is it a ſmal matter to frequent their conuenticles in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Church, whoſe ſeruice, Sermons, miniſtration of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramentes are as heretical, as them ſelues are in moſt articles heretikes?
<pb facs="tcp:7400:88"/>But preſuppoſing it to be ſo, let vs con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider of leſſer pointes generally.
<note place="margin">De men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dac. cap. 13</note> If a man ſhould tel you out of S. Auſten that we ought rather to dye then to make a venial lye, or to diſſemble ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nially againſt the truth, you woulde wonder. Wel, let that be perfection ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then neceſſitie. This is certaine, the leſſer the thing is for the which we ſuſteine perſecution,
<note place="margin">D. Greg. in reſp. ad in terrogati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ones Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtini Angloru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Apoſtoli.</note> 
                  <hi>propter iuſtitiam,</hi> for righteouſnes, the more heroical and meritorious the fact is, S. Iohn Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſt for telling Herode of his vnlawful wife (it is a ſmal thing in reſpect of death to holde ones peace.) S. Laurence for the Church goodes to the poore. Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nye for not deliuering Church-bookes,
<note place="margin">See Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſtome in Babila, that a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lat ought to dye for the leaſt point of eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cal priui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and prieſtly authoritie Contra Fauſtum li. 19. ca. 14</note> Bibles, ornamentes in the time of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ocleſian. Chriſoſtome for rebuking the pride of Eudoxia the Empreſſe. Babi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>las before him for excommunicating the Emperour a murderer. Not as though theſe were ſmal thinges, but many ſo eſtéeme them, and thinke it were better to yéelde, or at the leaſt not meddle, then to deale in them. S. Auſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <pb facs="tcp:7400:88"/>hauing amplified the glorious martir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Eleazarus and the Machabées before the time of grace, for refuſing ſwines fleſhe, not the greateſt point of their lawe, declareth howe more neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarye it is that we ſuſtaine any death <hi>pro Euchariſtia, pro Baptiſmo:</hi> for the bleſſed Sacrament, for Baptiſme, for any other article of the newe lawe. As for Images onely, accompted a ſmal point among cold Catholikes, howe many of al eſtates, prelates, nobles, ſuffered either death or baniſhment in the time of ſeuen Emperours that wer Imagebreakers? They conſidered that <hi>Quicun<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> totam lege<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> obſeruauerit,
<note place="margin">Iacob. 2.</note> of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendit autem in vno, factus eſt omniu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> reus.</hi> Whoſoeuer kéepeth al the law be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, and offendeth in one point, he is made giltie of al. They remembred that ſhe was the true mother, which would haue the whole child, or no part thereof, abhorring from the diuiſion of it. He that wil dye for the bleſſed Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, and wil not for purgatorie or indulgences, diuideth Chriſte, and the
<pb facs="tcp:7400:89"/>lawe of his Church. He that maintey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth al Catholike articles to death, and yet boldly communicateth with here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tikes, he is content to be halfe a Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like, and deuideth the childe. But reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber what our Salomon threatneth by his ſeruaunt Iohn. <hi>Noui opera tua, &amp; fidem, &amp; charitatem, &amp; patientiam.</hi> I knowe thy workes and faith,
<note place="margin">Apoc. 2.</note> and cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, and patience, and many other good thinges, <hi>ſed habeo aduerſus te pauca, quia permittis mulierem Iezabel</hi> (he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſie and heretical conuenticles) <hi>ſedu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere ſeruos meos. &amp;c. Ecce mittam eam in lectum,</hi> to ſeduce my ſeruantes. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde, I wil caſt her into a bed (hel fire) <hi>&amp; qui moechantur cum ca, in perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione maxima erunt.</hi> And they that play the harlottes with her, ſhalbe in very great tribulation, they that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate with her.
<note place="margin">Cap. 3.</note> And, <hi>Eſto vigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lans, &amp; confirma coetera quae moritura erant.</hi> Watche wel, and ſtrengthen o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thinges, which were like to dye, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther pointes which procure eternal death, for lacke of zeale and perfection. <hi>Non enim inuenio opera tua plena co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram
<pb facs="tcp:7400:89"/>deo meo.</hi> For I doo not finde thy workes ful before my God. <hi>Sed habes pauca nomina, qui non inquinauerunt veſtimenta ſua.</hi> Howbeit thou haſt a fewe names which haue not defiled their garmentes, haue not by commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicating polluted them ſelues.
<note place="margin">Li. 4. ca. 17 Math. 5. Quicu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ſolucrit v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num de mandatis iſtis mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mis, mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus voca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitur in regno coe lorum. Whoſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth one of theſe leaſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements, shalbe cal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>led the leaſt in the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of heauen.</note> 
                  <hi>Et am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulabunt mecum in albis quia digni ſunt.</hi> And they ſhal walke with me in white, becauſe they are woorthy: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they haue not omitted any litle point of my pleaſure. Such a Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pion was S. Baſil, of whom Theodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retus writeth thus: <hi>Cùm Praefectus (Valentis Imp. Ariani Modeſtus) Coe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaream veniſlet, Baſilium magnum ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerſitum honorificè excipit, hortatur vt cedat tempori, &amp; ne propter nimis curioſam dogmatum obſeruationem, ea<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> paruò aeſtimanda<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, tot tantas<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan>, ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſias prodat, pollicetur ſe Imperatoris amicitia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ei conciliaturu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. &amp;c. Cui diuinꝰ ille vir: Pueris quidem haec (inquit) ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uenit: At qui ſunt in ſacris literis educati, ne vna<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> quide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſillaba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> diuinoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> dogmatu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> prodi ſinunt, ſed pro iſtorum defenſione, ſi opus ſit, nullu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> non mortis
<pb facs="tcp:7400:90"/>genus libenter amplectuntur.
<note place="margin">Mat 5. Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta vnu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> aut vnus apex non prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teribit. One lote, or one ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle shal not paſſe.</note> Quod au<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tem ad Imperatoris amicitiam attinet, eam cum pietate iunctam magni aeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo: ſed ſi ea careat, pernitioſum eſſe di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>co. Ac cùm praefectus diceret eum ame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem eſſe, me (inquit) hanc ſemper ame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiam opto habere.</hi> When the Liefte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of Valens the Arian Emperour Modeſtus, came to Ceſarea, he ſendeth for Baſil the great, interteineth him honorably, erhorteth him to yéelde to the time, and not to diſquiet ſo manye and ſo great Churches, for an ouercu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious preciſenes in opinions, and that litle to be accompted of, he promiſeth him to procure him the Emperours fauour. To whom that man of God aunſwered: This talke, in good ſoothe, would doo wel to childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but they that are brought vp in holy Scriptures, and ſacred writings, cannot abide that one ſillable of any diuine article be betray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed or neglected, but for defence of them, if néede be, wil willingly embrace any kinde of death. And as for the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours frendſhipp, if it be ioyned with
<pb facs="tcp:7400:90"/>godlines, I eſtéeme it greatly: if not, I ſay it is pernitious &amp; hurtful. Nowe whereas the Lieftenant ſaide he was madd, and not wel aduiſed, I wiſhe (quoth he) to haue this madnes al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies. Marke, <hi>Ne vnam quidem ſilla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bam,</hi> Not ſo much as one ſillable, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the Emperour, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though he was accompted a mad man for it, as nowe a dayes they are that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt in litle pointes. Againe, how wary were the Catholikes in not graunting any one worde, no not one letter, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though of it ſelfe indifferent: but that might be wreſted to hereſie, as <hi>omoiou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion</hi> of a like ſubſtance, to the Arrians for <hi>omousion,</hi> and <hi>tres hypoſtaſes,</hi> for <hi>tres perſonas</hi> in S. Hierome, which he cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth <hi>Litum melle gladium.</hi> A ſword an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noynted with honey. <hi>Chrisotocos,</hi> the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of Chriſt to the Neſtorians. Why ſo? S. Ambroſe, <hi>In cauſa Dei,
<note place="margin">Li 2. offic. cap. 17.</note> vbi com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munionis periculum eſt, etiam diſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulare peccatum eſt no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> leue.</hi> In Gods cauſe, when there is daunger of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municating, when we may be thought
<pb facs="tcp:7400:91"/>to take part with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, or may in déede be induced to conſent after a ſort to their errors, in that caſe to diſſemble or yéelde neuer ſo litle is no litle ſinne, which is a leſſon for vs to abhorre fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> any one thing that the heretike would gladly obtaine of vs, be it neuer ſo li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, as to come to Church onely: yea, I know them to whom was ſaide of the greateſt Potentates, doo but ſaye you wil come to Church: which ſome Elea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zarus would neuer haue ſaide: but they did ſinfully yéeld ſo farre, which would neuer haue yéelded, I thinke, if the he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retike had not tempered his deceipt to the leaſt requeſt that maye be in that kinde: to whom it is al one, whether they doo, or ſéeme to doo, when other ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant people thinke they doo and may be tolde, that ſuch and ſuch promiſed to doo. Which ſéeming onely, what a ſinn it is, ſée the eight and tenth reaſon out of S. Ciprian, S. Auſten, and the example of Eleazarus.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="chapter">
            <pb facs="tcp:7400:91"/>
            <head>¶ Of carnal affection to wife and children.</head>
            <p>THe ſcriptures are ful to the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye in Gods cauſe. <hi>Qui amat patre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, matrem, vxorem. &amp;c. pluſquam me, no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſt me dignus.</hi> He that loueth father, mother, wife. &amp;c. more then me, is not woorthy of me.
<note place="margin">Marc. 9.</note> 
               <hi>Si oculus tuus ſcandali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zat te, eiice eum: ſi manus dextera, am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puta eam.</hi> If thine eye offende theée, caſt him out: if thy right hande, cutt it off, better it is to go alone to heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, <hi>vnum oculum habentem,</hi> hauing but one eye, then with thy wife or childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> into hel. The rewarde of the contrary is this. <hi>Qui reliquerit vxorem, vel liberos. etc.
<note place="margin">Math. 19.</note> propter nomen meum, centuplum ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipiet, et vitam aeternam poſsidebit.</hi> He that ſhal forſake wife or children. &amp;c. for my name, ſhal receaue a hundred folde, and poſſeſſe euerlaſting life. Is this a hard caſe?
<note place="margin">Math. 10.</note> 
               <hi>Putatis</hi> (ſaith Chriſt) <hi>quòd pacem veni mittere? non, dico vobis, ſed bellu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: Veni enim ſeperare fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> à patre ſuo, et nurum à ſocra ſua. etc.
<pb facs="tcp:7400:92"/>mici homines domeſtici eius.</hi> Thinke you that I came to ſende peace? No, I tel you truth, but warre: for I came to ſeperate the ſonne from his Father, and the daughter in lawe from her mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in lawe. &amp;c. The enemies of a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> are they of his owne houſholde: not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe Chriſt is the cauſe of this diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but becauſe this enſued of his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, whiles one foloweth him, &amp; the other doth not: thone is a Catholike, thother an heretike: one zealous to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake al, thother wil kéepe al to forſake God.
<note place="margin">Deut. 13.</note> And therefore in the olde lawe it is commaunded: <hi>Si ſurrexerit pſeudo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>propheta, &amp; dixerit: Veni, ſeruiamus diis alienis. &amp;c.</hi> If there riſe a falſe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher, and ſay: Come, let vs go ſerue or woorſhipp ſtraunge Gods, (that is, al falſe doctrine and error,) caſt thou the firſt ſtone vpon that perſon, albeit he be thy father, thy brother, thy ſiſter, thy wife, <hi>quae dormit in ſinu tuo,</hi> that ſlée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth in thy boſome.
<note place="margin">Deut. 33.</note> And, <hi>Qui dixerit patri ſuo &amp; matri ſuae, neſcio vos, hic eſt qui facit voluntate<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> meam.</hi> He that
<pb facs="tcp:7400:92"/>ſhal ſay in this caſe to his father, and to his mother, I knowe you not: he it is that doth my wil.
<note place="margin">Luc. 4.</note> 
               <hi>Qui non odit pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trem ſuum &amp; matrem. &amp;c.</hi> He that ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth not his father and mother, is not my Diſciple.
<note place="margin">Epiſt. ad Heliodor.</note> S. Hierome not in the caſe of auoyding ſinne, but of ſéeking greater perfection, ſaith: <hi>Licet paruu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus ex collo pendeat nepos,
<note place="margin">Sir Tho. More to his daugh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garet.</note> licet vbera quibus ne nutrierat mater oſtendat, li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cet in limine pater iaceat, per calcatum perge patrem, ſiccis oculis ad vexillum crucis euola. Solum pietatis genus eſt, in hac re eſſe crudelem.</hi> Although thy litle nephewe hange about thy necke, although thy mother ſhewe the breſtes wherwith ſhe gaue thée ſucke, althogh thy father lye croſſe thy way in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> doore, treade ouer him and go forward, melte not once at the matter, but flée couragi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly to the banner of the Croſſe. This is the onely caſe, wherein crudelitie is religious godlines. This is to be done, if our frendes would ſtay vs from en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tring religion, much more in the caſe of profeſſing our faith. Where thoſe
<pb facs="tcp:7400:93"/>ſarings haue place, <hi>Sine mortuos ſepe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lire mortuos ſuos.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luc. 9.</note> Suffer y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> dead to bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye their dead, to him that would bury his father firſt, and afterward folowe Chriſte.
<note place="margin">Math. 23.</note> Againe, <hi>Nolite vocare vobis patrem in terris: vnus eſt enim pater veſter qui in coelis eſt.</hi> Cal ne man fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vpon earth, for you haue but one father, him that is in heauen. If your earthly father be againſt your heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye, then <hi>Vnus ſit pater veſter qui in coelis eſt.</hi> Let he onely be your Father that is in heauen: otherwiſe, ſée the daunger, and the conſequence of carnal perſuaſions procéeding from vnfrend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye frendes in S. Auſten.
<note place="margin">In pſa. 48</note> 
               <hi>Quid eis fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerunt tentationes ſoeuientium?</hi> What did the temptations of them that dealt ſeuerely preuaile with them? Nothing in compariſon. <hi>Maiorem violentiam habuerunt oculi flentiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſuorum, quàm perſecutiones inſectantiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Quàm mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tos etram tenebant filij nè paterentur? quàm multoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> genibus prouolueban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur vxores. etc?</hi> The eyes of their wée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping frendes had more force and vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence,
<pb facs="tcp:7400:93"/>the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the perſecutions of the hang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men. How many did the children holde backe from ſuffering? how many were there, at whoſe knées their wiues caſt themſelues to that purpoſe? And, <hi>quàm multi volebant eſſe Catholici manifeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta veritate coniuncti,
<note place="margin">Epiſt. 48.</note> et offenſionem ſuorum reuerendo, quotidiè differe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bant?</hi> How many would gladly be Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholikes being conuicted by manifeſt truth, and differred it dayly, fearing the diſpleaſure of their frendes. To whom al true Catholikes muſt ſay, as Chriſte to Peter, who for vnſkilful loue to his maſter, would haue hindred the redemptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the world. <hi>Vade poſt me Satana, ſcandalo mihi es, non ſapis ea quae ſunt dei.</hi> Come behinde me Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan, thou art a blocke in my way, thou haſt no ſauour or féeling of thoſe thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges that God would haue. This is to be ſaide, if he perſuade vs to ſubſcribe, to take the othe, to receaue, to come to their conuenticles, that we maye be ſounde Catholikes, that we may ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther offende in hearing, nor in ſeing
<pb facs="tcp:7400:94"/>that which we ought not, as it is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in the prayſe of Lot.
<note place="margin">2. Pet. 2.</note> 
               <hi>Aſpectu enim et auditu iuſtus erat.</hi> For he was a iuſt man both for ſight and for hearing. Which I beſéeche almightie God to graunt vnto vs, who wil vndoubtedly wel reward vs for it: for litle, ſhort, and worldly diſcommodities, vnſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able ioyes, euerlaſting bliſſe, hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen it ſelfe and the holy Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie, to which be al glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye for euer.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="intrusive_page">
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:7400:94" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <gap reason="intruder" resp="#UOM" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page inserted from a different book〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
